<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<!--
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/xsl" href="../xsl/rymer.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/css" href="../style.css" alternate="yes"?>
-->
<TEI>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>About the James Malcolm Rymer Archive</title>
            <author>James Malcolm Rymer</author>
            <editor>Rebecca Nesvet</editor>
            <editor>Rae X. Yan</editor>
            <editor type="technical">Adam McCune</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Rebecca Nesvet</publisher>
            <publisher>Rae X. Yan</publisher>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <idno>context</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct xml:id="about">
               <analytic>
                  <author>Rebecca Nesvet</author>
                  <author>Rae X. Yan</author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="2015"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <!-- Information about the encoding of the text -->
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Information about the project itself (goals, organization, activities)</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Information about how the texts in a collection were chosen or excerpted</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="unknown">
               <p>Information about treatment of errors in the source (silently corrected, etc.)</p>
            </correction>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Information about normalization practices (e.g. treatment of roman numerals,
                  spelling, etc.)</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation form="std">
               <p>Information about treatment of quotations (preservation of original quotation
                  marks, etc.)</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="hard">
               <p>Treatment of the hyphenation of the source</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Information about whether and how the text has been segmented (mostly for
                  linguistic purposes)</p>
            </segmentation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Information about any interpretive information added to the text</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="frontmatter">
            <head xml:id="collection_disclaimer">Disclaimer</head>
            <p>This collection is a work in progress and, as such, subject to continual
               modification, evolution, and revision. Please pardon instances where information or
               content is missing as we continue to build out our collection. </p>
            <head xml:id="collection_mission">Mission Statement</head>
            <p>A prolific author of 'penny bloods' and ‘dreadfuls’, James Malcolm Rymer is credited
               with inventing the enduring pseudo-historical villain Sweeney Todd. Rymer also made
               major interventions in British fictional representations of nautical life and
               Victorian transoceanic imperialism. The James Malcolm Rymer Collection aims to
               recover this influential and engaging author's attributed texts and the genre of the
               'penny blood' for scholarly and general readers. To these ends, the Collection will
               consist of open access, intellectually accessible digital editions of selected
               fiction by and/or attributed to James Malcolm Rymer (1814-1884). These editions will
               be published at <a href="http://www.priceonepenny.info/">Price One Penny
               Editions</a>. The Collection will reveal Rymer's surprisingly nuanced writing's
               subtexts, historical contexts, and potential modern applications. Along with the <a
                  href="http://www.priceonepenny.info/">Price One Penny</a> edition of <a
                  href="http://www.priceonepenny.info/editions/Inquisition_static/index.html">The
                  Mysteries of the Inquisition</a>, the James Malcolm Rymer Collection will serve
               editors of succeeding <a href="http://www.priceonepenny.info/">Price One Penny
                  Editions</a> as an exemplar. It also aims to showcase new approaches and the
               application of best practices in digital documentary editing of illustrated fiction
               and serials. </p>
            <head xml:id="collection_selection">Selection Statement</head>
            <p> The collection will consist of:</p>
            <ol>
               <li>critical editions of penny fiction composed by or attributed to James Malcolm
                  Rymer,</li>
               <li>diplomatic transcriptions and facsimiles of any holograph manuscripts composed by
                  Rymer,</li>
               <li>and transcriptions of archival materials, photographic reproductions of images,
                  and original digital visualizations, including maps, that help to contextualize
                  Rymer's fiction.</li>
            </ol>
            <p>In particular, texts attributed to Rymer that prove to have been composed in whole or
               part by others will be included for the light they might shed on the development of
               Rymer's image and the penny 'blood' genre. Selections in the fiction genre will
               appear as diplomatic transcriptions, with versioning to reveal the texts' evolution.
               Engravings and 'gutter advertisements' will appear in photographic facsimiles. When
               extant and available to the editors for reproduction online, illustrated wrappers,
               detached illustrated inserts, and colored versions of engravings will also be
               provided as photographic facsimiles. </p>
            <head xml:id="collection_annotation">Annotation Statement</head>
            <p> Identifications will consist of document-centered notes and XML tags, created in
               conformity with TEI-5 guidelines. They will appear as marginal notes or pop-ups.
               These notes will refer to the prosopography, which will be compiled in accordance
               with TEI-5 standards. Annotations may include permalinks to open access material.
               Proprietary material will not be hyperlinked. </p>
            <p> Place tags will in future include geo-coordinates for historical places that exist
               at the time of tagging. Fictional places with historical street addresses or
               geo-locations will likewise be identified as such. Fictional places with vast or
               vaguely defined locations will be identified as such, and the geo-coordinates
               conjectured as accurately as possible. </p>
            <p> Annotators will strive for objectivity, political neutrality, and accessibility. To
               these ends: Historical persons' identifications will derive when possible from the
               Encyclopaedia Britannica and/or the Oxford Dictionary of National Biography. When
               this is not possible, identifications will derive from appropriate scholarly sources. </p>
            <p> Where an annotation will likely function as a plot spoiler, this will be noted and
               the reader prompted to accede or refuse to continue to the relevant part of the note. </p>
            <p> Citations will follow the TEI-5. </p>
            <p> Authors of annotations will be credited as "annotators" using their discrete XML
               IDs. It is particularly important to recognize the original, scholarly contributions
               of student annotators. Where such annotators work in teams, the team will be credited
               using both XML IDs. </p>
            <head xml:id="collection_transcription">Transcription Statement</head>
            <p>Published fiction will be diplomatically transcribed in XML. It will be tagged and
               annotated in accordance with TEI-5 guidelines. Multiple editions will be represented
               as versions. Where an open-access photographic facsimile or a text or part thereof
               exists with a stable URL, the stable URL will be hyperlinked. Silent amendation will
               standardize spacing by removing extraneous and distracting overuse of white space.
               Nonstandard spelling and obsolete language will be retained. Most typos will be
               identified as such in notes. However, the editors will correct rare typographical
               errors that could distort meaning, such as the substitution of a roman numeral VI for
               IV. Such corrections will be explained in notes. </p>
            <p>Contextualizing manuscripts will be transcribed diplomatically and encoded in keeping
               with TEI-5 guidelines. Where manuscripts can be legibly reproduced in photographic
               facsimile and rights for open access publication may be obtained, they will be.
               Transcriptions of engravings will be stored as metadata, and will represent plate
               number (if any), page number (if any), caption (if any), and any legible text
               inscribed within the image. This text will be encoded in keeping with TEI-5
               guidelines. </p>
            <p>In keeping with the MLA Guidelines for Editors of Scholarly Editions: </p>
            <ol>
               <li>all transcriptions will be fully compared by an editor (at present. Rebecca
                  Nesvet or Rae Yan) with the original documents, as distinct from a photocopy of
                  those documents;</li>
               <li> Someone other than the original transcriber will carry out a thorough and
                  complete check of each transcription, whether against the original or a photocopy
                  of the original;</li>
               <li>Transcriptions will be sampled by an editor for accuracy, and the results of that
                  sampling included in a published note.</li>
            </ol>
            <head xml:id="collection_tagging">Tagging Policy</head>
            <p>Generally, tagging of prose fiction will follow the TEI-5 guidelines, with a few
               exceptions and clarifications. These include identifying words in British dialects
               (i.e., Hibernian English, Scots Gaelic) as foreign words. This is necessary firstly
               because the dialect in THE SEPOYS tends to conform to the TEI definition of foreign
               language ("belonging to some language other than that of the surrounding text"), and
               secondly, so as not to imply a racist distinction between British and non-British
               languages other than 'Home Counties' English. Language XML IDs derive from the IANA
               Registry.</p>
            <p>Honorifics for particular characters may be added to character XML IDs as additional
               names, using the "addName" tag, but will not be tagged inline. Glosses will derive
               etymological and historical usage information, when possible, from the Oxford English
               Dictionary.</p>
            <head xml:id="collection_imagemetadata">Image Metadata Policy</head>
            <p>Image metadata will conform to the CDWA template endorsed by the College Art
               Association, but will include additional categories as appropriate: <ol>
                  <li> Where the composition includes a clock with readable time, this will be
                     indicated in the metadata. Where the clock and other context allows the exact
                     time of day (AM or PM) to be determined, this time will be indicated using the
                     military/European time format. Time zones will not be specified because in the
                     1840s, they had not been standardized globally. </li>
                  <li>Metadata will also identify characters and locations using person and place
                     name tags </li>
                  <li>Metadata will indicate whether an engraving accompanies or previews particular
                     chapters or instalments, as appropriate </li>
                  <li>4) Images will include typed captions, including place numbers.</li>
               </ol></p>
            <head xml:id="collection_contributors">Contributors</head>
            <p><strong>Rebecca Nesvet</strong> is Assistant Professor of English at the University
               of Wisconsin, Green Bay. She earned her PhD at the University of North Carolina,
               Chapel Hill, in 2014. Awards include the International Conference on Romanticism's
               Lore Metzger Prize for the best graduate essay (2012). Her research is published in
                  <emph rend="italic">Women's Writing, Prism(s): Essays in Romanticism, The
                  Keats-Shelley Journal, Literature Compass, The Review of English Studies</emph>,
               and <emph rend="italic">Shakespearean International Yearbook</emph>. She is an Editor
               at the <emph rend="italic">Digital Mary Russell Mitford</emph> and contributed
               research to Gina Luria Walker's Pickering and Chatto edition of Mary Hays' <emph
                  rend="italic">Female Biography</emph>. She also reviews crime fiction for the
               United Kingdom and Canada-based site <emph rend="italic"><a
                     href="www.reviewingtheevidence">Reviewing the Evidence</a></emph>.</p>
            <p>
               <strong>Rae Yan</strong> Rae Yan is a PhD candidate in nineteenth-century British
               literature at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. Her research explores
               the "obsession with China" in Victorian literature and how this literature influenced
               revolutionary impulses in early twentieth-century China. She is currently pursuing a
               certificate in digital humanities through UNC Chapel Hill. </p>
            <p>
               <strong>Adam McCune</strong>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
