<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<!--
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/xsl" href="../xsl/rymer.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/css" href="../style.css" alternate="yes"?>
-->

<?xml-model href="../schema/sepoys.schema.xml" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Sepoys; Or, Highland Jessie: an electronic edition</title>
            <author corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">James Malcolm Rymer</author>
            <editor corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#RN">Rebecca Nesvet</editor>
            <editor corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#RXY">Rae X. Yan</editor>
            <editor type="technical">Adam McCune</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Rebecca Nesvet</publisher>
            <publisher>Rae X. Yan</publisher>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <idno>sepoys</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct xml:id="installment4" prev="sepoys.2.27.xml#installment3"
               next="sepoys.3.13.xml#installment5">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter VII: The City of the Mogul</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-03-06"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter VIII: The Flight from Delhi</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-03-06"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <!-- Information about the encoding of the text -->
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Information about the project itself (goals, organization, activities)</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Information about how the texts in a collection were chosen or excerpted</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="unknown">
               <p>Information about treatment of errors in the source (silently corrected, etc.)</p>
            </correction>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Information about normalization practices (e.g. treatment of roman numerals,
                  spelling, etc.)</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation form="std">
               <p>Information about treatment of quotations (preservation of original quotation
                  marks, etc.)</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="hard">
               <p>Treatment of the hyphenation of the source</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Information about whether and how the text has been segmented (mostly for
                  linguistic purposes)</p>
            </segmentation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Information about any interpretive information added to the text</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="installment">
            <head><date when="1858-03-06">Saturday, March 6, 1858</date></head>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="../facsimiles/sepoys.2.27.png"/>
            </figure>
            <pb n="113"/>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <head>THE <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="indian">SEPOYS</orgName>; OR, <persName
                  corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">HIGHLAND JESSIE</persName>.</head>
            <head>A TALE OF THE PRESENT INDIAN REVOLT.</head>
            <head>BY <persName type="pseudo">M. J. ERRYM</persName>.</head>
            <head>AUTHOR OF "<title>JANE BRIGHTWELL</title>," "<title>THE SNOW-DRIFT</title>,"
               ETC.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch7">CHAPTER VII.</head>
               <head>THE CITY OF THE MOGUL</head>
               <p><placeName type="city">DELHI</placeName>, the beautiful!--<placeName type="city"
                     >Delhi</placeName>, the magnificent!--seat of the old <orgName type="indian"
                     >Mogul</orgName> dynasty!--pearl of <placeName type="country"
                     >Hindostan</placeName>!--It is of thee we must now speak, ere yet the sunny
                  days of thy peace and prosperity had passed away! When they bazaars glittered with
                  the profusion of all that was bright and beautiful!--when thy fountains sparkled
                  in the sun untouched by the splash of blood!--when they princes glistened with
                  barbaric pearl and gold!--and when thy real lords, the European residents, idly
                  lolled upon their silken cushions, little dreaming of the volcano that was to
                  explode over and around them! </p>
               <p>For a brief period must we leave those in whose fortunes we have become so deeply
                  interested, in order to go back in the chronology of events, and account for the
                  strange and startling circumstances that placed <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName> and her poor
                  young sister <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                  >Bessie</persName>, in that den of massacre and horror at <placeName type="city"
                     >Cawnpore</placeName>.</p>
               <p>The day had been one of unexampled heat for the season ; and the cooler evening
                  air--only cooler, but not cool--that set in at the sunset over the scorched roofs
                  of <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>, was felt as a seasonable relief by a
                  large party assembled at one of the most fashionable <placeName type="building"
                     >bungalows</placeName> of the great <addName
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#cityofthemogul">City of the Mogul</addName>.</p>
               <p>The <orgName type="family">Hawkins</orgName>'s formerly stood high in the
                  presidency for wealth and influence. Mr. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Vernon Hawkins</persName> was an old
                  civil servant of the <orgName type="company">East India Company</orgName>, and had
                  grown grey and yellow in <placeName type="country">India</placeName>, adding up
                  his rupees by lacs towards the latter end of his career, and now only staying in
                     <placeName type="country">India</placeName> that he might see started on the
                     <cb n="2"/> same race for gold, his two sons--<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal Hawkins</persName>, who
                  was rapidly rising in the army, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar Hawkins</persName>, who was in
                  the civil service, as collector at <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>.</p>
               <p>The <orgName type="family">Hawkins</orgName>’s were fond of classical names for
                  their children. Their only daughter was named <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#volumina">Volumina</persName>
                  <!--[sic?]-->, and in good truth, taken as a whole, the family had sorely “shaken
                  the pagoda tree" in <placeName type="country">India</placeName>.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrhope">Mr. Hope</persName>, of the
                  civil service, had been the intimate friend of Mr. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Vernon Hawkins</persName>. They had
                  come out in the same vessel and landed together as <distinct type="slang"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#griffins">griffins</distinct> (newcomers) on the
                  shores of <placeName type="country">India</placeName>, so that the two families
                  seldom passed a day without seeing each other; and on this particularly sultry
                  occasion they sat together, half on the shaded verandah of the <placeName
                     type="building">bungalow</placeName>, while the <foreign
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#punkah">punkah</foreign> (a large board hinged
                  to the ceiling of apartments which acts as a fan) gently agitated the heated air.
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrhope">Mr. Hope</persName> had
                  been gathered to his fathers for more than a year, and but that her eldest
                  daughter was the wife of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#fletcher"
                     >Major Fletcher</persName>, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshope">Mrs. Hope</persName> would fain have
                  left <placeName type="country">India</placeName>.</p>
               <p>The native servants flitted to and fro with noiseless steps on the matted floors,
                  bringing cooled sherbet in long flagons to such of the party as desired it ; and
                  as the sun dipped beneath the faint haze of the western sky, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar Hawkins</persName> drew his
                  cigar languidly from his mouth, and sayd, “By Jove, there comes that half-blood
                  again! What does the fellow want here? These savages are a precious bore, on my
                  life!"</p>
               <p>"Oh, the wretch!" exclaimed <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#volumina"
                     >Miss Volumina</persName>. “I do wonder at you, Miss <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName>, I do, indeed,
                  to bow to a native!"</p>
               <p>"But <persName corresp="sepors.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur Ahib</persName> is
                  a gentleman!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                     Hope</persName> gently, while a tinge of colour glowed on her soft cheeks, “and
                  he is a prince in his own land!"</p>
               <p>"A fiddle-de-dee!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar
                     Hawkins</persName>. “The idea of these native fellows giving themselves airs!
                  My brother <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Hannibal</persName> says that they are a good deal too much petted, these
                     <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="indian">Sepoy</orgName> vagabonds, and that some
                  day we shall have to shoot a few score of them; and by Jove, it’s my idea
                  too!"</p>
               <p>"I certainly think," said Mr. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon"
                     >Vernon Hawkins</persName>, <cb n="3"/>who had reached <placeName type="city"
                     >Calcutta</placeName> with eighty pounds in his pocket, and now had two hundred
                  thousand in good investments,--“I certainly think that, considering what we do for
                  the natives, they are singularly ungrateful!"</p>
               <p>"Oh, horrid!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#volumina"
                     >Volumina</persName>. “There’s my maid actually fell asleep while dressing me
                  this morning, under the pretence of fatigue, because she had been up four nights,
                  fanning while I slept!"</p>
               <p>"And my fellow sulked for half the day," added <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>, “because I hit him
                  on the head with the heel of a boot for pulling off my socks so clumsily!"</p>
               <p>"The natives are really getting dreadful, my dears," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshawkins">Mrs. Hawkins</persName>. “What a
                  pity it is that there isn’t something like they used to have in the West Indies!
                  My uncle, the respected <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bonus">Mr.
                     Bonus</persName>, had an estate there, with Negroes and natives, and all that
                  sort of thing; and they always kept a man with a large cart whip, ready to punish
                  any of them that did anything wrong!"</p>
               <p>"Ah!" added <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>,
                  “that’s the way the niggers here ought to be treated!"</p>
               <p>"Nay," interposed <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                     Hope</persName>; “would not kindness do much more to win their love?"</p>
               <p>"Love! Love!" screamed all the <orgName type="family">Hawkins</orgName> family;
                  “she says love! Oh, poor <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie Hope</persName>!" and then they set off in a chorus of laughter, which
                  only stopped when they got too hot to laugh any longer.</p>
               <p>By the time this rapid discourse had taken place, the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young mountain chief</roleName> who
                  had been noticed approaching through the garden, by the party, had reached the
                  steps which led to the verandah, and had there bowed low. His salutations had been
                  returned by <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>
                  and the <orgName type="family">Hope</orgName> family only, for they knew that
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrhope">Mr. Hope</persName> had
                  esteemed him gently.</p>
               <p>And now, with a dignity in his look and manner, which for a moment awed even
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar Hawkins</persName>
                  to silence, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>
                  approached <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr.
                     Hawkins</persName>, saying, “<roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName>, it is an untimely hour
                  for business, but I come a petitioner for—“ </p>
               <p>"Now, really," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr.
                     Hawkins</persName>, “my good sir, if you want anything you had better apply at
                  my <cb n="1"/>office, or, I may say now, at my son’s office—in the morning, or
                  some other day!"</p>
               <p>"Not in the morning, by Jove!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>, “I’m going out for
                  some sport!"</p>
               <p>"I come not for myself," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, mildly. “I come for another, and for all here!"</p>
               <p>As he spoke, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                  >Jeffur</persName>, with a wave of his arm that had much grace and dignity in it,
                  included the <orgName type="family">Hopes</orgName>, who say apart a little from
                  the <orgName type="family">Hawkins</orgName>’s, in the expression “all here."</p>
               <p>"You were our father’s friend," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>. “Speak
                  freely! What have you to say, <roleName type="honorific">Prince</roleName>
                  <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>?"</p>
               <p>"Prince! ha!—ha!" laughted <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar Hawkins</persName>; “ha!—ha!—friend! Why, now, really, my dear
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>,
                  our good friend, <roleName type="military"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#fletcher">the Major</roleName>, would not be
                  well pleased to hear that!"</p>
               <p>"Peace!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, without betraying the least anger or surprise. “Peace let
                  there be here. <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                     >Sahib</roleName>, I come from a poor <foreign xml:lang="hi"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#ryot">ryot</foreign>, near the village named
                     <placeName type="city">Choree</placeName>. The young <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahibs</roleName>, in their eagerness for
                  the chase, trampled his little patch of vegetation ; and a lighted cigar, flung on
                  the thatch of his hut, burnt the thatch and soon reduced it to flames. Compensate
                  the poor man, <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                     >Sahibs</roleName>: he and his have had to take refuge among the tombs, for a
                  fever is vexing the blood of his youngest child." </p>
               <p>"Now, by Jove!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar
                     Hawkins</persName>, “this is too bad! Hence a gentleman who is away from his
                  own country, and devilish hot from morning to night and from night to morning in
                  this place, can’t go our for a little amusement but he’s asked for compensation!
                  What’s to compensate me, I wonder, for knocking up my best horses and losing a
                  dog, eh?"</p>
               <p>"The poor <foreign xml:lang="hi" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#ryot"
                     >ryot</foreign>, <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName>, neither knocked up the
                  horse nor lost the dog!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>.</p>
               <p>"Now, I tell you what, my good sir," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr. Hawkins</persName>, “I never
                  argue with a native, nor allow any of my family to do so. Be so good as to call at
                  the proper office, and see the proper authority, who, after proper consideration
                  in the proper official way, will do the proper thing when and how he thinks
                  proper, and that is the only answer I ever give to a native!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> bowed, with
                  a sad smile, and then with a quiet, gentle movement, he went up to <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName>, and after a
                  low bow, he said, while his voice shook a little, “O, maiden of the starry eyes!
                  Where is now thy brother, the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName>
                  <roleName type="military" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#fletcher"
                     >Major</roleName>—I mean the husband of thy sister?"</p>
               <p>"Well, I never!" muttered <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#volumina"
                     >Miss Volumina</persName>. “Maiden of the starry eyes, indeed! No native ever
                  took such a liberty as to say such a thing to me!"</p>
               <p>"My husband, good <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                     >Annie</persName>, “is with his regiment at <placeName type="city"
                     >Cawnpore</placeName>!"</p>
               <p>"At <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>!—at <placeName type="city"
                     >Cawnpore</placeName>!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> stood silent
                  for a moment, and then he said gently, “How much happier you would all be
                  together—I mean with the <roleName type="military"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#fletcher">Major</roleName>
                  <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName>,
                  away from <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>—at <placeName type="city"
                     >Cawnpore</placeName>—anywhere away from <placeName type="city"
                     >Delhi</placeName>! You and yours—this very night—anywhere but at <placeName
                     type="city">Delhi</placeName>!"</p>
               <p>His voice now shook as he spoke, and with his hands clasped he leaned towards the
                  sister, as he repeated the words, “anywhere but at <placeName type="city"
                     >Delhi</placeName>!"</p>
               <p>A feeling of alarm came over the heart of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>, and as she
                  glanced in the direction of an <foreign corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#ayah"
                     >ayah</foreign> who was rocking her child to and fro, while the little fellow
                  laughed in glee.</p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>," she said,
                  “you are a friend in feeling towards us! Tell us what your words signify? </p>
               <p>For a moment the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">mountain chief</roleName> seemed on
                  the point of speaking, and then the sudden boom of a cannon in the distance came
                  upon the ears of the now startled group.</p>
               <p>"Heyday! What, in the name of all that’s odd, is that?" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar Hawkins</persName>. “Has the
                     <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dalhousie"
                     >Governor-general</roleName> taken it into His Excellency’s head to pay
                     <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName> a visit?"</p>
               <p>Bang went another cannon.</p>
               <p>"Good heavens! What is it?"  said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, as she
                  involuntarily placed her arm upon the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young chief</roleName> of the
                  hills.</p>
               <p>There was then the rattle of a drum, and, in the distance, the braying sound of
                  cavalry trumpets came upon the ears of the startled group.</p>
               <p>Even <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar Hawkins</persName>
                  turned a little pale, as he cried aloud to his own servant to attend him, and say
                  if he knew the cause of the tumult in the city.</p>
               <p>For the first time <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar
                     Hawkins</persName> called in vain—no servant made his appearance. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName> mechanically
                  flew to the <foreign corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#ayah">ayah</foreign>, and
                  clasped her child to her own breast.</p>
               <p>"What is it? Oh, what is it?" she cried.</p>
               <p>"A fire, no doubt," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr.
                     Hawkins</persName>. “Nothing but a fire. There is really nothing to be alarmed
                  at, of course."</p>
               <p>"By Jove—of course!" echoed <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar Hawkins</persName>. “A fire, no doubt. I didn’t think of that. These
                  natives are so stupid!"</p>
               <p>"And so ungrateful!" added the father.</p>
               <p>"And so careless and idle!" said the mother.</p>
               <p>"And so ugly!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#volumina"
                     >Volumina</persName>.</p>
               <p><cb n="2"/>At this moment a Hindoo servant came rushing up to the steps of the
                  verandah, and gesticulating furiously with his farms, he said something which
                  ended only in a strange kind of yell, and then disappeared.</p>
               <p>The <orgName type="family">Hawkins</orgName> family, now fairly alarmed, sprung to
                  their feet, and as a horseman dashed into the compound, they all exclaimed, with
                  one voice, “<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Hannibal</persName>! <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Hannibal</persName>!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal Hawkins</persName>
                  flung himself from his foaming steed, and rushed up to the party, as he exclaimed,
                  “A revolt! A revolt of the <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName>! By heaven, the
                  niggers are up! A revolt!—a revolt! The <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName>
                  are in arms! <placeName type="city">Meerut</placeName> is sacked, and all
                  massacred! They march on <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>! My regiment
                  refuses to act, and the Sepoy gunners are firing signal cannon from the battery by
                  the <placeName type="building">Cashmere Gate</placeName>!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshawkins">Mrs. Hawkins</persName>
                  uttered a scream. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr.
                     Hawkins</persName> rubbed the top of his head with a confused look ; and
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> fairly
                  toppled backwards, chair and all, and lay sprawling on the steps of the verandah.
                  The <orgName type="family">Hope</orgName> family clung to each other in mute
                  terror.</p>
               <p>Bang went another gun from the walls of <placeName type="city"
                  >Delhi</placeName>.</p>
               <p>"They are at it again! The rebels will be in the city before the morning, and
                  there is no adequate force to stop them, or hold the place! We must be off and
                  away!"</p>
               <p>"Yes, yes! The plate—the jewels!" cried <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshawkins">Mrs. Hawkins</persName>.</p>
               <p>"My papers!" said the father.</p>
               <p>"My cigars!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>. “By Jove! Where’s my rifle? Holloa! Where are all the
                  rascally servants!"</p>
               <p>"Here’s one, <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                     >Sahib</roleName>!" yelled a tall <orgName type="religion">Hindoo</orgName>,
                  who had, up to then, been the quietest and most submissive of the household, but
                  who now bounded into the midst of the terrified circle, with his hair loose, the
                  wild fire of semi-intoxication in his eyes, and a blazing torch in his hand.
                  “Here, <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                     >Sahibs</roleName>—all here! They are here, and with but one cry, and that is,
                  Death to the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>! To man, woman,
                  and child! To the young and to the old! To the maiden, and the infant at its
                  mother’s breast! Death to all! Death to the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>! Life for the
                     <orgName type="indian">Sepoy</orgName>! Life for <placeName type="country"
                     >India</placeName>! Ha! Ha! The time has come! The lotus leaf has gone forth!
                  The avengers are at hand! Death! Death! Death! Blood on the land—on the
                  tree-stem—on the door-step—on the roof-top! Blood, death, and fire!"</p>
               <p>With another yell, that rung high and loud in the night air, he flung the lighted
                  toched into the middle of the apartment, and, clearing the steps of the verandah
                  at one bound, he disappeared in the garden.</p>
               <p>"By Jove!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>.</p>
               <p>"Stop, stop, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Hannibal</persName>!" cried <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr. Hawkins</persName>, as <roleName
                     type="military">Captain</roleName>
                  <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal Hawkins</persName>
                  drew his sword, and rushed after the man.</p>
               <p>A wild disorderly shout now burst from ten thousand voices in the city. Then came
                  a volley of musketry, and then, mingling with the soft light of the Indian sunset,
                  there was the red glare of fire in various parts of the city.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal Hawkins</persName>
                  returned breathless and heated. The lightly-clad and agile native had easily
                  eluded him. It was <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>, then, who called out, in hopeful accents, “<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur Ahib</persName>! <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur Ahib</persName>! He is our
                  friend, and will save us yet!“</p>
               <p>All eyes were now turned in the direction where the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young hill chief</roleName> had been
                  standing, but he had disappeared, and was nowhere to be seen, in or about the
                     <placeName type="building">bungalow</placeName>. But a new person was at this
                  moment added to the alarmed group, for a lady, who was a recent importation from
                     <placeName type="country">England</placeName>, and who rejoiced in the name of
                  the Hon. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss
                     Flint</persName>, hearing the tumult, rushed from her chamber in a charming
                  state of deshabille, and flung herself almost into the arms of old <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr. Hawkins</persName>, as she
                  exclaimed, “Oh, gracious! What is the matter? Oh, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr. Hawkins</persName>, why did you
                  come to <placeName type="country">India</placeName>? I, who refused two Irish
                  gentlemen, and a sugar-broker in the City, and might have married twenty times, at
                  least, in England! Oh! Oh! Oh! What’s that?"</p>
               <p>Another gun from the walls seemed now to shake the <placeName type="building"
                     >bungalow</placeName> to its foundation.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr. Hawkins</persName> then
                  seemed to think that it devolved upon his to assume a sort of generalship of the
                  party, and, shaking off the Hon. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName>, he cried
                  out, “I didn’t persuade you to come, my dear madam. You came husband-hunting on
                  your own account. Shut the doors—I mean the jalousies! Fire the punkah—no,
                  the—the—fowling-pieces! Kill the villains! Let’s all run away as quick as we can!
                  Murder! Fire! Rebellion! Pack up the goods!—call the rascally servants!—stand
                  round me, all of you!—there will be bullets going about soon!"</p>
               <p>The Hon. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss
                     Flint</persName> swooned—<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName> swore—Mrs. Hawkins felt a strong inclination to faint, and
                  so did <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#volumina">Volumina</persName>;
                  but they thought that if they did so, they would very likely be left behind; so
                  they preserved their seenses, and only screamed in chorus with the Hon. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName>, now and
                  then.</p>
               <p>"Silence, all of you!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>. “You <cb n="3"/>will only bring the fellows upon
                  us by that clatter! Hark! There!—there again! That is firing! I must not stay
                  here! My duty is with the few troops we have in <placeName type="city"
                     >Delhi</placeName>!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>,
                  who, whatever may have been his faults in regard to his general tone and manners,
                  by no means wanted courage, was about to rush from the <placeName type="building"
                     >bungalow</placeName>, when his mother clung to him on the one side, and
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#volumina">Volumina</persName> on
                  the other.</p>
               <p>"Oh, what will become of us, if you desert us" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshawkins">Mrs. Hawkins</persName>. “My
                  son—my son! Your one arm can do little in <placeName type="city"
                  >Delhi</placeName>, but it may save us!"</p>
               <p>Now that was the most sensible speech that <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshawkins">Mrs. Hawkins</persName> had ever
                  made, and it had some effect upon the <roleName type="military"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, who said, “I
                  will only go a little way beyond the ramparts, and will then return to you, on my
                  honour!"</p>
               <p>To this there could be no denial, and the <roleName type="military"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> left the
                     <placeName type="building">bungalow</placeName>, and crossing the garden and
                  court in front of it, he made his way into one of the streets of the city.</p>
               <p>The scene that there met the view of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>, in its
                  multifarious details, baffles all description. The straggling mass of rebels that
                  had made their way from <placeName type="city">Meerut</placeName> had reached
                     <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>, and the torch of insurrection was
                  lit. Simultaneously with their rush at the city gates, the Sepoy regiments within
                  had shaken off their allegiance to their officers, and the confusion in the city
                  was as if fifty thousand madmen had broken loose, and were yelling and roaring
                  through the streets.</p>
               <p>Before many moments had elapsed, a Sepoy of his own regiment made a rush at
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> to cut him down, shouting as he advanced, “Death to the
                     <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>! Death to
                  all!"</p>
               <p>The <roleName type="military" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName> met the savage in full career, and cut him to the earth.
                  Then, staggering back, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>, pale, and, with, as he considered, death staring
                  him in te face, placed himself against a doorway, and with his drawn sword
                  extended before him, awaited the next attack.</p>
               <p>And while there, all the din and roar of the rebellious city came upon his ears.
                  The rattle of musketry—the beating of drums—the clash of cymbals mingling with
                  that of swords—and the boom of the cannon which the <orgName type="indian"
                     >Sepoys</orgName> on the walls were turning on the small parties of fugitives
                  who were flying from the city. The screams of women and children—the agonised
                  cries of the wounded—and the fearful shouts of the now savage Hindoos—the hoarse
                  cry of the <orgName type="religion">Mussulman</orgName> devotees calling aloud for
                  blood—all made up a chaos of sounds that were enough, once heard, to haunt the
                  imagination for a lifetime.</p>
               <p>It might be three, four, or five minutes, that, as if paralysed, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>
                  maintained the same attitude and listened to those fearful sounds. Then a rabble
                  of <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName>, bearing a head upon the point of a
                  spear, came streaming into the street. In a moment a dozen muskets were pointed at
                  him, and a volley from the whole rattled about his ears.</p>
               <p>"Death to the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>!" was the
                  cry.</p>
               <p>And death would indeed have been there and then the lot of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> had not
                  the door behind him suddenly opened, and a strng hand drawn him through it, and
                  closed it again on the instant.</p>
               <p>"Save thoose who will trust in you1" said a voice. “Leave the city by the
                     <placeName type="building">Eastern Gate</placeName>. It will not be closed
                  against you and those with you. Oh, hasten! As you value those who should be
                  dearer to you than life itself!"</p>
               <p>A glance at the form of him who thus spoke showed <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> that it
                  was the <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young
                     chief</roleName>, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur
                     Ahib</persName>, who spoke; but before he could reply there came a volley of
                  blows upon the closed door, and it began rapidly to yield to the <orgName
                     xml:lang="ur" type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> who were without.</p>
               <p>"Death! Death!" was the cry.</p>
               <p>"Down!—down to the floor and lie still—not as you value your life, for you are a
                  soldier, but as you value the lives of those whom you may yet save—down!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>,
                  even in the confusion of that dreadful moment, understood him, and dropped upon
                  his face to the ground. The <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young chief</roleName> strode over
                  him with his drawn sword in his hand, at the moment that the door fell inwards
                  with a loud crash.</p>
               <p>The infuriated faces of a dozen <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="indian"
                     >Sepoys</orgName> appeared at the opening.</p>
               <p>"Death ! death! Death to the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>!"</p>
               <p>"It is done!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>.</p>
               <p>The young <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>
                  struggled to his feet.</p>
               <p>"You have saved me!" he said.</p>
               <p>"I know it—it was for others. Do not thank me, I can see, O Sahib, that you are
                  about to do so. Go down that passage, and clamber the wall in the garden beyond
                  it; you will their <!-- sic --> find yourself with your family again. <cb n="1"
                  />Lose not a moment, but fly from the city; for before the dawn of a new day there
                  will not be a drop of English blood within it that will not stain its streets or
                  its houses."</p>
               <p>"Oh! Tell me yet—what is the meaning of it all?—this dreadful revolt?" </p>
               <p>"No more! No more! Fly while you can! The <placeName type="building">Eastern
                     Gate</placeName>—remember! <placeName type="country">India</placeName> has
                  risen, and the old Moguls will once again rule in the halls of the imperial palace
                  of <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>! Fly, I say! Fly—or all is lost!—for
                  you, and for those you should save!"</p>
               <p>If anything had been required to aid the remonstrances of injunctions of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> to the young
                  Captain to make the best use of his time, it would have been found certainly in
                  the roar and din of conflict from the city ; and now through the broken-down
                  doorway he saw a sight which froze his blood with horror, and nearly deprived him
                  of the power of action. </p>
               <p>Hunted like some wild animal of the chase, a fair and gentle-looking English girl
                  came screaming onwards, pursued by a troop of yelling savages. Her garments had
                  been torn from her, and her long, fair, silken hair waved in wild disorder about
                  her delicate limbs.</p>
               <p>They cut her down close to the broken doorway. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hawkins">Captain Hawkins</persName> heard her
                  last shriek, and he saw her body dragged by the limbs in different directions by
                  his murderers.</p>
               <p>It was only the strong arm of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> that prevented the young officer from rushing forth, sword
                  in hand, in the vain hope of rescuing her.</p>
               <p>"Hold! Hold!" whispered <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>. “Are you mad?"</p>
               <p>"I am mad! Hold me not! Oh! This is indeed maddening!"</p>
               <p>"You cannot save her."</p>
               <p>"I can avenge!"</p>
               <p>"And fall yourself! Think of those you love."</p>
               <p>"Alas! Alas! Hear me—you, who I know are looked up to as a chief and a warrior by
                  the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="indian">Sepoy</orgName> and by the whole <orgName
                     type="religion">Hindoo</orgName>, as well as the Mahomedan race—hear me, while
                  I tell you that if the cause of the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="indian"
                     >Sepoy</orgName> was as pure as an angel might bless, and if he had more reason
                  for revolt than ever falls to the lot of mortal man, deeds like this would blast
                  him and all his race for ever!"</p>
               <p>"I know it," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, sadly. “Go! Go! I know it—I feel it! Go at once!"</p>

            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch8">CHAPTER VIII.</head>
               <head>THE FLIGHT FROM DELHI.</head>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>
                  felt indeed that it was fully time he should take what steps he could for the
                  rescue of the family in the <placeName type="building">bungalow</placeName>. There
                  was an imperious gesture about the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young mountain chief</roleName> which
                  enforced command ; and withotu another word the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> betook himself
                  to the garden wall mentioned by Jeffyr as separating him from the compound of the
                     <orgName type="family">Hawkins</orgName>'s.</p>
               <p>To scale the wall was the work of a moment ; and the young man stood among the
                  terrified throng he had so recently left.</p>
               <p>It was, at the instant, a piece of good fortune that <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar Hawkins</persName> did not
                  fire at him, as he appeared on the top of the wall, by mistake, for one of their
                  eneies. It was <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                     Hope</persName> who called out loudly, "It is <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>! It is
                  your brother!"</p>
               <p>"By Jove! so it is!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>. "I thought it was one of the niggers, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal</persName>!"</p>
               <p>"Quick! quick!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>. "There is not a moment to lose! I believe the city
                  is in the hands of the rebels, and I have seen such sights as I never wish to see
                  again! Get a couple of the carriages out from the stables, and put in the
                  strongest horses! We must be off at once!"</p>
               <p>"All right!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>; "off, and away! By Jove, though, I should like to have a
                  shot at some of the rebels first! What's that?"</p>
               <p>"Murder!" screamed <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss
                     Flint</persName>,--"murder!" </p>
               <p>All eyes were turned in the direction of that great personage, and they saw her
                  pointing,with a delirious look, at a portion of the wall of thecuort close to the
                  gates which shut in the whole establishment from the open thoroughfare beyond. </p>
               <p>Something dark was slowly making its way over the top of the wall. It was a Sepoy,
                  with his tulwar in his mouth, so as to leave him full use of his hands, and who,
                  in another moment, would have been in the court. His design was, no doubt, to open
                  the gaes frm within and admit his comrades, when the slaughter of the family would
                  have been certain.</p>
               <p>"Shoot him!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>; "shoot him, somebody!"</p>
               <p>"Down he goes!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>. </p>
               <p>There was a flash and a report, and, with a shrief, the <orgName xml:lang="ur"
                     type="indian">Sepoy</orgName> rolled into the garden. </p>
               <p>This shriek of the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="indian">Sepoy</orgName> was echoed
                  by such a yell without, that one would have thought a legion of fiends were at the
                  gate. The fact was, that a party of some thirty Sepoys had determined upon
                  attacking and sack<cb n="2"/>ing the <placeName type="building"
                     >bungalow</placeName>, and had preserved silence, with the hope that one of
                  their number migh crawl over the wall, unperceived, and open the gates. The
                  failure of their plan rendered silence no longer an element of success with them,
                  and they yelled, and bellowed, and roared, and struck the gates with their muskets
                  in all the rage of disappointed vengeance. </p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr. Hawkins</persName> and the
                  females seemed to be quite paralysed by terror, and all he could do was to mutter
                  something about appealing to the proper athority, who would do something in a
                  proper way when he thought proper. </p>
               <p>The Hon. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss
                     Flint</persName> appeared to faint away three times, and to recover again with
                  astonishing rapidity; and then she commenced a series of screams that rose shrill
                  and clear over the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="indian">Sepoys</orgName>' yells of
                  rage.</p>
               <p>"Silence!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>, who was that upon him must devolve all that could be done
                  in the fearful emergency,--"silence! This noise will confuse us! <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>, can you get the
                  carriages round to the back gate?"</p>
               <p> "Yes! yes!"</p>
               <p>"How many of us are here? One, two, three, four, five, six! Oh! We make a party of
                  nine! You must get out both the carriages, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>, and be quick about
                  it! Give me your gun, and I will keep these wretches at bay!" </p>
               <p> The gates were secured by a stout bar, or the <orgName xml:lang="ur"
                     type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> would soon have forced their way into the
                  garden; for they fired a musket through the lock, which shattered it to atoms.</p>
               <p>
                  <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> surrendered
                  his gun to his brother, and ran to the stables, at the back of the <placeName
                     type="building">bungalow</placeName>, to get out the carriages and horses; but
                  it was not without a notion that there might be an attack in that quarter as well
                  as from the front.</p>
               <p> "Now go into the house," said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, and pack up,
                  into as small a compass as you can, what you wish to take with you. I will hold
                  this post till <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName> tells me he has the carriages ready."</p>
               <p> "Look! look!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                     Hope</persName>. "Another!"</p>
               <p> On the top of the wall appeared a Sepoy, apparently, by some extraordinary means,
                  hanging head downwards, and trying if that process brought him low enough to lift
                  the bar from the gates. The fact was, that a couple of his comrades held him by
                  the feet in order that this audacious attempt should be made.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>
                  levelled and fired, and the Sepoy fell; and again came the yell of rage from those
                  withotu, and they began to batter the gate with a force that made it shake again,
                  and threatened its speedy demolition.</p>
               <p>"Hurry <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>, some
                  of your!" said the Captain. "Our lives depend upon a moment's delay."</p>
               <p> Into the various rooms of the <placeName type="building">bungalow</placeName> now
                  rushed the females, and with hurried fingers began to make small packages of what
                  they valued most; while <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr.
                     Hawkins</persName>, with a weak, silly look, first ran in one direction and
                  then in another, not knowing really what he was about.</p>
               <p> And now there arose a roaring shot from the <orgName type="indian"
                     >Sepoys</orgName> without, and, mingles with the cries, was an English voice
                  calling aloud for help.</p>
               <p>"Kill! kill the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>!" shouted the
                     <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName>. "Kill him!--cut him to pieces!" </p>
               <p> There was a clash of weapons without; and then a voice, unmistakably English,
                  cried out, "Villains! I will sell my life dearly yet! Help! Help! In the
                     <placeName type="building">bungalow</placeName>!"</p>
               <p> "By heavens!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>, "I should know that voice! It is <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant Adrian</persName> of ours,
                  and those wretches are slaughtering him! I will make yet one effort to save
                  him!"</p>
               <p>Some distance to the right of the large gates was a small narrow door in the wall,
                  the key of which was always kept in the forked branch of one of the trees close at
                  hand. </p>
               <p>This door had apparently escaped in the darkness the attention or observation of
                  the <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName>, or they could much easier have forced
                  it than the gates to which they paid all their attention.</p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Adrian</persName>!" cried
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>. "<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                     >Adrian</persName>, to the right! To the right!"</p>
               <p>"Help! help!" shouted the <roleName type="military"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant</roleName>. </p>
               <p>Then there were several shots fired, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> rushed
                  to the narrow door and opened it. Covered with wounds and bleeding fearfully,
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant
                     Adrian</persName> fell down on the very threshold. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personogrphy.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> dragged
                  him in, and slammed the door in the faces of a couple of <orgName type="indian"
                     >Sepoys</orgName> who rushed at it.</p>
               <p>"You are much hurt, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                     >Adrian</persName>?" said the <roleName type="military"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>. </p>
               <p>"I fear they have done for me!" said <roleName type="military"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">the Lieutenant</roleName> faintly.
                  "Let me lie here!" </p>
               <p>"No, no! my good fellow, rouse yourself! We are going to run for it, and you must
                  go with us!"</p>
               <p>There was no reply. The young officer had either died or fainted.</p>
               <p>And now <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> felt that he had exposed the weak part of his post to the
                  foe, and that his posi<cb n="3"/>tion in the garden would soon be untenable; most
                  welcome, then, was the cry of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>, "All right, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal</persName>! Come on! come
                  on!"</p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>, help me
                  here!"</p>
               <p>"What is it?"</p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Adrian</persName>, of our's!
                  I don't think he is dead! We must not leave him to those butchers!"</p>
               <p>"By Jove, no! Confound the niggers! I'll carry him, and you protect the retreat!
                  The others are all in the carriages!"</p>
               <p>"That is well! Ah! It is too late!"</p>
               <p> The small door in the wall, through which <roleName type="military"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">the young Lieutenant</roleName> had
                  been rescued, was now dashed open, and several <orgName xml:lang="ur"
                     type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> rushed into the garden. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> fired
                  both barrells of the gun he had in his hands into the midst of them, and then he
                  rushed after <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                  >Caesar</persName>, who made good his retreat into the house, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> secured
                  a door through which they passed, and to force which, ould take the Sepoys several
                  minutes.</p>
               <p>Those minutes were the life of the whole party. </p>
               <p>There was in the <placeName type="building">bungalow</placeName> a suffocating
                  smoke and a strong odour of burning wood, which at once suggested the idea that
                  the building was on fire ; and, indeed, hardly had the young man reached the
                  further end of the hall, which went right through the house, when there issued
                  from one of the rooms the very <foreign corres="sepoys.backmatter.xml#ayah"
                     >ayah</foreign> who had always professed so much devotion to <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>'s child, and
                  who had come with her to nurse on the occasion of the visit to the <orgName
                     type="family">Hawkins</orgName>'s. She bore a lighted torch in her hands,
                  which, before she noticed the young man with his wounded friend, she began
                  applying to the muslin hangings of a window. </p>
               <p>"Hold!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>. :You she fiend, what are you about?" </p>
               <p>With a scream of fright, the <foreign corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#ayah"
                     >ayah</foreign> dropped the torch, and ran into one of the rooms. </p>
               <p>"We have no trouble about her!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>. "Come on! By Jove!
                  the niggers are all alike, men and women!" </p>
               <p>"And where will all this end?" ejaculated <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>. </p>
               <p>The young man closed the hall, and issued out from it to the back of the
                     <placeName type="building">bungalow</placeName>, just as the <orgName
                     type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> forced the front door. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> secured
                  the keys of the back one, and locked it. That was another moment's delay. </p>
               <p>Immediately before them now they saw the two carriages, with the females already
                  seated. The domestic carriages used in <placeName type="country">India</placeName>
                  are small and light ; and as the party, including the wounded <roleName
                     type="military" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                  >Lieutenant</roleName>, now consisted of ten persons, it was much as they could do
                  to pack themselves in the little frail vehicles.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant Adrian</persName>
                  was laid along the bottom of one of the carriages, and it was hastily resolved
                  that <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> was to drive one, and his brother <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> the other. And now
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> proceeded
                  to open the gate that would lead them into a back thoroughfare of the city, not
                  far from the river <geogName type="river">Jumna</geogName>, when, before he drew
                  the last bolt, he felt certain there was a pressure on the door from without.</p>
               <p>He listened, but all was still.</p>
               <p>The young man was active enough when he chose, and to scramble up by some
                  projections in the wall and peep over it, was the work of a moment. A number of
                  dark figures lay close under it, evidently in waiting for the carriages to come
                  forth.</p>
               <p>The danger was indeed imminent. </p>
               <p>"By Jove! What's to be done?" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>. "And here come the
                  other niggers from the front!"</p>
               <p>"There! there!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                     Hope</persName>--"round that angle of the wall by the custard-apple trees! Have
                  we not noticed how frail it is? It can be easily broken down, and the carriages
                  will pass out!"</p>
               <p>"It's the only hope!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.persongroaphy.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>. "Come <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>, and help me!"</p>
               <p>The two young men seized some garden implements which fortunately were kept there,
                  and attached the rotten and falling wall. A breach was made in a few seconds, and
                  just as the <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> rushed from the back door of
                  the <placeName type="building">bungalow</placeName>, half suffocated by the smoke
                  with which it was filled, and which had retarded them, the two carriages, with
                  various bumps over the fallen rubish<!--sic--> of the old wall, emerged from the
                  compound.</p>
               <p>Shots were fired after them, but the horses were fresh and neither <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> nor <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal</persName> spared any
                  means to urged them forward. Still that drive through <placeName type="city"
                     >Delhi</placeName> was an awful one, and had there been anything like
                  organization about the <orgName type="indian">Sepoy</orgName> force, the escape of
                  the party would have been simply impossible.</p>
               <p>As it was, however, the victorious <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> had
                  scattered throughout the city in parties, more intent upon plunder than any united
                  action. To be sure, every isolated European they met with was at once barbarously
                  murdered ; but all they could do against these two carriages, going along at such
                  headlong speed, was to fire after them, on the chance of hitting some of the
                  party.</p>
               <p><cb n="1"/><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> did not forget the advice of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur Ahib</persName> to take the
                     <placeName type="building">Eastern Gate</placeName> of the city, and he
                  directed his course thither accordingly, closely followed by <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> in the next
                  carriage. Occasionally a sudden jerk of the wheels would betray the fact that they
                  had ridden over some dead or dying wretch in the roadway, and a horrible light
                  from the conflagration of various <placeName type="building">bungalows</placeName>
                  began to spread itself about all things. </p>
               <p>In order to reach the <placeName type="building">Eastern Gate</placeName>, they
                  had to pass across the principal street in<placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>
                  ; and as they reached it, and, in fact, were about to emerge into it, they heard
                  the clangour of cymbols <!--sic--> and the beating of drums, and shouts of a large
                  cavalcade.</p>
               <p>The young men stopped the panting horses, and from the obscurity of th narrow lane
                  in which they were, they saw pass, accompanied by as much barbaric pomp as could
                  be imprised for the occasion, the old <roleName type="indian">King of<placeName
                        type="city">Delhi</placeName></roleName>, in whose name the mutineers
                  intended to act.</p>
               <p>Seated on an elephant, with his shaggy eyebrows almost hiding his eyes, the old
                  faded representative of the <orgName type="indian">Moguls</orgName>, surrounded by
                  his sons, passed on. From time to time, prisoners were flung down before the huge
                  feet of the elephant ; and there was a grim smile of satisfaction as the shrieks
                  of the crushed and mangled wretches rose shrilly to his ears.</p>
               <p>The cymbals clashed again, and the drums beat, as the wild procession passed on,
                  carrying a long train of half-intoxicated <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName>,
                  peons, and the rabble of the city in its rear.</p>
               <p>"This is horrible!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>. </p>
               <p>"On! on!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>; "the way seems clear now."</p>
               <p>They dashed forward, and a few minutes brought them to the <placeName
                     type="building">Eastern Gate</placeName>; but, to their dismay, they saw there
                  a strong guard of Sepoys, and that a couple of cannon were so placed as to command
                  the thoroughfare leading to the gate, which itself was closed.</p>
               <p>"We are lost!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>. "by Jove, it's all up!"</p>
               <p>"I fear the worst," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>.</p>
               <p>At this moment, mounted on a richly caparisoned charger, there issued out from the
                  small court in front of the <placeName type="building">guard-house</placeName>, an
                  officer in a glittering suit of chain armour.</p>
               <p>"Guard!" he cried.</p>
               <p>There was the rattle of muskets, and the whole guard turned out from the low
                  building that served for a guard-house.</p>
               <p>"Open the gate!"</p>
               <p>"Ah!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>, "I know that voice! It is <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur Ahib</persName>! He is in
                  command of this gate!"</p>
               <p>"We are saved, then!" sobbed <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                     >Mrs. Fletcher</persName>, as she clasped her child closer to her bosom.</p>
               <p>"Pass on, two carriages!" cried <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur Ahib</persName>, in a cold
                  tone of military command <!-- compare with "sneer of cold command"-->. "Pass on,
                  by order of the <roleName type="honrific">King</roleName>!" </p>
               <p>Hardly conscious at the moment whether they had really passed through the gate or
                  not, so sudden and unlooked-for was this deliverance, the little party found
                  themselves without the walls.</p>
               <p>"By Jove!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>, "that's a noble fellow!"</p>
               <p>The females sobbed aloud in their fulness of heart ; and then, before another word
                  could be spoken, a tremendous concussion, as if from the disruption of a world,
                  shook the ground, and was followed by a roaring, rushing sound, that had something
                  inexpressibly awful in it.</p>
               <p>"<persName>Willoughby</persName> has fired the Magazine!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>. "He
                  said he would!"</p>
               <p><emph>(To be continued in our next)</emph></p>

            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
