<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model hcorresp="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!--<?xml-model hcorresp="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<!--
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/xsl" href="../xsl/rymer.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/css" href="../style.css" alternate="yes"?>
-->


<?xml-model href="../schema/sepoys.schema.xml" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Sepoys; Or, Highland Jessie: an electronic edition</title>
            <author>James Malcolm Rymer</author>
            <author>
               <persName type="pseudo">M. J. Errym</persName>
            </author>
            <editor>Rebecca Nesvet</editor>
            <editor>Rae X. Yan</editor>
            <editor type="technical">Adam McCune</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Rebecca Nesvet</publisher>
            <publisher>Rae X. Yan</publisher>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <idno>sepoys</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct xml:id="installment8" prev="sepoys.3.27.xml#installment7"
               next="sepoys.4.10.xml#installment9">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter XIV: The Captive Officers.--The Hindoo Sacrifice</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-04-03"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter XVI: The Sisters and Zeelook.--The Stream and the
                     Escape.</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-04-03"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <!-- Information about the encoding of the text -->
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Information about the project itself (goals, organization, activities)</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Information about how the texts in a collection were chosen or excerpted</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="unknown">
               <p>Information about treatment of errors in the source (silently corrected, etc.)</p>
            </correction>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Information about normalization practices (e.g. treatment of roman numerals,
                  spelling, etc.)</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation form="std">
               <p>Information about treatment of quotations (preservation of original quotation
                  marks, etc.)</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="hard">
               <p>Treatment of the hyphenation of the source</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Information about whether and how the text has been segmented (mostly for
                  linguistic purposes)</p>
            </segmentation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Information about any interpretive information added to the text</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="installment">
            <head>
               <date when="1858-04-03">Saturday, April 3, 1858</date>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="../facsimiles/sepoys.4.03.png"/>
            </figure>
            <pb n="201"/>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch15">CHAPTER XV.</head>
               <p>THE CAPTIVE OFFICERS.—THE HINDOO SACRIFICE.</p>


               <p>THE indignation of the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                     >Sergeant</roleName> at the horrid rites he saw in progress at the Hindoo
                  temple, would have prompted him to rush in, sword in hand, if he had not been
                  restrained by his <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>, who placed his hand on his arm, whispering in his ear, "Be
                  quiet, my good fellow. We have not seen all yet, or I am much mistaken!"</p>
               <p>There was now a pause of a few moments' duration, only broken by the hissing of
                  the serpent, which, although the Brahmin had ceased his strange monotonous tune on
                  the reed flute, still swayed its head to and fro to the same measure, as if it
                  still proceeded. Then both the Brahmins spoke at once in a sort of recitative
                  chorus, and although <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> strained his sense of hearing to listen, and was a good
                  Hindostanee scholar, he could not make out what they said. A scene, however, soon
                  presented itself, which needed no words to enable the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> fully to
                  comprehend it.</p>
               <p>At a sign from one of the priests of the idol, the Hindoo who was nearest to the
                  archway that opened to the free air, withdrew with a howling reverence to the
                  idol; and then the slow beat of a tom-tom or native drum, was heard, and some
                  half-dozen Sepoys, wearing some portion of the uniform of one of the revolted
                  regiments, made their appearance, surrounding several ferocious-looking natives,
                  who appeared to be dragging along with them some long bundle or package, tied up
                  in cloth, and bound round by a rope.</p>
               <p>The curiosity of the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName> was wound up to the highest pitch to know what this could
                  all mean; but he was not kept long in suspense. At an order from one of the
                  Brahmins, the strange-looking parcel was unrolled and dragged out of the
                  coverings. Apparently more dead than alive, for she could not stand, appeared a
                  young girl, certainly of not more than fourteen years of age; and although her
                  apparel was torn and disordered, the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> recognised it as
                  that worn by the females of the <orgName type="religious">Mahomedan</orgName>
                  races of <placeName type="country">India</placeName>.</p>
               <p>She tried to stand, but was evidently too weak; and <cb n="2"/>she sunk to the floor,
                  uttering piteous cries, but in a low weak voice, as though she were either
                  half-starved, or had been subject to ill-usage sufficient to deprive her of all
                  strength.</p>
               <p>"Wretch!" said one of the Brahmins; "wretch, of an accursed race who deny the
                  ancient gods of <placeName type="country">India</placeName>, your time has come!
                  Your blood shall be an acceptable offering; and all who touch it, or see it flow,
                  shall be more sacred than the brothers of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#siva">Siva</persName>, and shall prevail over
                  the <orgName corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>!"</p>
               <p>"Mercy!--oh, mercy!" sighed the girl.</p>
               <p>"We do not know the word!" said the Brahmin, with an impatient gesture. "You die
                  the death! You it was who gave information to the Feringhee post, at <placeName
                     type="city">Goerka</placeName>, and you die the death!"</p>
               <p>"Oh, no!--no! In mercy spare me! My kindred are rich! They will heap gold upon
                  your shrine! Oh, holy prophet! I am young to die! Mercy! have mercy upon me!"</p>
               <p>"Sergeant?" whispered <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>, hoarsely. </p>
               <p>"Yes, your honour!"</p>
               <p>"Run back the way we came, and bring three or four of your men with you.
                  Quick,--on your life!"</p>
               <p>The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Sergeant</roleName> did
                  not reply to a single word, but darted off, first on his hands and knees, and
                  then, springing to his feet, he flew, rather than ran, down the passage to the
                  great hall.</p>
               <p>"Guard the entrance securely," said one of the priests.</p>
               <p>The Sepoys, with ferocious pleasure, fixed their bayonets, and stood ready to
                  resist all comers.</p>
               <p>"Now, brother!" added the Brahmin to the other, who, gravely nodding his head,
                  brought forth a small bag from behind the idol, from which he took a broad-bladed
                  knife.</p>
               <p>The <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook">Mahomedan girl</addName>
                  utttered shriek upon shriek!</p>
               <p>A ferocious Sepoy darted forward, and twined his large hand in her fair hair, and
                  tried to force her head back, so as to expose her neck to the Brahmin with the
                  knife!</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>
                  could bear no more! Had he felt that he must be alone through all the fearful
                  struggle that must ensue, he would have plunged into the midst of them to save
                  that sweet, delicate young girl from such a death!</p>
               <p>"Hold!" he cried, with a voice that echoed through the place and seemed to
                  paralyze every one in the <placeName type="building">unhallowed
                  temple</placeName>. "Hold! incarnate fiends!"</p>
               <p>His revolver was in his hand, and the first bullet from it hit the ruffian who
                  held the young girl by the hair, and sunk deep into his brain. The feelings of the
                  young officer were too much excited to permit him to stay where he was and fire at
                  the miscreant throng; but, thrusting his revolver back <cb n="3"/>into its belt, he vaulted
                  over the rocky breastwork in front of him; and, sword in hand, rushed at the
                  Brahmin with the knife.</p>
               <p>The Brahmin was a tall and powerful man, and he made a lounge<!--sic--> at the
                  heart of the young offier which, but that his thick buff pistol-belt turned the
                  point aside, would have terminated his career at once.</p>
               <p>"Death to the Feringhee!" shrieked the priest.</p>
               <p>That was his last shriek, for the sword of the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> cleft him to the
                  very eyes!</p>
               <p>The Sepoys, however, seeing that there was but one man, made a rush towards him as
                  soon as they recovered from the first shock of their amazement; but, as they were
                  upon the point of reaching him, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> heard a
                  loud shout from the <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>, who cried to him, "Stoop, your
                  honour!--stoop, your honour, till we give them a volley!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>
                  understood the <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>'s tactics in a moment; and, clasping
                  the young Mahomedan girl in his arms, he flung himself on the floor with her.</p>
               <p>"Fire!" cried the <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>.</p>
               <p>A volley of musketry, on the instant, resounded through the place.</p>
               <p>The cries of the Sepoys, and the curses of the Brahmin, sounded through the smoke,
                  and mingled with the ring of the ramrods of the soldiers as they reloaded.</p>
               <p>"Fire!" again cried the <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>; and another volley rung
                  through the temple.</p>
               <p>"Forward, my boys!" then shouted the <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>; and as the
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</persName> sprung
                  to his feet, and lifted the young girl in his arms, he found himself surrounded by
                  the soldiers, and that the victory was won. Some half-dozen of the Sepoy guard lay
                  on the floor with the dead Brahmin; but the other priest of the hideous temple was
                  nowhere to be seen..</p>
               <p>"A guard to the door!" shouted the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</persName>. "A couple of
                  men, <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>! Shoot, or bayonet, whoever attempts to
                  pass!"</p>
               <p>"All right, your honour!"</p>
               <p>"Look behind the idol! I saw some one go that way!"</p>
               <p>The <roleName>Sergeant</roleName> darted in the direction pointed out by his
                  officer; and, in a moment, dragged out the other priest, who had flown there for
                  shelter from the bullets: he made a desperate attempt to escape, but a couple of
                  soldiers bound his hands behind him with their belts.</p>
               <p>There was a flush upon the face of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> now, as
                  he cried, "Take him out! Take him outside!"</p>
               <p>"Yes, your honour! And--and--"</p>
               <p>"Shoot him!"</p>
               <p>"Yes, your honour!"</p>
               <pb n="202"/>
               <cb n="1"/>
               <p>The Brahmin uttered a howl as he was dragged into the open air. The report of a
                  couple of muskets in another moment echoed through the neighbouring wood, and the
                     <roleName>Sergeant</roleName> returned. </p>
               <p>"That's done, your honour! Is the poor young thing dead?"</p>
               <p>"No, no!"</p>
               <p>"Why, she is but a child, sir! What bloodthirsty ruffians!"</p>
               <p>"Bloodthirsty, indeed! Post a sentinel here, <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>! I will
                  take this poor young creature, who seems to have fainted, to the ladies: they will
                  understand what to do with her better than I shall!"</p>
               <p>In the excitement of the moment, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> never
                  felt the slight weight of the <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook"
                     >young Mahomedan girl</addName>, but vaulted with her over the rocky
                  breastwork; and hurring down the passage, he appeared in the great hall of the
                  rock temple, saying, "Ladies, here is a present for you!"</p>
               <p>The alarm of the party in the rock temple at the firing and sound of conflict so
                  close to them, had been great; and now that the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, with all the
                  hurry of the recent tumult in hsi manner, burst in upon them, with what looked
                  certainly more like a dead body than anything else, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName> uttered a
                  scream, and there was a general agitation among them all.</p>
               <p>"Don't be alarmed!" added the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>. "It is only a
                     <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook">young Mahomedan
                     girl</addName> that I have rescued from the Brahmins!"</p>
               <p>"Don't bring the creature here!" cried <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName>. "I daresay
                  she is no better than she should be!"</p>
               <p>"But if she is as good, my dear madam," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>, "I
                  think that will be sufficient; and, at all events, if she is as good as she is
                  beautiful, she is good indeed!"</p>
               <p>As he spoke, the young officer laid the still form of the young creature on the
                  floor, of the temple; and when <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie Hope</persName> saw the pale face, and the delicately beautiful
                  features, so pale and wan, as though death had indeed set up his sole dominion
                  there, she rushed forward, exclaiming, "And they have killed her?"</p>
               <p>"I trust not, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Miss
                     Hope</persName>! I don't think they had a chance to do that. My impression is
                  that she has fainted!"</p>
               <p>"Water!--water!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>. "Oh, mother, help her--help her! She is not one of us, by
                  creed or by country, but she is helpless and in need of aid, and then the whole
                  human race are kin!"<!--annotate this motto, quote in headnote--></p>
               <p>"By Jove," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>, "if that girl <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName> is not a
                  trump, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Adrian</persName>!"</p>
               <p>"She is," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                     >Adrian</persName>--"she is all that--that--"</p>
               <p>"Why, hilloa! what a colour you have all of a sudden!" added <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>, as the young
                     <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant</roleName>
                  flushed with pleasure to hear her whom he loved praised.</p>
               <p>By this time, however, all question as to whether the <addName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook">young Mussulman girl</addName> was
                  dead or alive was set at rest, by her opening a pair of the loveliest eyes in the
                  world, and looking timidly about her.</p>
               <p>"Be not alarmed," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>, "you are safe now."</p>
               <p>Tears gushed to the eyes of the young girl; and as she happened to see <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>, she
                  sprung from the stone floor of the <placeName type="building">temple</placeName>,
                  and from <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>'s
                  lap, on which her fair head was lying, and flinging her arms round the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>'s neck, she
                  cried, "My friend! my preserver! Oh, how shall I thank and bless you ever and
                  ever?"</p>
               <p>"Don't think of it," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>, who felt rather embarrassed at the hasty character
                  of the embrace. "Don't think of it, at all. I am only too happy to have been the
                  means of saving you from the Brahmin who would have made a sacrifice of you."</p>
               <p>"Well I am sure," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">the
                     Hon. Miss Flint</persName>, as she procured from some hidden recess of a
                  pocket, a large fan, and placed it open before her eyes. "I never did see such
                  bold, shameless conduct! To be hugging a he<!--sic--> creature like that, and
                  before everybody, too! This is Indian manners and morals, I suppose?"</p>
               <p>"She is a <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#childofnature">child of
                     nature</distinct>, my dear <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName>," said
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>.</p>
               <p>"A child of a fiddlestick, sir," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName>, with an
                  indignant toss of the head. "If she were twenty children of nature, she should
                  behave with propriety."</p>
               <p>The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>
                  gently disengaged the arms fo the young Mahomedan girl from about him, as he said,
                  "And what is your name, my dear?"</p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook">Zeelook</persName>. Ah, they
                  are all killed! Father--mother--all! I am alone, with no one in all the world to
                  love me now, but you!"</p>
               <p>"Really," cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss
                     Flint</persName>, "this is abominable! Ladies, are you going to sit still and
                  hear such things!"</p>
               <p>The others smiled slightly, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName> gently led the
                  girl to the midst of the little party, and she said, "We will all love you, if you
                  will share our fortune with us. We are but fugitives ourselves; but such
                  protection as we can give you, shall be yours freely."</p>
               <p>The young creature hurriedly embraced and kissed <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> on the cheek, but
                  it was plain that she had eyes and ears for little else but <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>. They
                  gave her refreshment, for she was half-famished; <cb n="2"/>then, in answer to their
                  inquiries, she said in a soft, lute-like voice, "Oh, we were too happy, when this
                  dreadful war broke outl and the English officers had been kind to my poor father,
                  when the Brahmins sought his life; so I went to warn them that the bad men were
                  consulting over their destruction, and when I returned my home was a pyramid of
                  fire, and my kindred murdered. The Sepoys seized me, and brought me to the odious
                  temple, where Allah is unknown, and the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#muhammad">Prophet</roleName> a scoff. You
                  rescued me, dear one!" </p>
               <p>Again she flew to the side of the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, and clasping
                  both her arms round one of his, she laid her head gently upon his shoulder, with a
                  sigh of joy!</p>
               <p>"Creature! hussey!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint"
                     >Miss Flint</persName>. "How dare you? I wonder at such unblushing conduct! Of
                  course, you guess he is a single man, and think you will get settled?"</p>
               <p>A peal of laughter from the whole party, which they could not resist, followed
                  this speech, and the <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook">Mahomedan
                     girl</addName> shrink back, saying faintly, "Ah, what have I done?"</p>
               <p>"Nothing! my dear, good <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook"
                     >Zeelook</persName>," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>.
                  "Nothing at all!"</p>
               <p>"Ah, yes! I am unveiled before men!"</p>
               <p>"Never mind that. You see that the English ladies do not veil; so cast aside that
                  notion, and remain with them. Can you tell me the name of the station at which you
                  warned the English officers of the approach of the Sepoys?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, yes, love. It is called <placeName type="city">Audab</placeName>."</p>
               <p>"Ah! That is on the road to <persName type="city">Agra</persName>. If there is a
                  force there, we cannot do better than to try to join it."</p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hannibal
                     Hawkins</persName>!" cried <persName>Miss Flint</persName>.</p>
               <p>"Madam!"</p>
               <p>"Weill you explain to your heathen, if you please, that dear and ove are not fit
                  expressions to be used to single men!"</p>
               <p>"Don't you do any such thing, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal</persName>," laughed
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>. "I only
                  wish she would call me such names. My ears tingle to hear them from her pretty
                  lips!"</p>
               <p>"Sir!" added <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss
                     Flint</persName>; "please to increase your distance from me!"</p>
               <p>"With pleasure, madam."</p>
               <p>"Nay, nay," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>; "don't let us quarrel about the artless expressions of
                  gratitude of this young girl. She associates no shadow of harm by such ters, and
                  we must not judge her by our own old European fashions. I would not check her for
                  the world."</p>
               <p>"Nor I!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                     Hope</persName>, kissing her.</p>
               <p>"Nor I!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName>.</p>
               <p>Even <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshope">Mrs. Hope</persName>
                  joined in the general exculpation of the poor <addName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook">Mahomedan girl</addName>; and only
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshawkins">Mrs. Hawkins</persName>
                  looked a little doubtful on the subject.</p>
               <p>More important matters, however, than the settlement of points of female etiquette
                  now called for the attention of the party. The day was sinking, and a dim twilight
                  was gathering in the valleys, so that if they did not intend--which assuredly they
                  did not--to take up their quarters for the night in the rock temple, it was time
                  to think of moving.</p>
               <p>A couple of the soldiers, with the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Sergeant</roleName>, were sent out as
                  scouts, to reconnoitre the route from the entrance to the temple and they reported
                  that all was still, only in one quarter of the sky, over the tree-tops, they
                  thought there was a strange reddish light which was not altogether natural.</p>
               <p>"It is likely enough some conflagration," said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, as he stepped
                  to the open space in front of the temple. From thence he himself saw the strange
                  aspect of the heavens in the quarter that had attracted the attention of the
                     <roleName>Serjeant</roleName>; and as even in the few moments that he looke dat
                  it the intensity of the red glare altered several times, he no longer had any
                  doubt but that it was a large fire of some sort.</p>
               <p>"It is now time to march," he said, as he returned to the inner part of the
                  temple. "Let us hope that we shall soon find some means of enabling you all to
                  ride, ladies; but at present we ave no resource but to go on foot."</p>
               <p>They all cheerfully rose, and prepared for a night march in the direction of
                     <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>, to which they still directed their
                  hopes, in the full belief that there was a sufficiently strong British force there
                  to hold the place. In a few minutes they all quitted the <placeName
                     type="building">rock temple</placeName>, which had been to them a most welcome
                  place of shelter, and commenced the march</p>
               <p>The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> went
                  forward himself, with two of the soldiers as a sort of advanced guard, and the
                  main body of the party, with the exception of a rear-guard of two others of the
                  soldiers, and the <roleName>Corporal</roleName>, followed at about a hundred and
                  fifty paces distant.</p>
               <p>The cessation of what may be properly called daylight is quick in <placeName
                     tyoe="country">India</placeName>, and by the time they had reached a quarter of
                  a mile from the rock temple the large lustrous stars shone out sweetly from the
                  deep blue sky. The moon would not rise until late, so that the night was about as
                  dark as itwould be in that fair clime, and the banian trees, of which they met and
                  passed several groups, sent dark shadows across their path. A soft <cb n="3"/>delicious
                  stillness was in the air, and the silence was only broken by the drowsy hum of
                  some of the insect tribe, whose habits are altogether nocturnal.</p>
               <p>Once only, in the distance, they heard th ecry of a jackall, and then some large
                  bird of prey passed over the heads of the party, flapping its long heavy wings in
                  the night air.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>
                  had, in addition to the watchfulness which was necessary to be kept up, for fear
                  of rousing some enemy, to be continally peering about him to make sure that he was
                  on the right path. Once before--but it was some years ago--he had ridden from
                     <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName> to <placeName type="city"
                     >Cawnpore</placeName>, and he thought he should be able to track the way again
                  with certainty, but still he had a doubt if he were quite right or not, more than
                  once or twice.</p>
               <p>"Halt!" he said, suddenly; "we are close to a village here, which I recollect; and
                  we ought to pass through it, although whether it will be prudent or not I can
                  scarcely say. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>! <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>! Come here!"</p>
               <p>"What is it?"</p>
               <p>"Do you know the village close to here?"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> glanced
                  about him, and then replied, "To be sure I do. I know it now. We must march
                  through it, for if we don't, we shall deviate into some low marshy ground, which,
                  on drained strips, is planted with rice; and if once we get into the water
                  channels and rice-fields we may wander about for hours."</p>
               <p>"Then you think we should push on?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, yes; at once."</p>
               <p>"Forward, then!--I still lead the way. We may pass through the village unobserved.
                  Advise silence on all."</p>
               <p>This was done; and, in addition to the silence of the party, they trod as lightly
                  as they could, and were soon among the wretched huts of which the village was
                  composed.</p>
               <p>Notwithstanding all their caution--though it was impossible that a party of such
                  numbers could pass through the village without some little noise--as they
                  expected, a door suddenly opened, and a man as suddenly appeared at it, with a
                  torch of resinous wood in his hand, which at once sent a bright, flickering glare
                  upon the whole party.</p>
               <p>"Quick, march!" cried the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>. "Get clear of the houses as soon as you all can!"</p>
               <p>They all quickened their steps, and then a bright flare of light suddenly shot
                  from a heap of dry grass, which had evidently been set light to that it might
                  serve as a kind of beacon. A shout of some fify or sixty voices rung through the
                  air; and just as the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>, who had flown to the rear, got his party past the last
                  hovel in the village, shots began to be fired in rapid succession.</p>
               <p>Whether this was merely an attack for the sake of plunder on the part of the
                  villagers, or they had any of the revolted Sepoys at hand, was a point on which
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> felt some anxiety, but which at the moment he had no means
                  of deciding. He, therefore, still pushed on, till getting clear of the village, he
                  came upon a number of logs of trees, lying across the roadway in such a fashion,
                  that it would have been quite out of the question for any carriage to have
                  effected a passage; and, indeed, good horsement could hardly have picked their way
                  through the intricacies of the obstruction.</p>
               <p>That these newly felled trees were there placed for the express purpose of
                  obstructing the flight of fugitives in vehicles, there could be little or no
                  doubtl but the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>, with a military eye, saw at once, that if they were an
                  obstruction in one respect, they formed a good defence in another.</p>
               <p>"Halt!" he cried, as he brought his party to the logs. "We won't be huned a mile
                  or two by the rabble of a village! Here, my men, just place some of these lighter
                  trunk<!--sic--> of trees upon the other! That will do! Now, where is the
                  enemy?"</p>
               <p>So admirable was the disposition of the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, that in a very
                  few minutes, by the aid of the logs, he was pretty fairly and securely
                  intrenched.<!--sic--></p>
               <p>The villagers, with torches, came yelling on; and when they got near to the logs,
                  they fired several muskets at the fugitives. A ball slightly touched the
                     <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>, who said, "Shall we give them a volley,
                  sir!"</p>
               <p>"Wait a moment! The road narrows hereabouts! They will be closer directly!"</p>
               <p>Scarcely anticipating resistance from so small a party, the villagers, to the
                  number of about a hundred, came rushing on in a wild disorderly throng,
                  brandishing knives and tulwars; while those who had muskets loaded and fired as
                  quickly as they could.</p>
               <p>"Now," said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>--"all ready?"</p>
               <p>"Ready, sir!" said the <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>.</p>
               <p>"Aim low, my men! Fire!"</p>
               <p>The volley fell into the very thick of the rabble rout, and every bullet told
                  once, if not twice. Roaring cries of pain arose, and the torches were flung aside,
                  and a general retreat ensued, which, in a few moments, left not a living enemy
                  upon the field. Some dark</p>
               <pb n="203"/>
               <cb n="1"/>
               <p>objects lying in the roadway, though, sufficiently testified to the fact that
                  the volley had not been without its effect.</p>
               <p>"That will do," said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>. "They will not attack us again! They have had enough of
                  us! Let us resume our march!"</p>
               <p>"Hold!" said <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant
                     Adrian</roleName>. "I hear the tramp of horses' feet! Ah! who, and what, is
                  that?"</p>
               <p>A single horseman galloped up to within twenty feet of the logs of trees by which
                  the road was barred, and dim as the night light was, there was no mistaking the
                  fact of his being a Sepoy cavalry man. His accoutrements glittered faintly, and
                  they could see that his drawn sword was in his hand.</p>
               <p>"Ho, Sahibs!" he cried. "Whither fly you from friends?"</p>
               <p>"What regiment?" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>, sternly.</p>
               <p>"That!" repied the Sepoy soldier; and having, unobserved by the party behind the
                  trees, possessed himself of both of his holster-pistols, one in each hand, he
                  fired them right at the head of the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>; and them, by
                  the pressure of his knees, wheeling round his horse, while he lay quite flat on
                  his back, he was off at a gallop before any one could find time to act against
                  him.</p>
               <p>"That's some close touch," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>, as he
                  dabbed up some blood from his cheek, in which a bullet had made a furrow about
                  skin deep.</p>

               <p>"Are you hit, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Hannibal</persName>?" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>.</p>
               <p>"Well I hardly know yet, but I think it's all right! Hang the fellow, he did it
                  cleverly enough!"</p>
               <p>"Cavalry! cavalry!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                     >Lieutenant Adrian</persName>. "They are upon us!"</p>
               <p>"Not yet, I think!" shouted the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>.</p>
               <p>With a tramp that shook the ground, a troop of revolted cavalry, probably on their
                  route from some out-station to <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>, charged
                  up to the logs, no dount thinking them a trifling obstruction, and that they would
                  soon sabre the small English party.</p>
               <p>"Fire!" cried the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName> again ; and the volley checked the horsemen in full career,
                  with the exception of three, who leaped over the logs. One, a gigantic Sepoy, made
                  a ferocious cut at <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>, whcih with difficulty he parried, but in doing so his foot
                  caught in a projecting branch from one of the trees, and he stumbled to his
                  knees.</p>
               <p>Again the Sepoy raised his sword and uttered a wild shout of triumph, when a shot
                  came right over the shoulders of the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> as he was
                  struggling to rise, and, hitting the savage in the face, hurled him from his
                  horse.</p>
               <p>The other two cavalry men were quickly disposed of by the soldiers, and the three
                  horses were seized at once, as spoils of war. The <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> struggled now to
                  his feet, half stunned by the blow that the Sepoy's sword had given him as it beat
                  down his guard; and he called out, "Who fired that shot? Who killed the
                  fellow!"</p>

               <p>"Ah, I was near you!" said the <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook"
                     >Mahomedan girl</addName>, as she crouched at his feet with his own revolver in
                  her hand, which he recollected he had placed close behind him on one of the fallen
                  trees.</p>
               <p>"And you saved me?"</p>
               <p>"I am happy!" she replied, as the tears flowed from her eyes. "They tell me I must
                  not say I love you--that I must not embrace you--but I can defend you!"</p>
               <p>"My dear <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook">Zeelook</persName>,
                  I love you, though, and all the world and all the old maids in it shall not
                  prevent me from saying so, and embracing you!"</p>
               <p>As he spoke, he caught the young girl in his arms and kissed her cheek. She
                  trembled like a frightened bird; but before another word could be spoken, or
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName>
                  could express her disapprobation of the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>'s conduct, the
                     <roleName>Sergeant</roleName> called out, "We must evacuate the position, your
                  honour. Look what they are at now!"</p>
               <p>The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> did
                  look, and a pang of dismay came across his heart as he now saw the Sepoys dragging
                  up a gun, which, although by its size probably only a nine-pounder, yet would, if
                  efficiently served, soon play havoc with their little entrenchment.</p>
               <p>"Heaven help us now!" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>; "but we must be
                  off! Cavalry and artillery! What are we to do?"</p>
               <p>The Sepoys crowded round the gun with blazing torches and such shouts of
                  exultation, that it was pretty clear what their opinion was of its efficacy. Close
                  to the side of the wood was the little copse from which the trees had been cut to
                  stop the road; and as the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName> glanced around him, he thought that there they would at
                  least be better protected rom the horsemen. He caught the
                     <roleName>Sergeant</roleName> by the arm, and whispered in hsi ear,
                     "<roleName>Sergeant</roleName>, keep up a fire from these logs in ront, so as
                  to shroad us a little with the smoke, and let your men take off their jackets and
                  caps, and bestrew them about the logs and branches, so as to look, in the
                  uncertain light, like men lying hidden."</p>
               <p>"I understand, sir!"</p>
               <p>The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> flew
                  to where the ladies were cowering <cb n="2"/>down in alarm, and got them to display a few
                  shalws and spare clothing upon the trunks of the felled trees. </p>
               <p>The <roleName>Sergeant</roleName> and three men kept up a desultory fire on the
                  Sepoys, assisted by <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName> and his father, until the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> said, in a low
                  but distinct voice, "Stoop low, all of you, and follow me!"</p>
               <p>The firing cease, and stooping so low tha they could not be readily seen behind
                  the breastwork of logs, they all passed, to the right, into the little wood.</p>
               <p>It was at this moment that the Sepoys, who were but amateur gunners, fired their
                  first round shot, and it fell crashing amidst the logs. They then tired to get up
                  a cheer, and by the flame of their torches they still fancied they saw the party
                  of English soldiers and fugitives crouching down amid the logs. Again and again
                  they loaded and fired, but the stillness and the silence among the logs alarmed
                  the so much that they hesitated to advance, and the cavalry men manifestly hung
                  back, fully anticipating a warm reception if they ventured on another charge.</p>

               <p>---</p>
            </div>
            <head>
               <date when="1858-04-03">Saturday, April 3, 1858</date>
            </head>
            <pb n="161"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch16">CHAPTER XVI.</head>
               <p>THE SISTERS AND <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook"
                     >ZEELOOK</persName>.—THE STREAM AND THE ESCAPE.</p>


               <p>TREADING almost in each others' footsteps, and preserving a complete silence, the
                  party who had so adroitly left the little entrenchment of logs followed <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> through
                  the wood. As they went, they heard the cannonade going on at their abandoned
                  position; and at times, no, as they got further and further out of the hearing of
                  the Sepoys, a smothered laugh would come from one of the soldiers at the thought
                  of the successful <emph>ruse</emph> that had been played upon their foes.</p>
               <p>By the time the gun had been fired about a dozen times, our friends were nearly
                  half a mile from the spot, and they found the wood suddenly closed, and that they
                  were close to the banks of a little stream which wound its way lazily between one
                  high bank and one low one--the low one, which was nearly laved by the water, being
                  the opposite to that on which they stood.</p>
               <p>With no small difficulty they had succeeded in bringing the cavalry horses with
                  them, although one of them was badly wounded, and bled much as they led him
                  along.</p>
               <p>On emerhing from the trees, the night sky appeared to be wonderfuly bright, and
                  they guessed that the moon was near to its rising.</p>
               <p>"Now, brother, where are we?" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>; "for I must
                  confess that I am out of my latitude."</p>
               <p>"And I," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>.</p>
               <p>There was a pause of irresolution; and then the <addName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook">Mahomedan girl</addName> was brought
                  forward by <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                     Hope</persName>, as she said, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook">Zeelook</persName> knows the place
                  well, she says, and can guide us."</p>
               <p>"That is providential!" exclaimed the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>. </p>
               <p>"Yes," said the girl. "The stream is named the <geogName type="river"
                     >Jeed</geogName>, and it runs through a valley here at hand, and then across
                  the high road to <placeName type="city">Agra</placeName> again.</p>
               <p>"That will do, my dear <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook"
                     >Zeelook</persName>!" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>; "and now each
                  of these troop-horses will easily carry two ladies, and that will do for six of
                  you."</p>
               <p>"I can walk," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook"
                     >Zeelook</persName>, as with a rapid glance around she saw that there were six
                  ladies without her.</p>
               <p>"Oh!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>,
                  "we will take it by turns, dear <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook">Zeelook</persName>--that is, you and
                  I. When you have ridden some way you will alight and I will ride."</p>
               <p>"You first," said the girl, kissing <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>'s hand as she
                  spoke.</p>
               <p>"No, I am far from tired."</p>
               <p>"Settle it among you," said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, as he made as
                  skilful preparations as he could for the comfort of the other ladies on the
                  cavalry horses; and when all were mounted but <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook">Zeelook</persName>, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName>, the latter
                  said, "No, sir! No, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hannibal Hawkins</persName>, I do not choose to ride with unprincipled
                  heathens! If <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Miss
                     Hope</persName> rides, I will; but let the creature get down!"</p>
               <p>The fact was that, at the moment <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName> began to
                  speak, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> had
                  prevailed upon <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook"
                     >Zeelook</persName> to ride first, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>, making
                  nothing at all of her light weight, had placed her on the horse.</p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName>, he
                  said, "I do not want to quarrel with a lady; but if you have any regard for me or
                  my family, by whom you have been a well-respected guest, be so good as to speak a
                  little more charitably of this young lady, to whom I owe my life!"</p>
               <p>"Lady?" shrieked <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss
                     Flint</persName>.</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="irishdialect">Arrah, thin</distinct>, ma'am," said an Irish
                  soldier, "do you want to bring the niggers down on us by that <distinct
                     type="irisdialect" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#hubaboo"
                  >hubaboo</distinct>?"</p>
               <p>"Sirm" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss
                     Flint</persName>, "will you be soo good as to try by a court martial, or
                  whatever you may call it, this insolent common soldier?"</p>
               <p>"Hush, madam!--hush! Silence in the ranks! <cb n="3"/>Nay, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook">Zeelook</persName>, sit still! All
                  is well! <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Miss Hope</persName>
                  is not ashamed to ride with you, nor I to hold your bridle, and be your guard!
                  Come, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Miss Hope</persName>,
                  since our friend <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss
                     Flint</persName> chooses a longer march, allow me!"</p>
               <p>The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>
                  lifted <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName>
                  to the saddle, and then <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName> said, "<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName>, I will
                  alight as soon as you please to ride."</p>
               <p>To this obliging offer <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss
                     Flint</persName> only replied by an indignant toss of the head, and a jerk of
                  her aristocratic nose, as if she were intent upon performing the juggling feat of
                  which some sogs are so proud--namely, of jerking a piece of meat off the end of
                  their noses, and then catching it in their mouths before it has time to gravitate
                  to the earth.</p>
               <p>"Now, in the name of heaven, let us go on!" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, "for the gun
                  has ceased firing, and our enemies cannot be very far off!"</p>
               <p>The road by the banks of the stream was broken and irregular, and the horses trod
                  uneasily. The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>, leading the horse on which was <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName> and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook">Zeelook</persName>, took the lead,
                  and that which was ridden by <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                     >Mrs. Fletcher</persName> and her mother followed immediately under the care
                  and guidance of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant
                     Adrian</persName>. Little did this party of sad and anxious fugitives suspect
                  the catastrophe that was at hand.</p>
               <p>They passed on till they suddenly turned the corner of the wood, through which
                  they had passed, and then, to their surprise and horror, a blaze of light from
                  blue-lights<!--sic: gloss this--> and torches flashed upon them, and a roar of
                  voices broke upon their ears.</p>
               <p>They were in the actual presence of some two thousand Sepoys, at the head of whom
                  was some high native chief, or one of the <orgName>royal family</orgName> of
                     <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>, in a magnificent <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmater.xml#howdah">howdah</distinct>, on the back of an
                  elephant, the superb trappings of which swept the ground.</p>
               <p>The Sepoy force and our little party of adventurers seemed to be for the moment
                  equally surprised at the sight of each other; and there was a shout of
                  gratification on one side and sighs of despair on the other.</p>
               <p>"Lost! lost!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>, as he recoiled a step; and intuitively, rather than from
                  any real expectation fo escaping, strove to back the horse he was leading into the
                  wood again; but the other, so close behind it, resisted the movement, and all was
                  confusion in the little cavalcade.</p>
               <p>Screams burst from the lips of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshawkins">Mrs. Hawkins</persName> and
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshope">Mrs. Hope</persName>, and
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>,
                  the latter of whom strove to jump from the horse, and fly with her little one for
                  security into the wood, or anywhere that would take her from the gaze of the
                  Sepoys.</p>
               <p>The <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>, without waiting for orders, gave the world to
                  his men to fire, which, in the face of such force, was useless, if not imprudent;
                  for the rebellion was but at its beginning, and it was scarcely yet known what
                  sort of treatment British prisoners might expect in the hands of the Sepoy
                  princes, of which this man on the elephant seemed to be one of high rank.</p>
               <p>The discharge of the soldiers' muskets into the thick of the Sepoy force, however,
                  brought matters to a climax. Several guns were fired on the English party in
                  teturn, and one shot struck <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon"
                     >Mr. Hawkins</persName> in the breast, and he fell with a deep groan. Another
                  killed the <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>; and then, as if in obedience to an order
                  from the leader on the elephant, the firing ceased, and a rush of some fifty
                  Sepoys, armed with tulwars, was made at the little party. There was a clash of
                  swords, shouts and cries for a few seconds; and of course the issue of such a
                  contest could not be doubtful. All passed with the rapidity of a feverish dream,
                  and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName>
                  found herself still on the horse after it had taken a fearful leap in the middle
                  of the stream that ran close at hand</p>
               <p>It was the <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook">Mahomedan
                     girl</addName> who held the bridle, and who urged the animal forward.</p>
               <p>"On! on!" she cried. "Oh, do not speak! You may yet be saved! On! on! Hold fast
                  for your life!"</p>
               <p>"My sister! Oh, God, my sister and the child!" sobbed <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                  >Jessie</persName><!--typo for Bessie--></p>
               <p>"They follow!! All is well! Oh, no! no! He is lost, and I live! I cannot abandon
                  him! Farewell!"</p>
               <p>The young girl slipped from the saddle, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName> heard a splash
                  in the stream as she alighted in it.</p>
               <p>"No! no!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>. "Oh, stay with us! stay!"</p>
               <p>It was too late, even if the exhortation had had a chance of being effectual.
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook">Zeelook</persName> was
                  gone, but <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>,
                  as the horse she was on splashed through the stream, heard the snorting and rapid
                  swimming of another close at hand to her. The fact was, that with the following or
                  imitative power, which si so strongly developed in animals, the horse that was
                  close to that ridden by <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName> and the <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook"
                     >young Mahomedan girl</addName> had leaped into the stream after its companion,
                  but it only had one rider. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#volumina"
                     >Volumina Hawkins</persName> had, in the first terror of the attack of the
                  Sepoy force, sprung screaming to the ground.</p>
               <pb n="204"/>
               <cb n="1"/>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> turned to
                  see who it was that followed, and in the dim light she caught a glance at her
                  sister, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName>. </p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>, is that you?"</p>
               <p>"Yes! Oh, yes! I have saved my dear one!"</p>
               <p>"Alas! Are we alone?"</p>
               <p>"I know not! <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                  >Bessie</persName>! <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>! Do you hear those awful sounds! Oh, sister, let us pray,
                  for surely our last hour has come! How can we, two helpless females, hope to
                  escape alone through this fearful land?"</p>
               <p>"Who shall say?" replied <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>. "God is with us, and the life he has given to us we are
                  bound to preserve as best we can! On, sister, on!"</p>
               <p>The sounds that met the ears of the sisters were indeed fearful. There were cries
                  and shrieks, and shouts of exultation, and the clash of weapons; and now and then
                  the call of a bugle or the tap of a drum in the Sepoy ranks; and as all these
                  sounds mingled strangely with each other as the sisters increased their distance
                  from the scene of conflict, they felt their hearts sink within them, and even
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> tried to
                  turn her horse's head, and to stretch her arms in the direction of the spot they
                  had left, as she cried, "No! no! I cannot bear this! It is too dreadful! Better,
                  better far that we should perish together!"</p>
               <p>"Oh, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, what
                  mean you?"</p>
               <p>"Return! return! There seems something base in thus flying from those with whom we
                  have gone through so many perils! Our mother, too! Oh, God, keep us and direct us
                  now!"</p>
               <p>"My child! My dear little one!" cried <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>, as she burst
                  into an agony of tears. "Oh, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>, let me hold this dear one to life and safety while I
                  can!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>'s tears
                  ceased. She sighed deeply.</p>
               <p>"You are right!" she said. "<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                     >Annie</persName>, you are right! We have that young life to look to. On then~!
                  on, in the name of heaven proceed, and let us yet do our best!"</p>
               <p>Again, the horse's<!--sic--> heads were turned away from that fatal wood, but now
                  it became evident that the animals were getting exhausted with the swimming, and
                  one, that on which <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName> rode, stumbled, and plunged completely over-head in the
                  stream.</p>
               <p>"To the bank, sister!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>. "Go to the right! The bank is low!"</p>
               <p>The horses scrambled to the shore, and shook the water from their dripping manes.
                  The moon at this moment rose from behind a clump of trees, and the sisters looked
                  about them with a forlorn hope of being able to come to some conclusion as to
                  where they were.</p>
               <p>It was in vain that <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName> and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie Hope</persName> strained their eyes in all directions, aided by the
                  beautiful moonlight, in order to discover the part of the country where they had
                  landed with the horses from the stream. All was new and strange to them. There
                  were trees~--there was the rippling water!--there were rocks piled up here and
                  there in masses, and a quantity of low brushwood--from which arose, in the night
                  air, the odour of sweet flowers--seemed to go far away to the illimitable darkness
                  around, but there was no house, no hut, or evidences of human habitation. With a
                  gush of tears, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName> called aloud on the young Mahomedan girl by name; but a
                  dismal echo only replied, and the sounds faded away in the fearful solitude around
                  them! </p>
               <p>"She is gone!--she is gone!" sobbed <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, "and we are alone
                  in this fearful land! Oh, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                     >Annie</persName>, what will become of us now? All that we loved are lost to
                  us; and she, who preserved us, has gone from us! She was not of our race, she was
                  not of our creed, but her heart was human!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName> seemed
                  stupified<!--sic-->, for a few moments, by despair: she could not strain her child
                  to her breast, and seek to drain the water of the stream from its long fair curls.
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> clasped
                  her hand and stilled her sobs, for there was now come on the slight night-wind,
                  the wild sounds of strife; and that strange light that the party had before
                  observed on a particular part of the heavens, appeared to blaze out again with a
                  fresh vigour. Then there was the loud sullen boom of a cannon which, in its
                  reverberations, for a moment absorbed all other sounds.</p>
               <p>The sisters clung to each other in silence. That sound seemed to forebode some
                  catastrophe the nature of which they could not guess, but which on that very
                  account appeared full of strange terror. </p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>," said
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, "dear
                  sister! It is still our duty to return, if we can, to those who are so near and
                  dear to us! You have refused once--Oh, think again?"</p>
               <p>"Kill me!--kill me!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName>, "and then go! I cannot!--I have but one thought! It is
                  here!--here!"</p>
               <p>
                  <emph>(To be continued in our next.)</emph>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
