<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model hcorresp="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!--<?xml-model hcorresp="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<!--
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/xsl" href="../xsl/rymer.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/css" href="../style.css" alternate="yes"?>
-->

<?xml-model href="../schema/sepoys.schema.xml" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Sepoys; Or, Highland Jessie: an electronic edition</title>
            <author>James Malcolm Rymer</author>
            <author>
               <persName type="pseudo">M. J. Errym</persName>
            </author>
            <editor>Rebecca Nesvet</editor>
            <editor>Rae X. Yan</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Rebecca Nesvet</publisher>
            <publisher>Rae X. Yan</publisher>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <idno>sepoys</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct xml:id="installment9" prev="sepoys.4.03.xml#installment8"
               next="sepoys.4.17.xml#installment10">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter XVII: The Beleaguered Force in Cawnpore</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-03-20"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter XVIII: The Attack--The Well, and the Rescue.</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-04-10"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <!-- Information about the encoding of the text -->
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Information about the project itself (goals, organization, activities)</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Information about how the texts in a collection were chosen or excerpted</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="unknown">
               <p>Information about treatment of errors in the source (silently corrected, etc.)</p>
            </correction>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Information about normalization practices (e.g. treatment of roman numerals,
                  spelling, etc.)</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation form="std">
               <p>Information about treatment of quotations (preservation of original quotation
                  marks, etc.)</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="hard">
               <p>Treatment of the hyphenation of the source</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Information about whether and how the text has been segmented (mostly for
                  linguistic purposes)</p>
            </segmentation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Information about any interpretive information added to the text</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="installment">
            <head>
               <date when="1858-04-10">Saturday, April 10, 1858</date>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="../facsimiles/sepoys.4.10.png"/>
            </figure>
            <pb n="209"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch17">CHAPTER XVII.</head>
               <head>THE BELEAGUERED FORCE IN <placeName type="city">CAWNPORE</placeName></head>

               <p>THE despairing tone in which <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                     >Mrs. Fletcher</persName> spoke, at the same time pressing her little one in
                  her arms, assured <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                     Hope</persName> that it was in vain to urge any course which looked like
                  seeking danger. She flung her arms around her sister's neck, as she said, "Be
                  calm!--OH, be calm, dear <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                     >Annie</persName>! The same providence that has protected us till now, will
                  protect us still! You recollect the counsel we have?--the counsel that so well
                  accorded with your own thoughts and feelings? It was to seek the route to
                     <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>! </p>

               <p>"Yes. My husband is there!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>. "On!--on!--Oh, let
                  us on!"</p>

               <p>"Alas, I know not the path! Yet let me think! Oh, how the hurry of these events
                  drive things from the memory? Did not some one say that by following the course of
                  this little stream, we should find it again across the high-road, or track to
                  Cawnpore?" inquired <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>.</p>

               <p>"Yes!--yes! I heard that!" hastily replied <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>.</p>

               <p>"Oh, then, in the name of heaven, let us not seek any modes of conveyance but that
                  which nature has furnished us with! Come, dear <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>, we will follow the
                  bank of the stream of foot; and we shall be far less likely to be seen than if we
                  rode on horseback! Let me carry the little one?"</p>

               <p>"No!--no! Not while life if mine! No!--no!"</p>

               <p>There was a strange and almost maniacal manner <cb n="2"/>about <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName> as she clung
                  to her child, and would not let even her much-loved sister, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, aid her with it,
                  which gave to the heart of the young girl a pang of alarm, that possibly the
                  fearful events of the last few hours and days, had affected the intellect of her
                  sister. She strove to soothe her by words of hopefulness and loving kindness!--by
                  talking of possible meetings in days to come with those she had loved so
                  dearly!--and the sounds of the sobs of the young mother, as her poor heart felt
                  the soft influence of the kind intention, fell gratefully on the ears of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope </persName>, and
                  encouraged her in exhorting her sister to bear up against the numerous perils that
                  surrounded them, and yield not to the almost overwhelming pressure of
                  misfortune.</p>

               <p>And so these desolate ones proceeded sadly on their way, with a hostile country
                  around them, and the bright stars of heaven above them--with no one to cheer
                  them--no arms, even could they have used them, wherewith to defend
                  themselves--little knowledge of their route--everything to dread, and so little of
                  hope mingled in the bitter draught of their sad destiny, that they seemed as if
                  led by some invisible chain to execution. And so delicately nurtured, too, as they
                  had been, so carressed<!--sic-->, and--if we may use the expression--so pampered
                  in the lap of luxury, that even the winds of heaven had not been permitted to
                  visit their cheeks too roughly, ow all unfitted they were to buffet with the
                  world, and encounter the lowering storm that was bursting over <placeName
                     type="country">India</placeName>! </p>

               <p>The way was rought; long branches crawled along the rugged route, and entangling
                  themselves among the feet of the poor wayfarers, both wounded and impeded them.
                  Now and then, either it was real, or fancy depicted the gliding motion of some
                  snake-like reptile, as, with a shivering speed, it shot away from before them.
                  Then they came to a portion of the river's bank, which was a kind of quick-sand,
                  deep into which they trod at every step, while the water oozed and bubbled up
                  around their feet.</p>

               <p>And they heard no sound but the occasional cry of a jackal in the woods, and, now
                  and then, the faint twittering of insect things, disturbed amid the brushwood
                  close to the stream!</p>

               <cb n="3"/>
               <p>"Sister?--dear <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                     >Mrs. Fletcher</persName>, "I repent me--"</p>

               <p>”Of what, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                  >Annie</persName>?”</p>

               <p>"I refused to let you take the little one. You are stronger than I am!--you may
                  reach some place of safety, and save this dear one and yourself! Teach it to pray
                  for its poor mother!--to bless her name! Say that--that--"</p>

               <p> "<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>! <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>!--what in the name of
                  heaven mean you?" exclaimed <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>, in a tone of alarm and consternation, as <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName> suddenly
                  stopped and despairingly cried,-- </p>

               <p>"I can go no further! Leave me here to die! Take the dear one and go on--"</p>

               <p>"Never!--never in life, dear <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                     >Annie</persName>! We will surely, live or die together; and even
                  now--look!--what is that admit those trees? I see a twinkling light! There may be
                  some human habitation, and we may get shelter! Oh, surely, let what wars the
                     <orgName type="religious">Hindoos</orgName> may wage against men, they cannot
                  deny women and children! There, dear <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>!--do you not see it?
                  A light like a large star. It shines among some bushes so serenely, and so
                  hopefully! Strive yet a little! You are better now! You walk bravely! That is
                  well! Ah, dear <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                  >Annie</persName>, in some happy home, with all those whom we love about us, who
                  shall say that we may not yet talk over the events of this now fearful-seeming
                  night! <!--compare with end of String of Pearls-->On!--on!--see, the light
                  brightens! There is a hut or bungalow of some sort! They will not be Sepoys,
                  there, but ryots--possibly some zemindar, or proprietor. We shall have a a
                  welcome, dear sister! Yet a little further! Think of your husband; and that every
                  step is et nearer and nearer still to him, and how he longs to hold you and this
                  dear little one to his heart: and see, the river now winds to the left! It is to
                  cross the road as we have been told. Cheer up, hear heart, and all may yet be
                  well!"</p>

               <p>Thus encouraging--thus entreating and aiding poor <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher's</persName> faltering
                  steps with what strength she had, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> played the
                  ministering angel to her suffering sister!</p>

               <p>The light they had seen moving among the trees brightened as they approached it ;
                  and they saw that it streamed</p>

               <pb n="210"/>
               <cb n="1"/>

               <p>from the open casement of a low-roofed bungalow, which, either was the isolated
                  dewlling of some <!--sic-->
                  <foreign xml:lang="ur" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#zemindar"
                  >zemindar</foreign>, or the commencement of a native village. A small cleared
                  space after they had passed a littlr way from the river to the right among a clump
                  of trees, brought them to a ruinous-looking shed at some little distance from the
                  bungalow, and there they paused ; for a dog began to bark furiously, and they
                  dreaded to advance. </p>

               <p>"Hush!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                  >Bessie</persName>; and she could not but tremble as she spoke, despite all the
                  hopeful things she had said to her sister,--"hush, dear <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>! Let us wait here for
                  a moment! The barking of the dog may bring out some one; and then we shall perhaps
                  be able to judge better, if it be safe to ask the hospitality we so much
                  need!"</p>

               <p>"You tremble, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>?" </p>

               <p>"Oh, no, no,--that is, I am chilled! The night air is cold even in <placeName
                     type="country">India</placeName>. Oh, hush! Crouch down here in the shadow of
                  the trees. See--see, some one has come out!"</p>

               <p>The alarm brought to the door of the bungalow a Hindoo, who carried with him a
                  lighted brand of resinous wood, which he held above his head with one hand, while
                  he shaded his eyes with the other, and stroveto pierce the obscurity beyond him to
                  see if any one was approaching to account for the alarm that the dog had given.
                  The appearance of this man was wild and ferocious, and the lower part of his face
                  was bound up with a white cloth, on which there were dark stains as if of blood.
                  The handle of a <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#creese"
                  >creese</distinct>, or dagger, projected from his girdle; and take him or all in
                  all, his appearance was certainly not calculated to inspire the sisters with faith
                  in any appeal to his benevolence.</p>

               <p>"Down!--down" they heard him say to the dog. "The curse of bad spirits be upon
                  you!"</p>

               <p>The animal was silent.</p>

               <p>The Hindoo then muttered something to himself; and placing the torch in the cleft
                  of a tree, close at hand, he retired hastily into the bungalow.</p>

               <p>"Annie," whispered <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>, "I will not trust that man! Can you, by any possibility,
                  walk further?"</p>

               <p>"I will try! Oh, yes--yes! Save me, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, save me!"</p>

               <p>"Be calm! This way!--this way!"</p>

               <p>Even as <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>
                  spoke, the man came out of the bungalow againl and this time he had a cloth about
                  his head and shoulders, and a musket in his hand. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> drew her sister
                  back hastily among the trees, and fear for a few moments overcome <!--sic--> all
                  sense of fatigue in the frame of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>, as they took
                  their way through briars and brushwood, whither they scarcely knew; but they
                  suddenly came to a low paling, a portion of which was composed of twisted branches
                  of the banian tree. Indeed, it was rather a kind of natural hedge, with numerous
                  large openings among the branches of the shrubs and trees that formed it, than a
                  paling, although art had evidently assisted at its formation. </p>

               <p>By a sort of instinct, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName> dragged her sister through one of the gaps; and they then
                  observed a little outhouse or building, no doubt devoted to some agricultural
                  purpose connected with the surrounding rice and indigo fields. The feeling, that
                  any shelter was a short of security, so long as it had a roof to it, prompted
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> to urge
                  her sister to enter this place; and stooping low, to get through its doorway, they
                  found themselves evidently in a fruit storehouse, the floor of which was thickly
                  strewn with dried grass.</p>

               <p>The odour of the mango, the pomegranate, the guava, the plaintain, and the papaya
                  came strongly on their senses; and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName> sunk, with a
                  deep sigh, in a state of utter exhaustion on the soft grass, which had been laid
                  some foor or so in depth uponthe hard-beaten earthen floor. </p>

               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> made an
                  endeavour to fasten the frail door by which they had entered the place; but she
                  quickly found how futile was such an attempt, so she knelt by it, and with every
                  sense wound up by the occasion to a painful stretch of acuteness, she strove to
                  look into the darkness beyond, and to listen for any sound that might indicate
                  approaching danger. </p>

               <p>A strange creaking noise, like the show progress of wheels over some hard dry
                  road, reached her ears: and then the dog again barked furiously, and she heard the
                  animal silenced by the voice of the Hindoo. The creaking noise of wheels
                  continued; and then to the surprise, as well as the joy, of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, she suddently
                  heard an English voice cry "Halt!"</p>

               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> uttered a
                  cry, and sprang to the side of her sister, whom she embraced and kissed with
                  almost delirious pleasure, saying with catching breath and tearful tones, "There
                  is help! Oh, there is help and dear companionshop without! I hear the blessed
                  tones of <placeName type="country">England</placeName>! Be hopeful and happy, dear
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>! Did I not
                  say that all would be well? I will go see them; and you will hear the deat tones,
                  and see the honest faces of our countrymen!"</p>

               <p>Without waiting for a moment's, reply, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> rushed fromm the
                  outhouse, and called out, "Help, here!--help, me! I heard an <placeName
                     type="country">English</placeName> voice!"</p>

               <cb n="2"/>

               <p>"Who is that?" said some one apparently in pain; and then before another word
                  could be spoken, Hindoo came through the trees with the torch, and holding it up
                  in his left hand, while with his right he clutched a very showy sword, the hilt of
                  which seemed to sparkle as if set with precious stones, he not only gazed upon the
                  scene before him, himself, but enabled <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName> to do
                  likewise.</p>

               <p>It was a strange scene, and, at the first glance, difficult to comprehend. There
                  was a small, half-covered country-waggon, or rather car, drawn by a couple of
                  tired-looking bullocks. The cart was half-full of hay and Indian grasses, on
                  which, pale and faint-looking, lay two English officers, one in a rich cavalry
                  uniform, stained with blood, and torn and hacked in many places ; and the other in
                  that of an officer of the line. Both of these officers had revolvers, which they
                  presented over the rickety side of the cart, although they seemed hardly to have
                  strength to pull the triggers of them, had there been occasion to do so.</p>

               <p>But the most curious part of the cavalcade, if it may be called such, was its
                  escort, which consisted of a cavalry soldier, with his head and left arm bound up
                  in bloodstained rages, and a cavalry sabre in his right hand; while a young and
                  frank-looking girl of some twenty years of age--her face pale with anxiety, but a
                  look of courage and determination in her blue eyes that was a joy to see--brought
                  a soldier's musket to the charge and stood resolutely on the defensive. Her dress
                  was picturesque, for she wore a foraging cap with a gold band and tassel, from
                  beneath which, in long wavy masses, escaped her fair hair, which was of that
                  beautiful colour called golden in the north, and upon which the light from the
                  Hindoo's torch shone as if there were literally threads of gold interwoven among
                  it. A scarf of tartan was wound tightly about her, and set off her fine figure to
                  advantage. Her atititude<!--sic--> combined grace with dignity; and there was a
                  chivalric courage about her, as she there stood with the musket at the charge, and
                  the bayonet gleaming in the flickering light from the Hindoo's torch, that would
                  have won the admiration of a painter.</p>

               <p>So suddenly had all these parties confronted each other-- the cart and its
                  occupants and guard, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                     Hope</persName> and the Hindoo--that for a moment or two, no one uttered a
                  word. But the light had flashed upon the fair face of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, and one of the
                  wounded officers cried out, "English ladies here? Is there a party? Have you
                  guards? If not, would to God we were in a better condition to aid you!"</p>

               <p>"We are but two!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>. "Myself and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>, my sister,
                  the wife of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#fletcher">Major
                     Fletcher</persName>. We had sought temporary shelter in yonder outhouse--"</p>

               <p>"Halt!" cried the young girl with the musket, suddenly. "Another step, and I
                  fire!"</p>

               <p>All eyes were now directed to where she now presented the musket; and they saw the
                  Hindoo, who had made a few steps toward the outhouse, with his hand on the handle
                  of his <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#creese">creese</distinct>, for he
                  had sheathed his rich sword, crouching down, and showing, through his retracted
                  lips, his teeth with a look of snarling rage.</p>

               <p>The tone of the girl was unmistakably Scotch; and it had a kindly sound with it to
                  the heart of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                  >Bessie</persName>. The Hindoo only for a moment suffered his countenance to wear
                  a look of baffled hate; and then, with the facile cunning of his race, he
                  recovered himself and <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#salaamed"
                     >salaamed</distinct> low, as he said, "I am the humble slave of the great
                     <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahibs</distinct>! I live but
                  in the light of the eyes of my lords, the <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</distinct> chiefs! What am
                  I? Nothing! Let my lords order! It is for me to obey! Great is the goodness of the
                  Ma'am <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</distinct> with the
                  musket!"</p>

               <p>"Disarm him, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#wootton"
                     >Wootton</persName>!" said the other officer to the cavalry soldier. "I don't
                  at all like the fellow's looks! Be quick about it!"</p>

               <p>The wounded cavalry soldier quickly deprived the Hindoo of his weapons; and
                  covered as he was by the musket of the young girl, he saw the wisdom of not
                  resisting, although the expression of his countenance, while the operation was
                  going on, was anything but amiable.</p>

               <p>"It is done, sir!" said the soldier, as he saluted the officer who had given him
                  the order.</p>

               <p>"And well done, too!" said the officer, faintly. "How weak I am, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hargrave">Hargrave</persName>! I fear I shall
                  not be able to get on any further!"</p>

               <p>The other officer, who was addressed as <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hargrave">Hargrave</persName> made an attempt
                  to rally his own strength, although it was nearly as far gone as that of his
                  companion, and addressing <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>, he said, "Is it possible, think you, with any regard to
                  safety, to get a night's repose here?"</p>

               <p>"Alas! I know not!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>. "I and my sister are but fugitives like yourselves, and we,
                  too, are weary and would fain rest! My name is <orgName type="family"
                     >Hope</orgName>, and we escaped, with friends, from <placeName type="city"
                     >Delhi</placeName> ; but meeting a force of Sepoys, are all scattered, if not
                  murdered, but ourselves. You will permit us, gentlemen, to join your party! We are
                  so very friendless!"</p>

               <cb n="3"/>
               <p>"Surely, surely!" cried both the officers, and at that moment there was heard the
                  sound of footsteps through the little wood, and pale and anxious, with the child
                  clasped to her breast, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName> appeared. At the first sight of the uniforms of the cavalry
                  soldier and the the officers, she uttered a cry of joy, and the tears gushed from
                  her eyes, as she exclaimed,</p>

               <p>"Saved! saved! Oh, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>, we are saved! Thank heaven, here are dear English
                  faces!"</p>

               <p>"We will do what we can to aid you," said the senior of the two officers; "but you
                  see, ladies, that we are in poor case ourselves! We were both badly wounded at an
                  out station, and had to escape the best way we could; and but for this heroic girl
                  here, and my servant, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#wootton"
                     >Wootton</persName>, we must ere have perished! We are trying to make our way
                  to <placeName type="city">Lucknow</placeName>! We will try, after a rest, if we
                  can crawl along on foot, and you shall have the cart to yourselves. It only holds
                  two!"</p>

               <p>"No, no!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName>, as she trembled with fresh apprehension. "You are both
                  wounded, and it will be our provinces to tend you as bst we may, and heaven will
                  help us all!"</p>

               <p>And now the young girl to whom the officer pointed as so gallant a friend and
                  preserver of the party, handed her musket to the soldier, and advancing kindly to
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcherr</persName>,
                  she said, "You are weary and faint! Let me carry the little one for you! Nay, you
                  may trust me with it; for though but a soldier's daughter, I have the heart of a
                  dear countrywoman of your own I fancy--<orgName typ="family">Hope</orgName> is a
                  good Scotch name!"</p>

               <p>With a gentleness that won the heart of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>, the young
                  girl took the infant and kissed its pale face. They saw a tear fall upon its
                  cheek, as she murmured, "Poor little one! These are sad times, indeed, for the
                  young and the helpless!"</p>

               <p>Sad times for all!" said the officer; "but you must not turn nurse, my good girl!
                  What should we have done without your bold spirit and ready arm? You have saved us
                  more than once from death! You are a heroine, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie</persName>! </p>

               <p>The girl blushed, and in answer to <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>, she drew
                  herself rather proudly to her full height, as she said, "My name is <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie Campbell</persName>! They call
                  me <persName>Highland Jessie</persName>, because I come from dear old <placeName
                     type="country">Scotland</placeName>, the land of the mountain and the flood! I
                  have a woman's heart, but the spirit of my race at times nerves my arm! I have
                  brothers in the service, and there is one who loves me better than a sister in the
                     <orgName type="military">Highland regiment</orgName>! They know not that I am
                  in <placeName type="country">India</placeName>; but I was alone in the <placeName
                     type="region">Highlands</placeName>, father and mother were both with the dead,
                  and I was desolate! They sunk to rest on the bleak mountain saide, without a home
                  or a shelter from the storm! Our home of generations was swept from the face of
                  the land, that the wild deer might be the sole inhabitant of the old glens and the
                  hills, as it was before man raised his <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#shieling">shieling</distinct> to the sky! All
                  were gone--brothers to the wars, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#donald">Donald</persName> with them! I have
                  followed! An officer's lady brought me over as attendant to her children; and I am
                  here now, doing, I hope, my duty, and living with the dear thought that I shall
                  see the kind faces of my kindred yet in this strange land, and that some happy day
                  I shall hear the <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#pibroch"
                     >pibroch</distinct> of my own <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#donald">Donald</persName>! Oh, you should see
                  him in his martial array!--so proud his step, so gallant his bearing, so tender
                  his heart! His blue eyes sparkle in the light, and there is music in his voice!--
                     <persName>Donald</persName>, my own <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#donald">Donald</persName>, who told me that
                  he loved me beneath the fair skies of <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#bonny">bonny</distinct>
                  <placeName type="country">Scotland</placeName>! God's blessing be his shield!" </p>

               <p>The young <placeName type="region">Highland</placeName> girl spoke with rapidity.
                  Her feelings carried her away, and there was a flush of vivid excitement upon her
                  face, as she now dashed away her gathering tears; and, bending with a graceful
                  action before her listeners, she added, "Oh, pardon me! I should not say what I
                  say, but when the old home in the <placeName type="region">Highlands</placeName>
                  looms before my mind, I am near distraught, and out of the fulness of my heart, my
                  lips speak!"</p>

               <p>
                  <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName> was
                  deeply touched by the noble words and graceful dignity of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Highland Jessie</persName>. She
                  sprang forward, and casting her arms around her, she said, "Be our friend,
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie</persName>! Be our
                  dear friend, for such we will esteem you; and if ever fortune smiles upon us
                  again, and these troublous times pass away, no one shall be more dear and honoured
                  with us, than you!" </p>

               <p>"She is a noble girl!" cried the officer, while a faint flush on his pale face
                  shouwed how deeply he felt what he said. "She is a noble girl! My friend,
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hargrave">Colonel
                     Hargrave</persName>, and myself, owe our lives to her ten times over!" </p>

               <p>"God bless her!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hargrave"
                     >Colonel Hargrave</persName>, faintly; "and if this is my last hour of life, as
                  I almost fear it is, I shall die your grateful debtor, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie</persName>!"</p>

               <p>"No, no!" cried Jessie. "Live on! Oh, cheer up; we will have rest yet! Some hut or
                  house is near at hand, and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#wootton"
                     >Wootton</persName> and I will still be your guards!"</p>

               <p>"To be sure, your honours!" said the cavalry sol-</p>

               <pb n="211"/>
               <cb n="1"/>

               <p>dier. "Never give in, <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hargrave"
                     >Colonel</roleName>! All will be right your honour, yet ; and I shall live to
                  see you yet with your regiment! Excuse a poor fellow for trying to cheer your
                  honour!"</p>

               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hargrave">Colonel Hargrave</persName>
                  tried to say something, and then, with a deep sigh, his head fell back, and a
                  deathlike paleness came across his face. </p>

               <p>"God bless you, my dear friend!" said the cavalry officer, as he clasped <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hargrave">Hargrave</persName>'s hand.</p>

               <p>"Water! water!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie"
                     >Jessie</persName>. "Is there any? He is but faint from the loss of blood!"</p>

               <p>"On my eyes be it!" said the Hindoo. "I will fetch water for the <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</distinct>!</p>

               <p>"And I will go with you," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#wootton">Wootton</persName>, "to help you, in
                  case you should forget to come back!"</p>

               <p>"I am my lord's slave, and if the great <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahibs</distinct> will cross the
                  threshold of my dwelling, it is theirs, and all within it. Who am I? Bosh! May the
                  graves of my kindred be defiled if I speal not the truth. May I be the brother of
                  asses, and may evil ones be about me, if I speak ill!"</p>
               <p>---</p>


            </div>
            <p>---</p>
            <head>
               <date when="1858-04-10">Saturday, April 10, 1858</date>
            </head>
            <pb n="211"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch18">CHAPTER XVIII.</head>
               <head>THE ATTACK.--THE WELL, AND THE RESCUE.</head>

               <p>THE hut of the Hindoo, who, with such doubtful faith, led the way for the wounded
                  officers, was soon reached, and with a great affectation of hospitality, he gling
                  its door wide, to admit his visitors.</p>

               <p>"Enter, Lord <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</distinct>!" he
                  said. "Enter the humble house of the lowest of your slaves!"</p>

               <p>The cart was stopped; and with difficulty, for he was badly hurt, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#lane">Colonel Lane</persName>--for he was the
                  wounded cavalry officer--alighted. The infantry colonel was still insensible; and
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#wootton">Wootton</persName>
                  carefully assisted <persName>Jessie</persName> to lift him from the vehicle, while
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel Lane</persName>, with
                  his revolver in his hand, kept an eye on the Hindoo, who would have volunteered
                  his aid, but <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Highland
                     Jessie</persName> warned him off.</p>

               <p>The interior of the hut was rude in the extreme: but it was more spacious than it
                  had at first seemed to be; and there was an inner apartment to it, as well as a
                  sort of loft in the roof, whcih appeared to be reached by a rude ladder made of
                  untrimmed pieces of wood, with the bark still on them.</p>

               <p>The Hindoo busied himself in the preparation of a couch for <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hargrave">Colonel Hargrave</persName>,
                  composed of grass, and some rough country cloth laid over it; and from the inner
                  room he brought a pitcher of water, which <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie</persName> sprinkled on the
                  face of the insensible officer, as well as inducing him to take a small portion
                  between his lips. With a sigh, then, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hargrave">Colonel Hargrave</persName> opened
                  his eyes. </p>

               <p>"Where am I?" he said faintly.</p>

               <p>"All right!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel
                     Lane</persName>. "Cheer up! you will soon be stronger, if we can only get you
                  something to eat, to repair the weakness you are suffering from. You have lost so
                  much blood, my dear friend!"</p>

               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hargrave">Colonel Hargrave</persName>
                  pressed his hand, as he said, in a low tone, "And you too!"</p>

               <p>"Oh, don't think of me! I--I--am--all right."</p>

               <p>The ghastly paleness of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel
                     Lane</persName> alarmed <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>, and she cried, "God help us all! Oh, what can we do? </p>

               <p>"My dear--young--lady, we--we are famishing, almost, as well as being wounded. If
                  we could only get some food!"</p>

               <p>"Here!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie"
                     >Jessie</persName>, as she appeared from a rummage of the hut, and presented on
                  a wooden dish, some rice and milk, and some cooked fruits she had found. "Here is
                  food. It seems all the place affords."</p>

               <cb n="2"/>
               <p>The Hindoo made a gesture of dissent; and, going to a remote corner, he tilted up
                  an earthen vessel, and took from beneath it, on a European plate, an ample portion
                  of a favourite Indian dish called <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#kitchri">kitchri</distinct>, which is compounded
                  of curried fowl, the flesh of the young goat, chillies, and other matters
                  according to taste.</p>

               <p>"May your slace be favoured in your eyes!" he said. "Here is that which the
                     <persName>King of Delhi</persName> might covet."</p>

               <p>The famished officers looked eagerly at the food, and then, with a bow to
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> and her
                  sister, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel Lane</persName>
                  said, "When you are all done, we will begin. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie</persName>, will you preside?
                  for, my good girl, you must want food as badly as we can."</p>

               <p>"Oh, no! no!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie"
                     >Jessie</persName>, "you are wounded; eat first. Do not pause, for we may be
                  all in peril here."</p>

               <p>In good truth, there was no time to stand on any ceremony; and, since anything in
                  the shape of spoons, or other modes of conveying the viands from the dish to the
                  mouth, there were none, each one helped himself and herself as best they could
                  with the help of some <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#chaffratees"
                     >chaffratees</distinct> or native cakes, which the Hindoo produced in pretty
                  good abundance.</p>

               <p>"May my good lords be strengthened!" he said, when he saw that they had cleared
                  the dishes. "Would that I had couches worthy of the repose of <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahibs</distinct>; but here is all!"</p>

               <p>Certainly, the sleeping accomodation was not very inviting, since, with the
                  exception fo the extemporaneous couch on whichlay <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hargrave">Colonel Hargrave</persName>, there
                  was nothing but the bare floor for any one else.</p>

               <p>"I am better!" said the Colonel, as he slowly rose. "Do you, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>, with your
                  little one, take this couch, rude as it is."</p>

               <p>"Nay," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel
                     Lane</persName>; "we may find, no dount, some more grass, and can get some sort
                  of resting-place for the ladies. Our stay here, at best, can be but brief."</p>

               <p>"My lord's words are wisdom!" said the Hindoo. "I will throw down dried grass in
                  abundance from above."</p>

               <p>He indicated the loft as he spoke; and without waiting for any reply to the
                  proposition, he coolly and quietly ascended the rough ladder, and disappeared
                  through the hole in the inner roof or ceiling of the hut.</p>

               <p>"I don't half like to lose sight of him, your honours," said the soldier. </p>

               <p>The little party started at this idea, and they all looked with anxiety towards
                  the rude ladder, up which their unwilling host had ascended. Twenty or thirty
                  seconds elapsed, which, to their anxieties, appeared like as so many minutes, but
                  no dried grass or Hindoo appeared.</p>

               <p>"He plays us false!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie"
                     >Jessie</persName>, as she sprung toward the ladder; but, before she could
                  reach it, it was suddenly pulled up from above; and in a wild, screeching voice,
                  the Hindoo shouted, "Death to the <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee!</distinct>--death! death!" </p>

               <p>Then ensued a crashing sound, and the fall of a heavy body just outside the hut.
                  The Hindoo had broken his way through the frail roof, and allowed himself partly
                  to foll and partly to jump to the ground outside. Another wild yell proclaimed his
                  exultation at his escape; and then something struck the door heavily on the
                  outside, and before any of the party in the hut could resolve upon a course of
                  action, they heard the monotonous sounds of a native drum at no great distance
                  without; and the gleam of some torches came in, through cracks and orifices, in
                  the little wooden structure, quite eclipsing the faint light of the miserable
                  lamp, composed of twisted cloth dipped in oil, which did duty in the hut.</p>

               <p>"We are betrayed!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel
                     Lane</persName></p>

               <p>"And lost!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hargrave"
                     >Hargrave</persName>.</p>

               <p>"No! no!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Highland
                     Jessie</persName>,--"no! no! There may be time yet! They are only villagers! To
                  the cart--to the cart, and we may yet escape!"</p>

               <p>She flew to the door and tried to open it outwards, which it was constructed to
                  do, but it was evident that the Hindoo had succeeded in fastening it in some wat,
                  for it resisted both <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie"
                     >Jessie</persName> and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#wootton"
                     >Wootton</persName>, as if it had been a solid rock.</p>

               <p>"I know what it is," said the cavalry man. "The rascal has got the end of a felled
                  tree against it."</p>

               <p>Mingling with these words from <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#wootton">Wootton</persName>, there came such
                  yells and shouts from without, as might well appal the stoutest hearts; and it was
                  evident that a throng of infuriated villagers, or escaped thieves from some of the
                  revolted stations, were rapidly approaching the hut.</p>

               <p>The situation of the small party of Europeans was indeed most critical, and they
                  might well look at each other as persons destined to death. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> flung her arms
                  around her sister, and for the first time since that horrible escape from
                     <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>, seemed to give way to despair. The
                  lips of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName> moved as though she would speak, but inarticulate sounds,
                  mingled with sobs, alone escaped her.</p>

               <p>The two officers forgot, in the strong excitement of <cb n="3"/>the moment, their
                  debility from wounds ; and, pale as they were, they stood erect, and listening to
                  the sounds without.</p>

               <p> It was <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie</persName> who
                  broke the terrible silence of the party int he hut.</p>

               <p>"Despair not!" she said. "There is yet life, and there is, therefore, yet hope!
                  The doopr may be secured within, surely?"</p>

               <p>She sprung forward to the door of the hut, and the cavalry soldier accompanied
                  her. They found that there were some strong wooden staples in the door-post, and
                  at the back of the door, through which a bar might be passed, if they could find
                  one to answer the purpose; but no such thing presented itself. The Hindoos without
                  raised another shout of triumph, and a shot came through the frail framework of
                  the house, and lodged on the opposite partition.,</p>

               <p>The officers immediately faced the door, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel Lane</persName> said, sternly,
                  "We shall be sacrificed, but we will sell our lives dearly! Would to heaven that
                  our deaths could, by any means, be the deliverance of these helpless ones! Ladies,
                  we bid you adieu! God help you, for we can do no more in this emergency!"</p>

               <p>A rush of Hindoos from without now shook the frail building; and then they heard
                  the unmistakable voice of the proprietor of the hut call out, "Remove the log!
                  remove the log! Sons of burnt fathers, what by you by that senseless effort?
                  Remove the log, and the door opens!" </p>

               <p>"No!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Highland
                     Jessie</persName>, as with the impulse of the moment she seized the musket and
                  slid it thorugh the stapes in the door and door-post,--"no, not yet!"</p>

               <p>A loud shout proclaimed the removal of the log of timber that had kept the door
                  from opening, and then a yell of disappointment, as those without found that it
                  was still fast, notwithstanding all their furious shaking at it.</p>

               <p>"Thank you, Jessie," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane"
                     >Colonel Lane</persName>. "This is a respite, if not a reprieve, my good girl!" </p>

               <p>"Fire!" cried a voice from without; and immediately an irregular discharge of
                  musketry ensued. The whole party within the hut stooped low, and the bullets flew
                  over their heads, crashing through the frail boarding of which the building was
                  composed.</p>

               <p>"Hold!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                  >Bessie</persName>, as the two officers were about to return the fire by random
                  shots with their revolvers, through the thin planking of which the front of the
                  hut was composed,--"hold! Do you hear that?" </p>

               <p>The reverbation of the firing had ceased, and now a dull, heavy knocking at a part
                  of the wall some few feet from the door, was plainly heard, and then a kind of
                  shutter, about two feet square, was removed from the outside, and the face of the
                  Hindoo proprietor of the wretched little abode appeared, distorted by passion, and
                  brandishing an axe in his hand. It was but for an instant that he so showed
                  himsef, for, by the dim light within the place, he saw <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel Lane</persName> raise his
                  revolver to a direct line with his head.</p>

               <p>The sharp report of the pistol and the disappearance of the Hindoo were
                  simultaneous; but the shout he raised when he dropped to the ground without,
                  showed that he was unhurt. </p>

               <p>At this instant <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName> uttered a cry of alarm, and the whole party turning in the
                  direction where she and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName> were, they saw both the sisters pointing with excited
                  gestures to the opening in the roof, leading to the loft, and from which appeared
                  to be dangling some small dark object, which in another moment dropped lightly to
                  the floor, and then springing with a graceful bound to its feet, showed itself to
                  be a young child, wrapped round the middle with a red cloth, but otherwise
                  perfectly unattired. The slight agile form and the sparkling eyes of the little
                  creature, who could not be above six or seven years of age, together with a look
                  of intense surprise on its facr, and a tremor of its libs, which made some gold or
                  gilt baugles<!--sic: bangles or baubles?--> clatter musically together, precluded
                  the notion of either espial or denial from it; but <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel Lane</persName> stepped
                  forward, and laying a hand upon the arm of the little intruder, he said, in
                     <distinct>Hindostanee</distinct>, "Who are you and where do you come from?"</p>

               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#raopatan">Rao Patan</persName>" is my
                  father," said the child, in soft, gentle accents. "I am come home; but he was not
                  within, so I crept to sleep above. <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#salaam">Salaam</distinct>,<distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</distinct>." </p>

               <p>The child made the usual <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#salaam"
                     >salaam</distinct> of the natives to Europeans of rank, and then folding her
                  arms across her breast, she stood submissive and silent. </p>

               <p>"Fire!" cried the voice again from without.</p>

               <p>An instinctive feeling of humanity induced <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel Lane</persName> to press his
                  hand upon the shoulder of the Hindoo child, as he said, "Stoop!--stoop, or you are
                  hit!"</p>

               <p>Again the irregular discharge of musketry from without crashed through the hut,
                  and then, with a rush, some half-dozen Hindoos clambered to the small opening that
                  had been made in the wall, evidently intent on forcing an entrance that way. </p>

               <p>Both the officers fired their revolvers, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#wootton">Wootton</persName> plied his sabre
                  with energy. One of the enemy dropped </p>

               <pb n="212"/>
               <cb n="1"/>

               <p>inside the hut, mortally wounded; and after rolling over twice, and making frantic
                  grasps at the dried grass on the floor, he straightened out his limbs with a
                  spasmodic jerk, and breathed his last.</p>

               <p>The light in the hut had gone out; the concussion of the air from the shots, both
                  within and without the place, had been too much for its frail existence; but
                  through the numerous crevices in the walls of the building, the flare of the
                  torces from without sent plenty of irregular and flickering light into the
                  interior. </p>

               <p>There was now a kind of lull in the attack; no doubt, the vigorous resistance
                  effected by the revolvers of the officers and the sabre of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#wootton">Wootton</persName> taught the
                  invaders of the little post caution. They tried now to accomplish, by treachery
                  and stratagemm, what force--although it might succeed in doing--would cost them in
                  the process more lives. </p>

               <p>"Hearken, <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahibs</distinct>!" said
                  the Hindoo proprietor of the hut from without,--"hearken, <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahibs</distinct>! Hand over what rupees
                  you have, and you all go in safety. On my head be it!" </p>

               <p>By the sound of the voice, this man was just below the little square opening in
                  the wall; and scarcely had he done speaking, when <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel Lane</persName> stepped up to
                  the Hindoo child, and, whispering to her, "Have no fear! I will not harm you!" he
                  sprang with her in his arms to the opening, and holding her up, so that the glare
                  of the torces fell full ipon her face, he dried out, "Another shot, villains--and
                  the life of this hostage is lost!" </p>

               <p>The Hindoo uttered a shriek of despair.</p>

               <p>"My child! my child!--my only one!" he cried. "I thought you far away. What evil
                  destiny has brought you home? My <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#aza"
                     >Aza</persName>! my beautiful! My child!--my child! Mercy! <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahibs</distinct>, mercy!"</p>

               <p>"That will do," said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane"
                     >Colonel</roleName>, as he placed the child in the care of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie</persName>; adding, "Look to
                  her well. God knows I would not hurt a hair of her head, but the sight of her may
                  yet save us from this dilemma."</p>

               <p>"It may indeed," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie"
                     >Jessie</persName>, as she soothed the trembling child, who, at the moment,
                  believed her destruction to be certain, notwithstanding the whispered words of the
                     <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonel">Colonel</roleName>. </p>

               <p>"Oh, no, no! <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahibs</distinct>, do
                  not kill me!" she sobbed. "I am only poor <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#aza">Aza</persName>, and have no mother.
                  Father is cruel, but I do not want to die!" </p>

               <p>"Peace--peace, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#aza">Aza</persName>!"
                  said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonel">Colonel</roleName>;
                  have no fear. What can all that mean without, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hargrave">Hargrave</persName>?"</p>

               <p>A great contention appeared to be going on among the Hindoos composing the
                  attacking party; and as they seemed too much engaged by it to take much notice of
                  the party in the hut, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel
                     Lane</persName> stepped to the opening in the wall to reconnoitre. </p>

               <p>"A strange scene. They have placed their torches in clefts of trees, and the
                  father of this child we have here is haranguing them with frantic speech and
                  gestures. They appear to deride him--he falls on his knees, and clings to their
                  feet! Don't you hear him shrieking? Now, they fall upon him--they will kill him!
                  No--no! They bind him hands and feet--what a desperate struggle he makes! They
                  overpower him!--and now they cast him among some bushes and brushwood. They seem
                  to have gagged him, for he is quiet. I can guess it all! For his child's sake, he
                  would make terms with us; but the others are too intent on our destruction, to be
                  swayed by his fears and feelings, and so have got rid of his importunities for the
                  time. They will commence the attack again--what is to be done?" </p>

               <p>"The house is surrounded!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie</persName>, at this moment
                  returning from an examination of the inner room.</p>

               <p>"There is a strong force waiting in silence at the back, with the hope that we
                  will attempt to force our way out in that direction, when they would fall upon us
                  at once." </p>

               <p>"Then all is lost!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>. </p>

               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>
                  dropped gently to her knees, and tried to pray; but her words were only frantic
                  calls upon heaven to spare her child.</p>

               <p>With the sound of drums and shouts of triumph the Hindoo rabble now pressed
                  onwards. They did not fire any more shots, but the twang of bow-strings might be
                  heard; and soon a full red glare came in through the crevices of the hut, and
                  sparks of fire began to fall through the opening in the ceiling leading to the
                  loft. </p>

               <p>The hut was in flames! </p>

               <p>With a shout of exultation the Hindoos now retired to some twenty or thirty paces;
                  and while the tomtoms were incessantly beaten, and a gong occasionally gave out
                  its clashing sound, they seemed to wait the moment when the half-wasted Europeans
                  must emerge and give themselves up to their foes. </p>

               <p>The Hindoo child then, as if awakening from a dream, suddenly started to the side
                  of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel Lane</persName>, and
                  placing her hand in his, she said, as she looked in his face, "No! They are bad
                  men without! They shall not burn the ma'am <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahibs</distinct> and the officer
                     <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahibs</distinct>! </p>

               <cb n="2"/>
               <p>Come, come! <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#aza">Aza</persName> knows
                  what to do! Come with <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#aza"
                     >Aza</persName>!--come!"</p>

               <p>"What does she say and mean?" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hargrave">Colonel Hargrave</persName>, who
                  had not so good a knowledge of Hindostanee as his friend.</p>

               <p>"She has some scheme of saving us, she thinks; and, child as she is, I fain would
                  trust her." </p>

               <p>"Come, oh, come!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#aza"
                     >Aza</persName>. "Look! The fire!--the fire! They are bad men!" </p>

               <p>"Lead on, in the name of heaven!" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel</roleName>. "Follow, all of
                  you! Who knows but this child may know some mode of escape which we, in our
                  ignorance of the place, would never discover?" </p>

               <p>With her little finger on her lips, the Hindoo child led the party into the inner
                  room, and, at the further extremity of it, she tore down a piece of matting, and
                  disclosed a narrow opening. The glare of the fire from the burning roof was more
                  than sufficient to light up the spot, and they saw a kind of shed or outhouse,
                  with a low, sloping roof, and on one side, but for some other pieces of matting
                  which waved to and fro in the night air, open to the wood.</p>

               <p>"Ah, that is well!" whispered the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel</persName>: we can escape by
                  this way!" </p>

               <p>"No!" said the Hindoo girl. "Look, <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                     >Sahib</distinct>!" </p>

               <p>She drew the matting a little on one side, for the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonel">Colonel</roleName> to look through,
                  and he saw that in that direction, as well as in others, theplace was surrounded
                  by the armed villagers waiting the result of the conflagration. </p>

               <p>"How, then, can you help us?" he said. </p>

               <p>Without a word, the girl hastily removed some loose pieces of wood that covered
                  the middle of the floor, and disclosed the open mouth of a <placeName
                     type="building">well</placeName>. </p>

               <p>"There, <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</distinct>!" </p>

               <p>"There? But the depth?" </p>

               <p>Light and agile as a fawn, the Hindoo girl swung herself over the edge of the
                     <placeName type="building">well</placeName>, and disappeared. </p>

               <p>"It is not deep," she said from below; "and there is but little water. The spring
                  has departed long since, and the <placeName type="building">well</placeName> is
                  only of use when the great rains come.</p>

               <p>In another moment she was by the side of the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonel">Colonel</roleName>, having
                  dexterously clambered up again by the rugged sides of the <placeName
                     type="building">well</placeName>. </p>

               <p>"It is the only chance," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane"
                     >Colonel Lane</persName>. </p>

               <p>"All saved!" said the girl, as she turned and gave a slight caress to <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>'s child. The
                  action spoke volumes, and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName>
               </p>

               <p>"I would trust her to the death!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel Lane</persName>, in a voice of
                  emotion. </p>

               <p>The monotonous beating of the tom-toms continued, and the shout of the Hindoos
                  welcomes the progress of the flames about the blazing hut. There was not a moment
                  to loose<!--sic-->, ad by one consent, the party made their way into the
                     <placeName type="building">well</placeName>. The depthj was not above ten or
                  eleven feet, and there was about a foot of thick muddy water at the bottom; but
                  that was all. A subterranean passage seemed to lead from the well, perhaps
                  connecting it with some other spring. Wretched, and full of discomfort as this
                  place was, it was a cool and welcome refuge from the blazing hut; and, with the
                  assistance of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie"
                     >Jessie</persName> and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#wootton"
                     >Wootton</persName>, the whole party were soon in the <placeName
                     type="building">well</placeName>.</p>

               <p>"Farewell!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#aza">Aza</persName>;
                  and she hastily began to arrange the boards over the mouth of the <placeName
                     type="building">well</placeName>. Crash, then, came something, and they felt
                  certain that the roof of the outhouse had fallen in. </p>

               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#aza">Aza</persName>, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#aza">Aza</persName>!" cried the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lane">Colonel</roleName>. "Alas! the poor
                  child will be killed! She had better been with us!"</p>

               <p>"God help us!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName>: we shall yet die here for want of air!" </p>

               <p>The well was completely dark, and a suffocating feeling came over the whole party.
                  They heard the cries and yells of the Hindoos, as they, no doubt, gloated over the
                  destruction of the Europeans, believing them to have miserably perished in the
                  burning ruins of the hut. </p>

               <p>"Help, help!" gasped <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hargrave">Colonel
                     Hargrave</persName>. "Air, or I perish!" </p>

               <p>"Air! air!" shrieked <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName>. </p>

               <p>"Your sword!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie"
                     >Jessie</persName>. "Your sword, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#wootton">Wootton</persName>! Oh, quick!" </p>

               <p>Dark as it was, the <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Highland
                     girl</addName> got the long cavalry sword by the hilt, and, feeling her way up
                  the rugged sides of the well, she thrust the weapon, with all her strength,
                  through the mass of rubbish that covered its mouth. Again and again, with the
                  energy of a last effort to save those with her and herself, she dashed the
                  sword-blade upwards. There was a rumbling sound of displaced wood and smouldering
                  fragments, and a rush of cooler air came down into the well.</p>

               <p>
                  <emph>(To be continued in our next.)</emph>
               </p>

            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
