<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<!--
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/xsl" href="../xsl/rymer.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/css" href="../style.css" alternate="yes"?>
-->

   
<?xml-model href="../schema/sepoys.schema.xml" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI> 
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Sepoys; Or, Highland Jessie: an electronic edition</title>
            <author corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">James Malcolm Rymer</author>
            <editor corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#RN">Rebecca Nesvet</editor>
            <editor corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#RXY">Rae X. Yan</editor>
            <editor type="technical">Adam McCune</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Rebecca Nesvet</publisher>
            <publisher>Rae X. Yan</publisher>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <idno>sepoys</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct xml:id="installment2" prev="sepoys.2.13.xml#installment1"
               next="sepoys.2.27.xml#installment3">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter III: The Escape from the Assembly Room</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-02-20"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter IV: The Sisters and the Child</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-02-20"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <!-- Information about the encoding of the text -->
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Information about the project itself (goals, organization, activities)</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Information about how the texts in a collection were chosen or excerpted</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="unknown">
               <p>Information about treatment of errors in the source (silently corrected, etc.)</p>
            </correction>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Information about normalization practices (e.g. treatment of roman numerals,
                  spelling, etc.)</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation form="std">
               <p>Information about treatment of quotations (preservation of original quotation
                  marks, etc.)</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="hard">
               <p>Treatment of the hyphenation of the source</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Information about whether and how the text has been segmented (mostly for
                  linguistic purposes)</p>
            </segmentation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Information about any interpretive information added to the text</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="installment">
            <head><date when="1858-02-20">Saturday, February 20, 1858</date></head>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="../facsimiles/sepoys.2.20.png"/>
            </figure>
            <pb n="97"/>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <head>THE <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="indian">SEPOYS</orgName>; OR, <persName
                  corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">HIGHLAND JESSIE</persName>.</head>
            <head>A TALE OF THE PRESENT INDIAN REVOLT.</head>
            <head>BY <persName type="pseudo">M. J. ERRYM</persName>.</head>
            <head>AUTHOR OF "<title>JANE BRIGHTWELL</title>," "<title>THE SNOW-DRIFT</title>,"
               ETC.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch3">CHAPTER III.</head>
               <p>THE ESCAPE FROM THE <placeName type="building">ASSEMBLY ROOM</placeName>.</p>
               <p>The confusion incident to the firing at the Highland soldier in the great Hall of
                  the Palace at <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName> had enabled the
                     <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young
                     hill-chief</roleName>, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur Ahib</persName>, to escape from the presence of the fiend <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>. Dexteriously rolling
                  behind the mass of cushions forming that part of the divan, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> had got out of
                  sight before the lights, that had been in some cases extinguished by the
                  com-cussion <!--[sic]--> of the air caused by the fire-arms, could be re-lighted. </p>
               <p>Gliding then behind the officers of the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>, who lined the great
                  hall, he succeeded in reaching the doors, and passed out unobserved among the
                  disorderly throng that followed the bearers of the supposed dead body of the
                     <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Highlander</addName>. </p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> loved
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName> with
                  all the ardour of his warm-blooded race; and although he had fought in the ranks
                  of the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>, the
                  horrors with which the latter stained what he, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, considered to be
                  the holy cause of <placeName type="country">India</placeName>'s independence, now
                  sat heavily at his heart, and he felt that he could no longer associate himself
                  with a struggle that partook of such a character. </p>
               <!--CHARTISM-->
               <p>"Dear <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>!" he
                  murmured to himself, "I will save you; and then, one again, until all these
                  unhappy troubles are over, I will seek my native hills, and wait the coming of a
                  calmer and happier season!"</p>
               <p>The intercourse of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> with the <orgName type="family">Hope family</orgName> had
                  been of the most friendly and intimate character. On several occasions, when they
                  had sought <geogFeat type="hills" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#dooctees">the
                     hills</geogFeat> for change of climate from the parched-up <geogFeat
                     type="plain">plain</geogFeat> below, he <cb n="2"/> had been the almost
                  constant companion of both the sisters; and the fascination of first love for the
                  beautiful English girl had sunk deeply into his romantic heart.</p>
               <p>Nor could a young, ardent being, like <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName>, be altogether
                  indifferent to the chivalric homage of the handsome youth, who ever brought to her
                  feet the spoils of the chase, and who, by a thousand words and looks, proclaimed
                  her to be the presiding divinity of his soul.</p>
               <p>True it was that the earnest wish of her sister and of her sister's husband,
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#fletcher">Major
                  Fletcher</persName>, was, that <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName> should become the wife of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant Adrian</persName>, a
                  gallant young officer and a cousin of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#fletcher">Major Fletcher</persName>; but,
                  although she could not refuse him her esteem and admiration, the heart--the true
                  innermost heart of the young girl was touched by the gallant <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>. </p>
               <p>How, and by what circumstances, the two sisyters and the babe became prisoners of
                  the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> in that
                  awful <placeName type="building">Assembly Room</placeName> at <placeName
                     type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>, will be hereafter explained. We have now to
                  do with their fate on that night of terrors. </p>
               <p>The moon had now passed its meridian, and a flood of light was pouring upon the
                  streets of <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>, giving a sweet opal tint
                  to the roofs of the temples and the superior houses, while the broad shadows cast
                  by the low bungalows, and by the <placeName type="building">Residency</placeName>
                  and the <placeName type="building">Assembly house</placeName>, took the opposite
                  direction to that which they had presented at the opening of our narrative.</p>
               <p>The consequence of this was, that darkness was superadded to the horrors of that
                  prison-house. Several of the children had died since the sunset, and the moans and
                  sighs from the starving throng came sadly on the still night air.</p>
               <p>There was a feeling of despair at the heart of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, for he only knew
                  one things, and that was, that he resolved to rescue <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> or to die with her.
                  The severed lock of her fair hair, which she had thrust to him through the
                  jalousies, had too surely proved to him her presence among the victims, who, sad
                  and faint, waited there their doom.</p>
               <cb n="3"/>
               <p>That lock of hair had rested on his heart; and now, in the shadow of some houses,
                  he paused, and pressed it frantically to his lips and brw, and murmured forth her
                  name in blessings.</p>
               <p>"Gods of my ancient race, and, you, God of the <orgName type="religion"
                     >Christians</orgName>, too, who, I am assured, is one of goodness and mercy,
                  teach me how to save her whom I love!"</p>
               <p>Tears gushed to the eyes of the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young chief</roleName>, and he strove
                  to think of some feasible plan of operations. He knew the guard was doubled--that
                  is zealously, and, indeed, on peril of its life, guarded the prisoners. What was
                  he to do? what could he do?</p>
               <p>Reeling <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> passed him,
                  brandishing their tulwars and shouting aloud anathemas on the <orgName
                     xml:lang="ur" type="european" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee"
                     >Feringhee</orgName>. He heard the subdued shouts as the wild scene at the
                     <placeName type="building">Palace</placeName> still proceeded; and in the far
                  distance he, too, heard the sullen boom of a cannonade.</p>
               <p>Despair was still at his heart, when, glittering in the moonbeams, as, with his
                  sparkling apparel, he passed across an open spot, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> saw an officer of
                  the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>'s house not
                  far from where he himself was hidden. The officer paused in the moonlight, and
                  looked curiously at something he held in his hand, and then muttered to himself,
                  "'Tis hard ot choose the fairest by another's eyes, and on my head be it if the
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> is
                  displeased!"</p>
               <p>A half-stifled cry burst from the lips of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>. He recollected to
                  have heard, while seated near <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                        >Sahib</roleName></persName>, a whisper pass from mouth to mouth, that an
                  officer of his new court, named <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#gabali">Gab Ali</persName>, was to repair to
                  the <placeName type="building">Assembly Room</placeName> and choose the fairest of
                  its occupants for the companion of the night orgies of the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>.</p>
               <p>This, then, was the officer. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> now knew him in a moment; and doubtless what he regarded so
                  curiously was the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana</persName>'s signet-ring, which was to give him authority to pass the
                  guard.</p>
               <p>To the apprehensions of a lover, who can be so fair as she whom he loves. Did
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, then,
                  while the thought gave him a heart-pang that nearly killed him, <pb n="98"/>
                  <cb n="1"/> doubt for a moment that it would be his <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> who would be
                  chosen?</p>
               <p>To spring from the deep shadow in which he was, and intercept the officer, was the
                  work of a moment. </p>
               <p>"Ho! <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#gabali">Gab Ali</persName>,
                  whither go you?"</p>
               <p>The officer drew back, and placed his hand upon his sword.</p>
               <p>"Who speaks?"</p>
               <p>“I--<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur Ahib</persName>!
                  Know you me not?"</p>
               <p>“Well--but trust you little. Go your path. I heard the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> ask for you but
                  now."</p>
               <p>“<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#gabali">Gab Ali</persName>, we are
                  men and brothers, so to speak, as being of the same nation, although race and
                  caste divide us! I conjure you to tell me whither go you!"</p>
               <p>The jewels on the rich dress of the officer glistened as he laughed gaily, and
                  replied, “On a mission for the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana</persName>. The <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName> girls are fair as
                  the moon, and our lord has taste!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> stepped
                  adroitly between him and the <placeName type="building">guard-room</placeName>,
                  and laid a hand upon his arm.</p>
               <p>“On your life, hinder me not!" said the officer. “Our heads would answer even for
                  this delay if it were known! Out of my path! I have to take a guard with me!"</p>
               <p>“I know it!--I guessed it! You go to the prison of the English captive women!
                  There is one so fair--so--fairer than all! Heaven keep me sane! But you go
                  not!"</p>
               <p>“Are you mad?"</p>
               <p>“I am--or shall be! On your life, stir not!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> drew his
                  sword like a flash of light, and it glittered in the moonbeams as it dazzled the
                  eyes of the officer, who sprung back a step, and called, hoarsely, “Guard!--guard!
                  Guard for the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                  >Nana</persName>!"</p>
               <p>At the same moment he drew his scimitar, and the keen blades clashed together.
                  Both were masters of their weapons; and the plash and sparkle of the blades, as,
                  like living things, they whirled round each other in the moonlight, was magical to
                  see. The exquisite chain armour of the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young mountain chief</roleName>
                  glimmered like the coat of a serpent as lithely he fought. Then there was a lounge
                  <!--sic--> and a fall, a bubbling kind of cry, and the officer of the tyrant fell
                  pierced through the lungs at the feet of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>.</p>
               <p>To stoop for the signet-ring--to tear it from <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#gabali">Gab Ali</persName>’s finger, and to
                  place it on one of his own--were the operations of a few seconds to <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>; and then, as he
                  stood calmly by his fallen foe, he called aloud.</p>
               <p>"Guard!--guard! Guard for the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana</persName>!"</p>
               <p>The cries of the fallen officer had already reached the ears of the guard, or
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>would
                  certainly not have encumbered himself with such companions; and it was only from
                  the policy of the moment that he raised the cry.</p>
               <p>The guard surrounded him in a moment, and a <foreign xml:id="hi"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#havildar">havildar</foreign> (sergeant) called
                  for a torch.</p>
               <p>"Peace!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, with as much calmness as he could command. “The moonbeams
                  are sufficient."</p>
               <p>"Seize him!" cried the <foreign xml:lang="hi"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#havildar">havildar</foreign>. “There is blood
                  upon his sword, and an officer of the court lies at his feet!"</p>
               <p>"Hold!" said the <!--sic--><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>; and he held out his finger, on which sparkled the
                  signet-ring. “Know you that? It is the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>’s signet! His own
                  emerald! You have seen it all, and know its power!"</p>
               <p>The <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> shrunk
                  <!--sic-->back.</p>
               <p>"It is the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>’s
                  signet!" said the havildar. "What are my lord’s orders?"</p>
               <p>The heart of the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">mountain chief</roleName> beat high
                  with hope.</p>
               <p>"Follow me, trusty guard!" he said. “A mission from the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>!"</p>
               <p>"On my head be it! But this body?"</p>
               <p>"Place it in the shadow. The <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana</persName>orders all!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> again
                  flashed the emerald ring in the eyes of the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="indian"
                     >Sepoys</orgName>, and they obeyed silently.</p>
               <p>"Now, follow me!"</p>
               <p>The guard consisted of eight men, and the havildar. They had cast off some portion
                  of their European costume, but they still wore the accoutrements connected with
                  their arms; and they shouldered their muskets precisely as they had often done on
                  the parade at <placeName type="city">Calcutta</placeName>. To be sure, there was a
                  careless bustle in the order of their march, and an aspect of aggressive insolence
                  in their manner, which were new; but the discipline they had acquired in the
                     <orgName type="company">Company</orgName>’s service still sufficiently clung to
                  them to make them good soldiers.</p>
               <p>Gladly would <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>
                  have dispended with the guard, and gone on his errand, for the delivery of the
                  fair object of his heart’s adorations, alone; but that was not to be thought of
                  then. Any attempt, even, to disencumber himself ot heir presence, would have
                  looked suspicious.</p>
               <p>And so, along the deserted streets--past many a looted house--past a fountain, a
                  temple, and along a narrow thoroughfare, close to the <placeName type="building"
                     >Bazaar</placeName>, the party went until they reached the house they sought,
                  and then <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>
                  felt that the agitation of his heart must <cb n="2"/>have been forcibly manifest,
                  even in his countenance, had he allowed the <orgName type="indian">Sepoy</orgName>
                  guard to see it.</p>
               <p>The tramp of the men had reached the ears of those on duty over the prisoners, and
                  there was a tap of a drum and the rattle of arms.</p>
               <p>"Halt!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>.</p>
               <p>They stopped at the foot of some stairs that led to the room in which the English
                  prisoners were confined. A <orgName type="indian">Sepoy</orgName> officer stepped
                  forward, sating, “The relief?"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> caught at
                  the idea.</p>
               <p>"Yes, yes!" he said eagerly. “You can retire; I bring you a relief, as you
                  see."</p>
               <p>"I retire," said the officer, “but the second guard, which doubled mine, I see
                  remains, as you have only a single relief."</p>
               <p>The heart of the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young chief</roleName> sunk within
                  him. He felt that the hope which but a moment before had sprung up so brightly in
                  his breast was fallacious. There was no gainsaying what the officer stated; the
                  guard had been doubled by order of the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana <roleName type="honorific"
                        corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName></persName>, and he
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, brought
                  but men enough for a single relief.</p>
               <p>"That is true," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, with a sigh, as he stepped back a pace or two.</p>
               <p>The muskets rattled, and the guard was changed. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> finding himself
                  merely in command of another havildar and eight other men.</p>
               <p>There was, however, no time for hesitation. The night was fast waning away;
                  already, in the quarter of the heavens, whence the sun was to rise, there was a
                  faint opalescent flush--the harbinger of the coming day. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> uttered a short
                  prayer to the gods of his native land, in which the name of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> mingled strangely
                  with the uncouth ones of the Indian deities. He felt that if he could not save her
                  before the morning light, he had but to perish with her. Moreover, it might be
                  expected every moment now that the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> would send another
                  messenger to see what had become of the officer slain by the <roleName
                     type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young
                     chief</roleName> in the moonlight.</p>
               <p>Starting from the painful reverie of a moment, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> spoke to the
                  officer of the guard.</p>
               <p>"The <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> commands,"
                  he said, “and all obey."</p>
               <p>"Even so," replied the officer, “The <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>s will be swept
                  from the land!</p>
               <p>"A good work. Know you this signet-ring of the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>?</p>
               <p>The officer saluted the emerald ring respectfully.</p>
               <p>"Great is the power of my brother, since he has the ring of the<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>. He is highly
                  trusted."</p>
               <p>"Even so," replied <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> anxiously. “There is a <orgName xml:lang="ur"
                     type="european" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>
                  girl among the prisoners who has found favour in the eyes of the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>. I come for her--I will
                  seek her."</p>
               <p>"Seek, and find," said the officer. “Peace be to you! The <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>is lord of all here. We
                  follow his standard--we all obey!"</p>
               <p>"Thanks! thanks! I shall report well of you to the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, as he sprang
                  lightly up the stone steps that led to the <placeName type="building">Assembly
                     Room</placeName>."</p>
               <p>A mist of tears--tears of joy came before the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young chief</roleName>’s eyes, as he
                  now considered the rescue of Bessie as cerrain; and it was with a shock of
                  surprise, when he reached a long corridor, open on one side to the night sky, that
                  he heard the rattle of arms, and a voice called hoarsely, “Who goes there?
                  Sentinel, to your duty!"</p>
               <p>"Hold!" gasped <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, “I am an officer of the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>!"</p>
               <p>"Advance, officer!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> slowly
                  stepped some paces within the corrdior, and there he saw a well-known officer of
                  the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>’s guard,
                  with some dozen men on duty. For a moment or two, the young man could not speak; a
                  crowd of doubts and surmises flashed across his mind. Would this man respect the
                  ring of the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>?
                  Would he, if did so, leave him, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, to escort the
                  prisoner. <!--sic--> Hope, which for a few brief minutes, had animated the
                  countenance of the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young mountain chief</roleName>,
                  again fled from his heart.</p>
               <p>"Well?" said the officer, as he confronted <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, with his drawn
                  sword at the defensive.</p>
               <p>It was necessary to say something.<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> was desperate, and
                  he summoned boldness to speak aloud.</p>
               <p>"From our lord, the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana</persName>," he said. "I am directed to bring before him a certain
                  captive from those in this place."</p>
               <p>"The pass-word?"</p>
               <p>"This ring. It is the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana</persName>'s!"</p>
               <p>"I know! My orders, however, are positive! The <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> gave you the pass-word,
                  doubtless; give it me, and you are free to perform your mission!"</p>
               <p>"He gave me no word, but his own ring surely suffices for so small a matter!"</p>
               <p>"No!"</p>
               <p>"On your head be it!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> affected a
                  carelessness he was far from feeling, and strolled towards the staircase as if to
                  return. The officer was a little alarmed.</p>
               <p>"Hold, my friend!" he said. "It may be as you say! You stay here with me, and I
                  will send a guard <cb n="3"/>with the prisoner to the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>, so shall we both be
                  content!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> grasped at
                  the balustrade of the staircase for support.</p>
               <p>"No, no!" he gasped. "No!"</p>
               <p>"Traitor!" shouted the officer, as he made a rush at <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>.</p>
               <p>The <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young
                     chief</roleName> at one bound cleared the stairs, and then drew his sword and
                  stood on the defensive.</p>
               <p>"Fire!" cried the officer.</p>
               <p>A single musket was discharged down the stairs, and then<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, springing up half
                  a dozen of the steps, called to the officer, who was at the top. "Coward, come
                  forth! My sword is your fate! Come forth, coward!"</p>
               <p>"Forward!" cried the officer.</p>
               <p>There was a rush of feet, and in another moment, instead of the officer, who had
                  no sort of intention of risking a hand to hand encounter with<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, the <roleName
                     type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young
                     chief</roleName> would have had the whole guard upon him. He ran round the
                  corner of the house, and stooping low, in the deep shadow of the overhanging
                  verandah which went round three sides of it, he avoided the guard, but the alarm
                  of something wrong had reached the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="indian"
                     >Sepoys</orgName> and in a moment<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> found himself face
                  to face with a sentinel, who brought his musket to the charge, as he challenged
                  the intruder roughly.</p>
               <p>The bayonet reached the breast of<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, but he seized it
                  in both hands and wrested it aside. The sentinel fired, and the ball passed the
                  cheek of<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>.</p>
               <p>Feeling now that the whole of the two guards would be upon him, the young man with
                  one sweep of his sword cut down the <orgName type="indian">Sepoy</orgName>
                  sentinel, and then fled close in the shadow of the houses. The tramp of feet was
                  after him, and, missing his footing, he fell into a small trench near the
                     <placeName type="building">temple of Ghada</placeName>. Another moment, and a
                  havildar, with a couple of the guard, were upon him.</p>
               <p>"Life and liberty, or death!" cried<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, for he felt that
                  if he were made a prisoner the life of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> were lost. With the
                  energy of despair he grappled the <foreign xml:lang="hi"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#havildar">havildar</foreign>, who was eager to
                  use his sword, but at such close quarters could not do so.</p>
               <p>Then suddenly there was a rush and a cry, and one of <orgName type="indians">the
                     Sepoys</orgName> fell to the right and the other to the left, both as if struck
                  by lightning. A tall dark figure, with fluttering and strange apparel, then
                  finished the affray by wrenching the sword from the havildar and passing it
                  through his heart.</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">A weel</distinct>," said a voice; "<distinct
                     type="scotsdialect">I just reckon they fellows will no do ony mair
                     mischief!</distinct>"</p>
               <p>In that tone, so strange to him, and in the tattered, torn, and blood-stained
                  uniform of the man who had come so opportunely to his rescue,<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> at once recognised
                  the <placeName type="region">Highland</placeName> soldier who had been ordered to
                  be shot in the <placeName type="building">Palace</placeName> by the
                     ferocious<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>, and
                  who he,<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>,
                  fully believed had met his death there and then.</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">Weel!</distinct>" said the <addName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Highlander</addName>, as he observed
                  the young man looking at him with amazement. "<distinct type="scotsdialect">Did
                     you no see a <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy"
                        >Highlander</addName> before, that you glower at him as if he was no
                     canny?</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"Generous friend!" cried<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>; "you have saved me!"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">Weel, I just tuk upon mysel' to suppose so. They
                     were making short wark of you, my lad. but how cam'st it all aboot--for to my
                     thinking you are just one o' the same kidney yersell?</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"And you?--You were shot in the hall!"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">Eh? na! There's mony a slip yet between <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName> and a bullet, my
                     lad. I just saw them level, and then doon I went, and they chucked me out for
                     dead--but I'm no that dead yet, as ye may see by the bit tap on the lug I gave
                     to they fellows there!</distinct>"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> seized the
                  hand of the <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy"
                  >Highlander</addName>. A thought occurred to him like an inspiration.</p>
               <p>"Heaven sends you!" he said. "Will you aid me?"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">'Deed, and I think I have, and if you will just
                     tell me the way out of <!--this uncanny place--> to the British force, it will
                     be one good turn for another.</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"I will, indeed. But listen to me first. The <orgName type="uk">English</orgName>
                  prisoners are confined in the <placeName type="building">Assembly Room</placeName>
                  yonder. There is one who--who--" </p>
               <p>The young man covered his face with his hands, and one deep sob came from his
                  labouring heart.</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">Hoot, laddie!</distinct>" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName>; <distinct
                     type="scotsdialect">and what are you greeting for the noo</distinct>?"</p>
               <p>"She is so dear to me--dearer than my life! Will you aid me in her escape? I would
                  gladly save them all, but that is impossible. We will do what we can. To-morrow I
                  fear that they will all fall a prey to the vengeance of the<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>!</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">And you, my lad--you fight for him, and belong to
                     him?</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"Never again! I fought a day for <placeName type="country">India</placeName>, but
                  from this moment I cast aside all connexion with the man of crimes and blood!
                  Welcome--far more welcome--the yoke of the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName> than the
                  barbarous rule of a monster!</p>
               <pb n="99"/>
               <cb n="1"/>
               <p>The <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Highlander</addName> grasped
                  the hand of the young man with a vice-like pressure, as he said, “ <distinct
                     type="scotsdialect">‘Deed, and you are a good lad, after all, and no that black
                     as I can see!</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"I come from the <geogFeat type="hills" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#dooctees"
                     >hills</geogFeat>, and have no kindred with the race of the <geogFeat
                     type="plain">plains</geogFeat>. But let me explain all to you. <placeName
                     type="building">The Assembly House</placeName> is guarded on all sides by the
                  Sepoys. A double chain of sentinels surround it. There is but one chance of
                  getting any prisoner from it, and that is at a point by the garden-gate, near to a
                  well that is there. A casement, looking from the room, is about twelve feet from
                  the ground. If we could dispose of the two sentinels at that corner, we might
                  right the casement, and break its thin boards, and rescue her I have sworn to
                  serve."</p>
               <p>“<distinct type="scotsdialect">We’ll tak’ them all out, man</distinct>!"</p>
               <p>“Would to heaven we could!"</p>
               <p>“<distinct type="scotsdialect">Weel, weel</distinct>! We can but try! I wish we
                  had that <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>,
                  from the <orgName type="irish">Connaught Rangers</orgName>, here! He’s a good lad,
                  that, though no a Scotchman!"</p>
               <p>"Oh, follow me at once! The morn is coming! On, on! My <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, if I can but save
                  thee!"</p>
               <p>"Just lead the way, lad, and I’ll follow you! Is it <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> is the name of the
                  young thing?"</p>
               <p>"Yes—<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                  Hope</persName>."</p>
               <p>"<orgName type="family">Hope</orgName>? Is it the <orgName type="family"
                     >Hopes</orgName> of <placeName type="city"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#killmarnock">Killmarnock</placeName>? Or the
                     <orgName type="family">Hopes</orgName> of <placeName type="city"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#netherby">Netherby</placeName>?"</p>
               <!-- it's important to know whether the Hopes are of Killmarnock or Netherby, if from Killmarnock, they are a Scottish family, if of Netherby, they are from the North Yorkshire -->
               <p>"I know not what you mean. On, on!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, stooping
                  low in order to screen himself from observation—a manoeuvre in which the <addName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Highlander</addName> imitated him—ran
                  a considerable distance, so as to make a detour round the house, and reach it from
                  a different quarter, which he at length succeeded in doing.</p>
               <p>"Hush!" he said, as he paused in the shadow of an old wall. “Round this next
                  corner, the sentinels are on duty!"</p>
               <p>"There’s but two of them."</p>
               <p>"Two only?"</p>
               <p>The <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Highlander</addName> make a
                  gesture of disdain; but at that moment they heard the tramp of feet, and the
                  unmistakable rattle of military accountrements, and they shrunk back into the
                  shadow of the wall.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch4">CHAPTER IV </head>
               <head>THE SISTERS AND THE CHILD.</head>
               <p>To the surprise of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, a couple of <orgName type="indian">Sepoy</orgName>
                  sentinels were placed on the wall of the <placeName type="building">Assembly
                     House</placeName>, to which he and his friend had just arrived; although that
                  point had been left to the supervision of the two on the other angle of the wall
                  up to that period.</p>
               <p>It was necessary, now, if he and the <addName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Highlander</addName> would speak even
                  in the lowest tones, to draw still further back from the spot.</p>
               <p>"Two more of them!" whispered <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>.</p>
               <p>"Weel, that's no great matter."</p>
               <p>"No; but if a musket is fured, it will alarm the main guard, and then all will be
                  lost!"</p>
               <p>"That's true enough, my lad," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName>, as he gave his nose
                  a vigorous rub to assist his invention. "<distinct type="scotsdialect">Weel,
                     there's no other way. We must just creep up as close to them as we may, and
                     each lay hold o' one!</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"It must be so!"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">My conscience, what's that that makes it so
                     dark?</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"Oh, blessed chance! The moon has just dippled behind the topmost minaret of the
                  old temple, and the darkness here is double what it was. Now, follow me, and go as
                  I go!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> flung
                  himself flat on the ground, and, with the slow and torturous action of a serpent,
                  made his way along the shadow of the wall. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName> followed him,
                  although he was not so good at that mode of progression as <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>.</p>
               <p>"Hush!" said the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young chief</roleName>, in so low a
                  voice that it sounded more like the murmur of some insect than a voice. He
                  arrested their route at the same moment, for they had reached to within half a
                  dozen paces of the two Sepoys on guard.</p>
               <p>And now <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName>
                  whispered something to <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, and put into his hand a small pebble, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> nodded; and then
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName> crawled off
                  for about twenty paces or so,. The two sentinels stood together conversing in low,
                  monotonous tones.</p>
               <p>Cautiously, then, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, as he had been instrucred by <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName> to do, flung the
                  pebble directly to where he was crouching. It made a slight noise, and the
                  sentinels started. They said something to each other, and then one went in the
                  direction of the sound and stooped down to look close to the wall, from which
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName> had removed
                  himself some paces further on.</p>
               <p>Suddenly, with a spring that brought the Sepoy to his knees, the <addName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Highlander</addName> was upon him, and
                  his fingers around his throat. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> at the same moment flung himself upon the man who still
                  remained near to him.</p>
               <p>The <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> dropped their muskets and tried to
                  call <cb n="2"/>for aid, but the pressure on their throats tightened, and their
                  strength left them. With paralyzed limbs, they dropped to the ground senseless and
                  motionless. Still there had been a slight rustling round; and from the other side
                  of the wall, at right angles to this one, the other two sentinels slowly
                  appeared.</p>
               <p>"Is all well?" said one in Hindostanee.</p>
               <p>"All well!" replied <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, in the same tongue.</p>
               <p>He stood in the attitude as if one guard, and in the darkness, the Sepoy imagined
                  it his fellow. With a slow tread he walkd on his guard, repeating to his comrade,
                  "All is well!"</p>
               <p>"What next?" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy"
                     >Sandy</persName>.</p>
               <p>"My friend, it will be impossible to get to the window I spoke of while those men
                  aere there. It is just above their heads, and they do not march on their guard
                  from it more than thirty paces."</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">Ony mair, after them?</distinct>" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName>.</p>
               <p>"No; there is no other sentinel on this side of the building."</p>
               <p>An English <placeName type="building">sentry-box</placeName> had been placed at
                  the point where these two Sepoys now kept guard; but it had been suffered to go
                  much to decay, the Sepoys having an objection to use it; and now the <addName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Highlander</addName>, whose eyes had
                  become used to the darkness, whispered to <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, that when the
                  backs of the guards were turned he would take possession of the <placeName
                     type="building">sentry-box</placeName>, and drag into it and choke, as he had
                  done the other Sepoy, whichever of them should pass it first.</p>
               <p>To any mode of operations which the friend he considered sent to him by heaven
                  chose to adhere, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> at once agreed; and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName>, watching his
                  opportunity, stepped adroitly into the box.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> hid himself
                  by standing close to it, next to the wall, in its deep shadow.</p>
               <p>There was more danger of alarm in disturbing these two sentinels than the two
                  others who had already bee disposed of, because they were that much nearer to the
                  main guard; and the covered corridor or verandah above, in which <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> had already had a
                  perilous adventure, came round that side of the house about half-way, there
                  terminating in a couple of fantastic-looking columns.</p>
               <p>Scarcely had <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>
                  and his friend secured the positions we have mentioned, than a confused din of
                  voices, accompanied by several shots, come upon their ears, and a drum beat
                  violently close at hand.</p>
               <p>What could be the cause of the uproar they could not imagine, but a havildar of
                  the guard came running up to the spot where the two sentinels stood, irresolute
                  apparently what to do, and called out, "One of you to the corner by the <placeName
                     type="building">temple</placeName>! An English prisoner escapes! Fire on him if
                  he pass that way!" </p>
               <p>One of the Sepoys ran to the spot mentioned, and disappeared in the darkness. The
                  other kept vigilantly on guard.</p>
               <p>And now the moon, as if resolved to perplex all parties more and more, showed
                  onep-half of its silver disk through some ornaments abot the roof of the
                     <placeName type="building">temple</placeName>, and scattered such a strange
                  mixture of light and shadow on the ground that it was almost impossinle to
                  distinguish one object from another.</p>
               <p>Suddenly, the sentinel appeared to see a <!--sic-->something which gave him both
                  fear and uneasiness, for he slopped back, keeping his eyes bent in one particular
                  direction, until he was on the very threshold of the <placeName type="building"
                     >sentry-box</placeName>.</p>
               <p>The <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Highlander</addName> being a
                  good head taller than the Sepoy, and likewise having the advantage of being
                  elevated on the floor of the <placeName type="building">sentry-box</placeName>,
                  could see well over his head, and crawling or rather wriggling along at some
                  difstance in front, he saw a strange-looking object on the groundm, which might be
                  a tiger, a serpent, a jackall, or any animal that the wilds of <placeName
                     type="country">India</placeName> could produce, but certainly looked anything
                  but human.,</p>
               <p>The Sepoy sentinel seemed to be stricken with a sort of panic, for he evidently
                  trembled, and it was not until he had gazed at the strange object for several
                  minutes that he seemed to recollect that he had a musket and that he was on
                  duty.</p>
               <p>"Who goes there?" he cried in Hindostanee.</p>
               <p>There was no reply.</p>
               <p>He then challenged in English in the manner the <orgName type="indian"
                     >Sepoys</orgName> speak the language. </p>
               <p>Still there was no reply, and the strange object wriggled slowly along.</p>
               <p>Then the Sepoy brought his musket to the level, but although <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName> had no idea in the
                  world what the object might be, he had no sort of intention of allowing the Sepoy
                  to give alarm by firing his musket.</p>
               <p>At the moment, therefore, that the sentinel put himself into an attitude to do so,
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName> just
                  stretched his arms out of the <placeName type="building">sentry-box</placeName>,
                  and clutched him by the throad with grasp of iron.</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">Na! na!</distinct>" he said; "<distinct
                     type="scotsdialect">you'll be no doing that, my bairn</distinct>!"</p>
               <p>A half-stifled shrief from the Sepoy, and all was still. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName> still held him by the
                  neck.</p>
               <p>"What is that?  said a voice from that portion of <cb n="1"/>the balcony which
                  stretched over a part of that side of the house.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> heard the
                  question, and promptly replied, "All is well!" </p>
               <p>He stepped from the cover of the <placeName type="building">sentry-box</placeName>
                  as he did so, and stood calmly in front of it, as if on duty.</p>
               <p>"Keep good guard," said the voice.</p>
               <p>"Good guard, <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                     >Sahib</roleName>!" replied <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>. </p>
               <p>All was still again.</p>
               <p>The strange gliding object had come to a halt, and there it lay about ten or
                  twelve yards from the <placeName type="building">sentry-box</placeName>, perfectly
                  motionless. </p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">My good lad</distinct>, said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName>, "what in the name of
                  all that's uncanny, do you call that?"</p>
               <p>""What?--what?"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">You odd-looking thing thereaway, by the
                     moonlight.</distinct>"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> was equally
                  puzzled with <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName>,
                  but now they as they both looked, the mysterious object seemed on fire, for a
                  strange glow of red heat came from some point of it, then as rapidly went out
                  again.</p>
               <p>"I will creep out, and look to it," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>.</p>
               <p>As he spoke, he put on the cap of the <orgName type="indian">Sepoy</orgName>
                  sentinel, who had by this time been deposited in the <placeName type="building"
                     >sentry-box</placeName> by <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy"
                     >Sandy</persName>, and cautiously the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young chief</roleName> stepped
                  towards the strange object. As he did so, it suddenly rolled over and then sprung
                  erect, and a voice said, "<distinct type="irishdialect">Murder and turf! here's
                     one of the niggers beyant me at last!</distinct>"</p>
               <p>The human character of the object could no longer be doubted, as it made a rush
                  past <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> towards
                  the <placeName type="building">sentry-box</placeName>, evidently to seize the
                  Sepoy's musket which lay on the ground; but <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName> closed with the
                  stranger, saying "<distinct type="scotsdialect">'Deed, but you won't. mu
                     lad!</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="irishdialect">Oh, think, by the mother of Moses, is that you,
                        <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy"
                     >Sandy</persName>?</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>?" said
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName>.</p>
               <p>It was indeed no other than <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis"
                     >Dennis</persName>, who had escaped from his guard, and who in that snake-like
                  fashion had been trying to found an outlet from <placeName type="city"
                     >Cawnpore</placeName>. It was with great difficulty that <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName> could control the
                  transport of his Irish friend sufficiently to prevent him from giving a wild
                  screeching hilloa!--which would, if <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName> had not half choked
                  him by putting his hand over his mouth, have brought all the Sepoys in <placeName
                     type="city">Cawnpore</placeName> upon them in a moment.</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="irishdialect">Oh, bedad! and it's all right we are
                  now</distinct>!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis"
                     >Dennis</persName>. "<distinct type="irishdialect">It's the united forces
                     again, and it's bang all the world we'll be after! Which is the way home, my
                     friend? I mean to the camp--Och! Botheroo!</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">Are you clean daft?</distinct>" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName>. "<distinct
                     type="scotsdialect">Just hand your stupid tongue, will ye? There's much to
                     do.</distinct>"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> now laid a
                  hand on each of them. "For the love of all you hold dear, aid me now!" he said;
                  "and aid me quickly, for there is no time to lose. See how the moon is coming: if
                  it come, and we here still, all is lost!"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">The lad speaks true</distinct>," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName>. "<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>!"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="irishdialect">Hereaway</distinct>," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>.</p>
               <p>"You'll just obey orders, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis"
                     >Dennis</persName>, <distinct type="irishdialect">my man. I'm a sergeant, ye
                     ken, and your superior officer.</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">Faith, then, that's true for you!</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"Now, my land, which is the casement?"</p>
               <p>"There! there! said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, as he pointed to the casement to which he ahd before
                  climbed by the aid of that very <placeName type="building">sentry-box</placeName>,
                  and through the jalousies of which he had received that precious lock of hair
                  which still rested on his heart. "Oh, it is there! The boarding is slight, and can
                  be easily broken through. Oh! aid me well!--save her, I implore you! Keep good
                  guard for me below here, while I ascend, and all may yet be well. I will direct
                  you to <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#havelock">Havelock</persName>'s
                  camp, with my best prayers."</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="irishdialect">Weel, well! we won't desert you, my lad. Take that
                     musket</distinct>, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis"
                     >Dennis</persName>."</p>
               <p>"Yes," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis"
                  >Dennis</persName>.</p>
               <p>"Shoulder arms!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName> shouldered
                  the Sepoy's musket.</p>
               <p>"Order! arms."</p>
               <p>"It's as good as done!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis"
                     >Dennis</persName>.</p>
               <p>"Keep close guard, and let no one approach."</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="irishdialect">Bedad, and this is mighty quare o'me keeping guard
                     here!</distinct>"</p>
               <p>Light and agile as one of his own mountain deer, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> sprung to the roof
                  of the <placeName type="building">sentry-box</placeName>, from which he could just
                  reach the lower part of the casement.</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">Here's a lightsome, active lad</distinct>," said
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName> admiringly,
                  as the figure of the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young chief</roleName> glittered in
                  its chain armour, as now and then a ray of moonlight fell upon it.</p>
               <p>And now, with heart and brain throbbing with excitement, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> tapped with his
                  dagger hilt at the wood-work of the casement. Then came a cry from within, and
                  something white appeared between the jalousies. They were two small fingers.
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> pressed
                  them with devotion, and his tears fell fast upon them.</p>
               <p>"Saved!--oh, God! saved! said a voice from within. "'Tus he! oh, 'tis he!" He has
                  not deserted us!"</p>
               <pb n="100"/>
               <cb n="1"/>
               <p>Then arose other cries, and prayers, and some shrieks from within that awful room
                  where the living and the dead lay together, with famine on every cheeck; and the
                  heart of the young man beat painfully against his coat of mail. The cries of
                  distress and terror reached the ears of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName> and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>, and the strong,
                  brave men shook in every limb, and wept like children. Then, with his dagger,
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> began his
                  work at the jalousies, and the splintered, dry wood flew fast before his efforts.
                  With his hands, then, he tore away the broken pieces, calling, as he did so, upon
                  the name of her he loved so truly. Two fair, thin--oh! so wan and thin--arms were
                  thrust through the first opening, and they fell on the neck of the <roleName
                     type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young
                     chief</roleName>. Sobs, and tears, and prayers came from the pale lips that he
                  saw in the moonlight, and the long, fair hair fell upon him like rays of
                  sunshine.</p>
               <p>"Saved! oh, God! I shall be saved!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>. "I do love him!--I
                  will love him! He is not o my creed or people, but God will let me love him!"</p>
               <p><emph>(To be continued in our next.)</emph></p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
