<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<TEI>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Sepoys; Or, Highland Jessie: an electronic edition</title>
            <author>James Malcolm Rymer</author>
            <editor>Rebecca Nesvet</editor>
            <editor>Rae X. Yan</editor>
            <editor type="technical">Adam McCune</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Rebecca Nesvet</publisher>
            <publisher>Rae X. Yan</publisher>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <idno>sepoys</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct xml:id="backmatter">
               <analytic>
                  <author>Rebecca Nesvet</author>
                  <author>Rae X. Yan</author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="2014"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <!-- Information about the encoding of the text -->
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Information about the project itself (goals, organization, activities)</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Information about how the texts in a collection were chosen or excerpted</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="unknown">
               <p>Information about treatment of errors in the source (silently corrected, etc.)</p>
            </correction>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Information about normalization practices (e.g. treatment of roman numerals,
                  spelling, etc.)</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation form="std">
               <p>Information about treatment of quotations (preservation of original quotation
                  marks, etc.)</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="hard">
               <p>Treatment of the hyphenation of the source</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Information about whether and how the text has been segmented (mostly for
                  linguistic purposes)</p>
            </segmentation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Information about any interpretive information added to the text</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="editorial_notes">
            <note xml:id="sepoys">Sepoys,<!-- insert full note on sepoys here? --></note>
            <note xml:id="sahib">Sahib, a male honorific in colonial India, equivalent to 'sir',
               'friend', or 'master', depending on context. Derives from sāhib (Arabic and Urdu);
               sāhab (Hindi).</note>
            <note xml:id="eeda">eeda, a many-stringed instrument </note>
            <note xml:id="feringhee">Feringhee, derogatory colloquialism for a white-skinned person,
               i.e., a European. Historically, denoted the Portuguese foreigners who were the first
               significant group of Europeans to attempt to colonize India.</note>
            <note xml:id="vishnu">Vishnu, in Hinduism, the Preserver, incarnation of Brahma.</note>
            <note xml:id="chunar">chunar, contextually referring to a silver-belled instrument
               though this has not been confirmed by our sources</note>
            <note xml:id="dooctees">Dooctees, definition of -- the hill tribe of which the fictional
               Jeffur is the chief </note>
            <note xml:id="grandlaama">Grand Laama, Great Monk</note>
            <note xml:id="chor">Chor, thief (Hindi)</note>
            <note xml:id="bang">bang, slang for an intoxicating liquor made from hemp</note>
            <note xml:id="donnybrook">Donnybrook Fair, a fair held in Donnybrook, Ireland, from 1204
               until its abolition in the 1850s. In the Victorian era, Donnybrook Fair was famous
               for its revelry and supposed chaos.</note>
            <note xml:id="dowga">Dawga,
               <!--I don't know but someone who can translate this YouTube video's title might: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rdgeLaWG3TY--></note>
            <note xml:id="siva">Siva, Destroyer, incarnation of the god Brahma in Hinduism;
               pronounced 'Shiva'.</note>
            <note xml:id="kalee">Kalee, Hindu goddess of death and destruction, incarnation of
               Parvati; usually spelled 'Kali' in English. </note>
            <note xml:id="budda">Budda, lit. "awakened" in Sanskrit. Indian religious leader who
               lived c.6-4 B.C. E. and founded the Buddhist faith. Born Siddhartha Gautama, a
               hereditary ruler, Buddha abandoned his terrestrial office and its attendant luxuries
               to become an ascetic. Most particulars of his biography remain the subject of debate. </note>
            <note xml:id="havildar">havildar, commander or quartermaster (Hindi; Arabic.) </note>
            <note xml:id="killmarnock">Killmarnock, city in East Ayrshire, Scotland (Lowlands).
               Robert Burns' poetry (<em>Poems, Chiefly in the Scottish Dialect</em>, 1786) was
               first published in Kilmarnock. Also the sometime location of the original Johnnie
               Walker bottling plant.</note>
            <note xml:id="netherby">Netherby, a town in North Yorkshire, England.</note>
            <note xml:id="tulwars">Tulwars, type of curved sword or sabre used in South Asia by
               cavalry and infantry (Hindi and Urdu).</note>
            <note xml:id="ghaut">Ghaut, water-stairs (Hindi); a cremation-space on the water; in
               modern English usually spelled <em>ghat</em>.</note>
            <note xml:id="cityofthemogul">City of the Mogul, Delhi</note>
            <note xml:id="griffins">griffins, military slang for newcomers</note>
            <note xml:id="punkah"> punkah, a large board hinged to the ceiling of apartments which
               acts as a fan</note>
            <note xml:id="ryot">ryot, normally, an Indian peasant or tenant farmer; here, indicating
               a tenant farmer specifically.</note>
            <note xml:id="ayah">ayah, nanny (Hindi, from the Portuguese 'aia').</note>
            <note xml:id="elhareeb">El Hareeb, location of ancient Egyptian tombs. See Richard
               Lepsius, Letters from Egypt, Ethiopia, and the Peninsula of Sinai, translated by
               Leonora and Joanna B. Horner (London: Bohn, 1853), 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="zemindar">zemindar, landed proprietor (Hindi).</note>
            <note xml:id="zemindar">zemindar, from the Urdu, a landowner, especially one who leases
               his land to tenant farmers</note>
            <note xml:id="manillas">Manillas, pennanular armlets made of bronze or copper, and
               sometimes gold, serving as currency in Western Africa.</note>
            <note xml:id="cresset">cresset, metal container used as a lamp.</note>
            <note xml:id="howdahs">howdahs, carriages usually carried by elephants; often used in
               hunting or warfare; often a symbol of wealth, decorated with gems.</note>
            <note xml:id="salaamed">salaamed, verb form of 'salaam', a salute that accompanies a
               greeting; lit. "peace" (Arabic). </note>
            <note xml:id="padisha">Padisha, derivative of 'king' (from the Persian).</note>
            <note xml:id="32nd">British foot regiment that entered Lucknow in January 1857,
               relieving the H. M. 52nd, and fought with the Sepoy insurgents. The 32nd Regiment was
               commanded by Lieutenant-Colonel John Eardley Inglis. In April 1837 it consisted of
               approximately 700 men. See Julia Selina Inglis, <em>The Siege of Lucknow: A Diary by
                  the Honourable Lady Inglis</em> (London: Osgood, 1892). University of Pennsylvania
               Digital Library, http://digital.library.upenn.edu/women/inglis/lucknow/lucknow.html
               Retrieved November 9, 2014.</note>
            <note xml:id="11th">11th Cavalry, i.e., 11th "irregular cavalry," a detachment of the
               British Army in India that joined the revolt. See Charles Ball, <em>The History of
                  the Indian Revolt</em>, 2 vols (London, 1858), 58.</note>
            <note xml:id="brahmin">Brahmin, priests; highest caste in the Hindu religion.</note>
            <note xml:id="thug">Thug, Indian hired assassin (Hindi); later became a colloquialism
               for a ruffian.</note>
            <note xml:id="childofnature">Child of nature, the French philosopher Jean-Jeacques
               Rousseau (1712-1778) in <em>Èmile</em> argued that children should be raised in
               nature (as if they were small animals), allowed to grow at their own pace and thus
               avoid the hypocricies of civilization. This connotation has particular significance
               given the prevalence of "wolf children" reported in India during this time. See John
               Lang's "Wolf Nurses" in Household Words, Vol. 6, 1853: 562; and Lang's "Wanderings in
               India" in Household Words,. Vol. 17, 1858: 135-145.</note>
            <note xml:id="hubaboo">hubaboo, a riot; also a nonsense term used in Victorian Irish
               published folksong (Hibernian English). See <em>The Dublin Comic Songster</em>
               (Dublin: Duffy, 1841), 105, 180. </note>
            <note xml:id="creese">creese, of Malay origin from the word "kris", meaning dagger of
               Malay or Indonesian origin, usually with a wavy blade</note>
            <note xml:id="shieling">shieling, from the Scottish Gaelic, a type of hut or collection
               of huts once common to lonely places in the hills and mountains of Scotland and
               northern England, also a word for mountain pasture grazing</note>
            <note xml:id="pibroch">pibroch, Scottish Gaelic for piping, traditionally of the Great
               Highland Bagpipe</note>
            <note xml:id="bonny">bonny, Scottish Gaelic for attractive or pretty</note>
            <note xml:id="kitchri">kitchri, according to Rymer, a dish of curried fowl with goat,
               chillies, and other spicing</note>
            <note xml:id="chaffratees">chaffratees, according to Rymer, a type of cake</note>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
