<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<!--
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/xsl" href="../xsl/rymer.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/css" href="../style.css" alternate="yes"?>
-->

<?xml-model href="../schema/sepoys.schema.xml" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>

<TEI>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Sepoys; Or, Highland Jessie: an electronic edition</title>
            <author corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">James Malcolm Rymer</author>
            <editor corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#RN">Rebecca Nesvet</editor>
            <editor corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#RXY">Rae X. Yan</editor>
            <editor type="technical">Adam McCune</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Rebecca Nesvet</publisher>
            <publisher>Rae X. Yan</publisher>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <idno>sepoys</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct xml:id="installment3" prev="sepoys.2.20.xml#installment2"
               next="sepoys.3.06.xml#installment4">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter V: The Last Night in the Assembly Room</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-02-27"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter VI: The Boat and the Rescue</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-02-27"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <!-- Information about the encoding of the text -->
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Information about the project itself (goals, organization, activities)</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Information about how the texts in a collection were chosen or excerpted</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="unknown">
               <p>Information about treatment of errors in the source (silently corrected, etc.)</p>
            </correction>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Information about normalization practices (e.g. treatment of roman numerals,
                  spelling, etc.)</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation form="std">
               <p>Information about treatment of quotations (preservation of original quotation
                  marks, etc.)</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="hard">
               <p>Treatment of the hyphenation of the source</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Information about whether and how the text has been segmented (mostly for
                  linguistic purposes)</p>
            </segmentation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Information about any interpretive information added to the text</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="installment">
            <head><date when="1858-02-27">Saturday, February 27, 1858</date></head>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="../facsimiles/sepoys.2.27.png"/>
            </figure>
            <pb n="113"/>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <head>THE <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="indian">SEPOYS</orgName>; OR, <persName
                  corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">HIGHLAND JESSIE</persName>.</head>
            <head>A TALE OF THE PRESENT INDIAN REVOLT.</head>
            <head>BY <persName type="pseudo">M. J. ERRYM</persName>.</head>
            <head>AUTHOR OF "<title>JANE BRIGHTWELL</title>," "<title>THE SNOW-DRIFT</title>,"
               ETC.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch5">CHAPTER V.</head>
               <head>THE LAST NIGHT IN THE <placeName type="building">ASSEMBLY
                  ROOM</placeName>.</head>
               <p>In long narrow pencils of light the glorious moonlight of that favoured
                  clime--where, to look upon the beauty of the earth, to breathe the perfumed air,
                  are luxuries--fell upon the throng of sad and tearful faces on that last night of
                  life and of misery in the <placeName type="building">Assembly Room</placeName> at
                     <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>.</p>
               <p>Far too intense and subtle for language were the various feelings that dominated
                  in the breasts of those fair and tender beings who were penned up in that fearful
                  slaughter-house. We feel that the heart sickens, and the brain throbs too
                  painfully in the approach to the horrors of that fearful catastrophe that shook
                  the feelings of a civilised world.</p>
               <p>The massacre at <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>!</p>
               <p>We write the fearful words as a foregone conclusion; but on that night of rare and
                  exquisite beauty, when but for man, who with his wild passions will mar the
                  fairness of all around him, there should have been but an atmosphere of happiness
                  in that favoured clime, all was despair--and the victims still lived!</p>
               <p>The abrupt departure of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, after the twinkling sound of the lute, and after <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> had bestowed upon
                  him the gift of the tress of hair, seemed to her and to <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>, her sister, like the
                  extinction of hope.</p>
               <p>They were not aware that it was the sudden advance of the <orgName type="indian"
                     >Sepoy</orgName> guard, which had compelled <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> so suddenly, and
                  without another word of love or encouragement, to quit the spot, but so it was. He
                  had barely <cb n="2"/>had time to spring from the top of the <placeName
                     type="building">sentry-box</placeName>,--which had, as we have recorded,
                  afterwards served him for the same purpose, namely, of reaching the window of the
                     <placeName type="building">Assembly Room</placeName>,--when the guard was
                  below.</p>
               <p>If the moon casts bright lights, it defines them well, and leaves as broad
                  shadows, so that <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> was well enough concealed; but the sisters suffered during
                  that night a world of anxiety.</p>
               <p>The few words that had passed at the window, and the incident, trifling as it was,
                  of any one with friendly feelings visiting that fearful place, had awakened a
                  sensation of hope in the breasts of the unfortunates there confined which vibrated
                  through all hearts.</p>
               <p>Closely packed as they were--mingled with the dead and with the dying--they still
                  whispered to each other that there was a friend without.</p>
               <p>And <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> sobbed
                  upon her sister's breast, for her fair, brave heart now was almost broken.</p>
               <p>"Oh, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>--all is
                  lost! all is lost! He comes not again, and we are doomed!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName> could not
                  reply. The moaning child that she held in her arms was all the world to her, and
                  already the cold damp of death was settling on its young brow.</p>
               <p>She had prayed to heaven, and there had come no aid. She had wept, and raved, and
                  shrieked, and all was as before; and now a kind of stupefaction seemed to be
                  creeping over her, which, perhaps, was a part of the mercy she had wished from on
                  high.</p>
               <p>"Sister! sister!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>; "oh, do not look at me so strangely! The moonlight comes
                  across your face, and although I know each feature so well, it is not your own old
                  expression that sits upon them all."</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> had one of
                  the hands of her sister clasped in her's, and the clasp gently tightened as she
                  spoke. In a low, soft, dreamy voice, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName> spoke,--"I feel as if
                  a certainty had come over my heart, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, that you will
                  live!"</p>
               <p>"And you?"</p>
               <p>"Nay, it may not be! But you will see him--my <cb n="3"/>dear <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#fletcher">George</persName>--you will see my
                  husband, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>!
                  Tell him--tell him--all!"</p>
               <p>She sobbed aloud.</p>
               <p>"Tell him that--that the love of my heart--the last prayer of my life--were
                  his!"</p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>--<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>! do not speak
                  thus--for we live or die together!"</p>
               <p>"No--no!" If that young mountaineer should come again, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, and with means to
                  save you, I implore you to let him do so, if it be you alone."</p>
               <p>"Never! I have sworn it to Heaven! Your fate will be--shall be my fate! We will be
                  saved together, or we will die together!"</p>
               <p>"Who talks of saved? Who uses the gracious word?" screamed a young mother, with
                  three little children clinging to her. "Oh, say if there is a hope?"</p>
               <p>"There is always hope!" sobbed <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                     >Annie</persName>.</p>
               <p>A wail then arose from a distant part of the room, and the word, "Dead! dead"
                  repeated in agonised accents, proclaimed that another victim had succumbed to the
                  horrors of the place.</p>
               <p>Then, reason--which was nearly quenched in the brains of some, and had subsided
                  into a cold, blank despair, the apathy of which was fearful, although
                  silent--suddenly left a mind which became wildly deranged; and a series of
                  frightful screams burst from the distorted lips of a maniac.</p>
               <p>"Water!--water! Help! Ha! ha! Dying!--dying, all! Plunge into the stream! Oh, what
                  joy is this? Hark to the firing! Well, they come! The child bleeds to death, with
                  a hundred wounds! The blood is hot! Who is that amid the smoke and reek of battle?
                  Husband, I come!--I come! Water! What, all turned to blood? Fire!--fire! Fire on
                  them! Now, brave hearts! 'Tis done! Ha! ha! ha! The boats!--the boats! Oh, yes!
                  they will let us go in the boats! Now, all to the boats! Oh, that is only the
                  guard to see us off! Farewell!--farewell The cool water laves the shore, and
                  ripples in the sunlight! Oh, glorious liberty! Oh, joy! Now all is well! Oh, happy
                  release! And the little ones--all <pb n="114"/><cb n="1"/>the loved faces--they
                  smile again! The heat and the terrors of the contest are over! The boats! Ay, the
                  boats will take us all to safety, and to loving hearts! All is well!--all is well!
                  Room, dearest, for you--for your kind friend and for you! Oh, no! no! Mercy! The
                  guns are charged with grape! That is man's thunder--Heaven's does not strike the
                  innocent! Help! mercy! Blood!--blood everywhere! They fire on us! Fiends!--fiends!
                  Listen to the death shriek--the splitting timbers of the frail barks--the groans
                  and cries of the dead and of the dying! Mercy! Help! help! All is lost!"</p>
               <p>A succession of fearful screams exhausted the strength of the maniac, and she fell
                  back insensible.</p>
               <p>Those who heard this saddened raving description of the horrors that had preceded
                  the imprisonment in that fearful place, could alone appreciate the terrible tones,
                  and cries, and shrieks, which gave it its maniacal force. No language can express
                  the vivid terror of the rapidly-uttered words.</p>
               <p>And now some, who, until that time, had been calm and still, or had only wept and
                  prayed, felt a sensation of desperation stealing over them. Many hours had passed
                  without food. The thirst that consumed them was a raging fever; and as they heard
                  the coarse laughter of the <orgName type="indian">Sepoy</orgName> guard without,
                  some, bolder than the others, struggled to the door of the apartment, and tried to
                  shake it from its fastenings.</p>
               <p>Others, again, paid no attention to all that was going on, but sat muttering to
                  themselves the names of those that were dear to them, or in sad silence.</p>
               <p>Several, with such rude means as presented themselves for the purpose, scratched
                  or wrote upon the walls dismal records of the time and the events of that
                  place.</p>
               <p>With a small earthenware pitcher that was in the room, and in which a scanty
                  supply of water had been brought more than twenty hours before, those nearest to
                  the door beat upon its panels, and called frantically for aid.</p>
               <p>"Water! water! water! Help! mercy! Water! water!"</p>
               <p>These were the cries that rang in the vexed ears of the <orgName type="indian"
                     >Sepoy</orgName> guard, and then there suddenly came a crashing sound, followed
                  by a shriek.</p>
               <p>One of the guard had fired his musket through the panel of the door, and the shot
                  had taken effect in the breast of a soldier's wife, who had an infant in her
                  arms.</p>
               <p>To describe the scene of horror and confusion that now ensued would be impossible.
                  It was fully expected by others that this shot would but be the precursor of
                  others, and that they would all perish in that fashion. Alas! they were reserved
                  for a worse fate still. There were some who, in the despair of their sufferings,
                  went close to the door, and placed themselves against its very panels, that they
                  might be the first to receive the bullets, if they came, thinking instant death a
                  happy escape from the sufferings they endured.</p>
               <p>But no more shots came just then.</p>
               <p>And now <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>
                  summoned to her aid all the force of character she could muster, and, with
                  streaming eyes and faltering voice, she strove to address the poor sufferers. Her
                  voice was nearly lost amid the chaos of sobs, and groans, and sighs from so many
                  sad human hearts; but some hard her, and blessed her for the attempt to utter
                  words of hope.</p>
               <p>"Listen! listen!" she said. "Oh, listen, all of you! and, in the pauses of your
                  tears and sighs, you will hear, as I have heard--close to this lattice as I am
                  placed--the distant sound of cannon! There! do you not hear?"</p>
               <p>There was an effort to be still and calm for a moment or two, and to listen. There
                  certainly did come upon the night air the boom of cannon in the distance. But who
                  shall take upon himself to say that they were friendly or hostile guns?</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> strove to
                  instil the feeling and idea that they were the former; and she spoke again.</p>
               <p>"You hear the sounds? They speak to my heart of hope and of deliverance! Moreover,
                  there is a friend of me, and so a friend to all, without! He, who has been already
                  to this window, I feel convinced has no come merely to complete or to assure
                  himself of the existence of a suffering he will not try to alleviate! Oh, be
                  hopeful yet!"</p>
               <p>The young girl could say no more, for her tears stopped her utterance. The night
                  was wearing on, and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> came not again. Her own poor heart belied the words of hope
                  she strove to whisper to others.</p>
               <p>And then, again, arose the shout and the cry for water; and amid the surging
                  throng the dead began to fall, and to be in the way of the living, and many a
                  shriek told the breaking of some poor heart.</p>
               <p>"Water! water! water!"</p>
               <p>What to them was the bullet of the <orgName type="indian">Sepoy</orgName>? That
                  raging thirst was worse than death! Water!--still the cry was water!</p>
               <cb n="2"/>
               <p>They shook the door with frantic force.</p>
               <p>And now there are some answering blows from without, and a loud voice, in the
                  peculiar <orgName type="indian">Sepoy</orgName> tone, calls out, "Water is
                  coming--water is coming! Clear away--clear away from the door!"</p>
               <p>With shouts of pleasure they do so. There is space sufficient to open the door,
                  and it is a few inches forced inwards. Then a little more; and then, with a shout
                  of triumphant malice, the <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> flung into the
                  midst of the expectant, dying, maddened throng, a large frail vessel of water,
                  which breaks as it falls, and but scatters some of its contents upon the pale
                  faces and disordered apparel of the poor sufferers.</p>
               <p>That they try to close the door again, but despair is strong, and several cling to
                  it, and rave for help and mercy.</p>
               <p>The <foreign xml:lang="hi" corresp="sepors.backmatter.xml#tulwars"
                     >tulwars</foreign> of the <orgName type="indian">Sepoy</orgName> guard are used
                  freely, and gashing wounds, from which the blood flows, are inflicted. The door is
                  closed again, and the dead and the dying lie close to its threshold.</p>
               <p>Oh! when will the horrors of the night cease? Will the blessed light of morning
                  end them? Yes, in a way!</p>
               <p>And now that time had arrived when, as we mentioned, while following the fortunes
                  of the gallant <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> without, the moon had passed over the building, and no
                  longer cast some straggling rays into the <placeName type="building">Assembly
                     Room</placeName> through the interstices of the jalousies.</p>
               <p>Then <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> even
                  gave up hope, and sunk to the floor beneath <cb n="3"/>the casement, and was very
                  still, although the tears fell, drop by drop, from her aching eyes. She thought of
                  her happy home--of her mother--of all who had loved her. All the incidents of her
                  sister's marriage, about three years previously, with <roleName type="military"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#fletcher">Captain</roleName>, now <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#fletcher">Major Fletcher</persName>, came
                  freshly to her mind. All the little coquetries and flirtations of her girlish
                  existence rose up before her most vividly; and then came the revolt of the
                     <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName>--the attack upon their home--the
                  flight--the refuge at <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>--the siege--the
                  capitulation--the fancied freedom and escape in the boats, and the attack upon
                  them. No wonder that the brain of the young girl almost reeled with the agony of
                  such thoughts, and at such a time, too, when inevitable death seemed to glare upon
                  her.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> was awakened
                  from this painful reverie by her sister, who tremblingly whispered to her,
                     "<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>,
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>--oh, try
                  to look at him!--try to look at my dear little one or feel if there is warmth yet
                  at his heart! He is dead! he is surely dead! <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, tell me, if you
                  can--oh, tell me if he lives! When I try to look at him, there is such a cloud of
                  tears before my eyes, his sweet face seems to fade away from me in a far-off mist.
                  Tell me, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                  >Bessie</persName>--tell me if he yet breathes!"</p>
               <p>Scarcely less affected than <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                     >Annie</persName>, did poor <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie Hope</persName> place her trembling hand upon the heart of the child;
                  but then, as she thought she detected a feeble pulsation, she cried, "Yes, dead
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>--yes, he
                  lives yet! Heaven has preserved him yet to you! Do you not hear me?"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName> did
                  not speak. She had sunk down under the casement in a deep swoon. And now poor
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> thought
                  that she was quite alone, and that death had seized upon her sister, as it would
                  soon upon the child, if that feeble pulsation at the heart she had felt, was
                  indeed anything more than the last flutter of existence which precedes absolute
                  dissolution. A kind of dizzy, fading away feeling came over her, as if she, too,
                  was gradually slipping from the world into the abyss of eternity. The cries, and
                  the groans, and the sobs, and the impassioned prayer, and occasionally the wild
                  shrieks of her fellow captives, began to sound as if afar off. The sense of thirst
                  and of hunger became blended, and only now and then a kind of shudder passed
                  through the form of the young girl.</p>
               <p>What is that? what is that? A strange sound at the casement? <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie's</persName> head is close to
                  it, almost touching the lattice boards of which it is compose, as she might not,
                  in her then condition, have heard the sounds.</p>
               <p>Hush! there it is again! Now a voice!</p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>! <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>~" it cries.
                     "<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Miss Hope</persName>!"
                  then it says, as if with recollections of the ceremonies of social life; and then
                  the more familiar name of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName> comes to her ears! The words do not seem exactly as if
                  addressed to her; they seem rather like the ejaculations of some one whose mind
                  was so full of her image that the lips shape her name to themselves.</p>
               <p>Then there are blows upon the wood-work of the casement and a strange crackling
                  sound. Some splinters fall into the room, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> overcomes at once
                  all her lethargy, all her faintness, and springs to her feet!</p>
               <p>"Listen! listen! there is help! He is here! he here!"</p>
               <p>There is no reply, save a faint moan from <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>. Doubtless,
                  that one word, "help," had reached her mind, and it had aroused the dying embers
                  of existence.</p>
               <p>Again, the blows that were struck from without upon the casement sent splinters
                  into the room, and then the voice of the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young mountain chief</roleName>
                  sounded in the ears of the young girl, and in all the blessed confidence of
                  woman's heart in those it loves, she believed herself already saved, since he was
                  there to will it.</p>
               <p>With a wild hysterical joy she clung to the casement, and then it was, that
                  through the space made by the dagger of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> projected her
                  gentle hands, as we have already recorded, and welcome her deliverer.</p>
               <p>Oh, what joy not to be utterly deserted and lost! not to be all forgotten by every
                  human heart! How differently the blood now coursed its way through the veins of
                  the young and gentle girl! With what a world of unknown strength and power to save
                  her did she endow <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, and in her eyes how precious was his every word!</p>
               <p>There was a pause; for if the dreaded <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana <roleName type="honorific"
                        ref="#sahib">Sahib</roleName></persName> and all his host had been below,
                  and only waiting the moment to strike him dead, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> could not have done
                  other than he did, which was just to forget all the world in the exquisite joy of
                  that moment when he felt the gentle arms of her whom he loved, so tenderly around
                  him.</p>
               <p>He heard her sob his name; he heard her say that she loved him; that she would
                  love him, despite any possible circumstance that might seem to set up a bar to
                  their affection; and then he felt himself richly repaid for all that he had dared,
                  and for all that he had still to dare; for many perils were yet before him!</p>
               <p>It was the voice of the <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy"
                     >Highlander</addName> below that first aroused <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> to the necessity of
                  instant action.</p>
               <p>"My good lad," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy"
                     >Sandy</persName>, "<distinct type="scotsdialect">it no seems to me the noo,
                     that you are getting on with your wark!</distinct>"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> started.</p>
               <p>"Dearest!" he said to <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>, "you shall be saved! Go but a few paces from the window,
                  and I will make an opening sufficient to drag you through!"</p>
               <p>"Yes, yes! And my sister and the little one!"</p>
               <p>"Your sister here?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, yes! You will be good and great, and save her, too! My selfish head forgot
                  her for the moment; but, dear <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, you will not forget her!"</p>
               <p>"If I forget any that you love, may the angel of life forget me!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>.</p>
               <p>As he thus spoke, with fresh vigour and a strength that, to look at the slight
                  frame, no one could possible have given him credit for possessing, the <roleName
                     type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young
                     chief</roleName> recommenced his work of demolition of the casement, and soon a
                  wide orifice presented itself, through which any person of ordinary dimensions
                  might easily be dragged.</p>
               <p>But these operations necessarily attracted attention in the room, and when the
                  cool grey light of the night sky began to show itself through the opening in the
                  casement, there was a cry and a rush to that part of the room, and frantic notions
                  of escape began to suggest themselves to all who had yet life enough to cling to
                  the little that remained.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> for a moment
                  was nearly torn away from the window by the throng, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName> and the child were
                  literally trampled upon as they lay beneath it.</p>
               <p>Then it was that <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> vaulted into the room, and flinging a protecting arm around
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, he said,
                  in low but distinct tones, for he feared the <orgName type="indian"
                     >Sepoy</orgName> guard might hear the tumult, "For the love of the heaven you
                  adore and the God you all worship, hear me and be still!"</p>
               <p>There was than in the tone and manner of the young man that commanded silence; and
                  in the attitudes of hope, fear, and joy into which they had been thrown by the
                  voice at the casement, the unhappy throng listened to him in breathless
                  silence.</p>
               <p>"As heaven is my judge!" he said, "how gladly would I save all--but, alas! I
                  cannot! By disguising two as Hindoo women, I can possibly, and only possibly,
                  reach a small boat on the stream that flows close at hand outside the gates of the
                  city. To take more would be for all to perish miserably."</p>
               <p>There was an awful stillness, only now and then broken by sobs and moans.</p>
               <p>"What would you have me do?" he added. "Poor, sad hearts! will you let me save
                  those I can, by saving, or trying to save, those I love?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, yes!" said every voice; "yes! Heaven help them and you!"</p>
               <p>The saddened throng recoiled from the window, and gave themselves up to despair
                  and death!</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> burst into
                  tears, nor was <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> much less affected. It was a moment or two before he could
                  speak again, and then he said, "Be of good heart, suffering ones! All may yet be
                  well. There are with me two of your country's soldiers, and them will I see in
                  safety past the city gates, and they shall hurry to the camp of your own troops,
                  and urge forward your countrymen to your rescue. Even now, before the dawn has
                  ripened into day, you may all be free; for I will chance my life upon aiding
                  you."</p>
               <p>There was a murmur of blessings and prayers for the safety of the <roleName
                     type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young
                     chief</roleName>, uttered through scalding tears; and then one fair young
                  creature, almost a child <pb n="115"/>
                  <cb n="1"/> herself, but the young mother of an infant of some two months old,
                  rushed to the window, and holding up her babe, she cried, in imploring
                  accents,--"Yes, yes! Leave me--leave us all, but those you can save! But, oh! take
                  my child! Save it! it is small and light to carry. God will help and reward you!
                  And when in that day when we shall all look upon the Majesty of Heaven, this
                  little one will hold up its sweet hands and testify for you. Oh, save it! save my
                  little infant, and I will stay and die content!"</p>
               <p>"I will--I will!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>. "By all my hopes, I will! Ah! you know not----" He had
                  taken the child in his arms.</p>
               <p>"Knows not what? what would you say?"</p>
               <p>"The little one is dead! It is already saved!"</p>
               <p>The young mother tottered a pace or two, and then fell heavily to the floor
                  insensible.</p>
               <p>Brighter, brighter each moment became the opening in the casement, for the dawn of
                  the new day was coming; and now <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> stooped, and with a
                  strength she did not think she possessed, but which was lent her by the oceasion,
                  she lifted her sister from the floor, and held her up to the casement.</p>
               <p>"Her first!" she said to <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>. "Her first!"</p>
               <p>Then the <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >young chief</roleName> tried to take the child from the arms of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>, to hand it
                  down to the <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy"
                  >Highlander</addName>; but in her despair the mother clutched it--dead or alive;
                  they knew not which it was--so closely to her breast, that without more force than
                  he would use, the gentle hill warrior could not take it from her; so he lifted
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName> and
                  the child together through the casement in his nervous arms.</p>
               <p>It was a feat of great strength that, standing so insecurely as he himself did on
                  the roof of the <placeName type="building">sentry-box</placeName>; but with skill
                  and coolness he managed it well.</p>
               <p>The <roleName type="military" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Highland
                     soldier</roleName>, who was taller than <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>, now stretched up
                  his arms, crying, "Deed, my lad, but that's weel down! Just let the bit lassie
                  doon to me, and I'll tak' good care she no has a fall."</p>
               <p>This was done well and skilfully, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName> was placed on
                  the ground in safety.</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="irishdialect">The top of the morning to you, ma'am,</distinct>"
                  said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>.</p>
               <p>The cool morning air had partially revived <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>, and she knew what
                  was going on, but she could not speak.</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="irishdialect">Oh, thin,</distinct>" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>, "<distinct
                     type="irishdialect">if you are speechless, just say so, and it's myself that
                     won't be after troubling you with conversation.</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">Just haud your tongue, will you?</distinct>" said
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName>. "<distinct
                     type="scotsdialect">You'll be gibbering us a' into trouble with the women
                     folk!</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"Now! now!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, as he held <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> in his arms.</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">A' weel, a' weel!</distinct>" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName>; "<distinct
                     type="scotsdialect">I shall get the next lassie doon better if I had just a
                     something to stand on.</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"Don't be after saying it twice," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>. "Isn't there me
                  back, any way?"</p>
               <p>The kind-hearted <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis"
                     >Dennis</persName> dropped down upon all fours, and the <addName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Highlander</addName> stood on his back
                  and handed down <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName> with ease.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> waved his
                  hand to the other occupants of the <placeName type="building">Assembly
                     Room</placeName>, and with a renewed promise of sending instant news of their
                  condition to <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#havelock">General
                     Havelock</persName>'s <placeName type="warfront">camp</placeName>, he sprang
                  down from the <placeName type="building">sentry-box</placeName> which had stood
                  them all in such good stead.</p>
               <p>"On, on!" he said. "Now, follow me--follow me quickly, for your lives' sakes! and
                  I hope yet that all will be well. Can your sister walk, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>--I mean, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Miss Hope</persName>?"</p>
               <p>"Call me <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>! Am
                  I not your <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>?
                  Can you walk, dear <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                     >Annie</persName>?"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">'Deed then!</distinct>" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName>, "there's any amount
                  o' help, ma'am, that you wad just like, if you will let an honest Highlander gie
                  it to you!"</p>
               <p>"Oh, thanks, thanks!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName> placed his
                  arms round <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName>'s waist, and lent her such effectual assistance that she
                  had scarcely to let her feet touch the ground at all.</p>
               <p>But still she clutched the child to her heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch6">CHAPTER VI</head>
               <head>THE BOAT, AND THE RESCUE.</head>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> clung to the
                  protecting arm of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, who felt a degree of happiness he had never known before,
                  or believed that human existence was capable of bestowing upon him; and so the
                  little part was about to leave the spot, when a strange clangour of cymbals and
                  the pattering of drums caused them to pause for a moment. It was well they did so,
                  for down the thoroughfare that passed close by the <placeName type="building"
                     >sentry-box</placeName>, there came a huge rubble rout of <orgName
                     type="indian">Sepoys</orgName>, with a couple of cannon and several of the
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana's</persName>
                  officers.</p>
               <p>Whither they were bound, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> had no sort of idea or means of knowing; but the detention
                  of the whole party appeared now to be quite certain, and for an in<cb n="2"/>stant
                  even <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> did not
                  seem to see his way out of this dilemma.</p>
               <p>The intellect of the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young chief</roleName> was, however,
                  fertile in expedients, and possibly the stake he had on hand--namely, the life of
                  his beloved one--sharpened still further his apprehension. In another moment he
                  adopted the only possible means of safety.</p>
               <p>"Dear <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>!" he
                  whispered, hurriedly. "The <placeName type="building">sentry-box</placeName> is
                  large--you and your sister hide in it at once! You, my brave and good friends,
                  crouch down in the shadow behind it! Quick! oh, quick!"</p>
               <p>In truth, there was not a moment to lose, for the troop of <orgName type="indian"
                     >Sepoys</orgName> was rapidly advancing, and had the dawn been but half an hour
                  further advanced, it would have been out of the question to carry out <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur's</persName> project.</p>
               <p>As it was, the dispositions he counselled were at once adopted, and then
                  possessing himself of the dead Sepoy's cap and musket once again, and dragging the
                  body out of sight, although in such close companionship with the two soldiers that
                  they had to stand upon it, he, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, placed himself directly before the open side of the
                     <placeName type="building">sentry-box</placeName>, and stood in the calm
                  attitude of a soldier on guard.</p>
               <p>A mounted officer diverged a little from the advancing force, and called out to
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, "All
                  well here, sentinal?"</p>
               <p>"All well, <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                     >Sahib</roleName>!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, as he saluted the officer, who from not being of rank
                  sufficient to have such a mark of honour paid him by a sentinal, was all the more
                  flattered by it, and rode on.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> breathed no
                  more freely. He thought that the danger was past, but it was not so. An officer of
                  the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana's</persName>, on foot,
                  called out, "The sentinels at this post were doubled! Where is your comrade,
                  soldier?"</p>
               <p>"He fled, on hearing a strange noise in the direction of the gate," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>.</p>
               <p>"The coward! he has the soul of a <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>!"</p>
               <p>The officer then gave an order to his followers, and one of them marched up to
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, saying,
                  "I am to stay with you, comrade, until the relief comes. You will be glad of the
                  company!"</p>
               <p>"Very!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                  >Jeffur</persName>.</p>
               <p>The <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young
                     chief</roleName> felt that if the suspicions of the Sepoy were for a moment
                  awakened, before his comrades got too far to aid him, all would be lost, so he
                  kept himself before the <placeName type="building">sentry-box</placeName> in such
                  a position that in the dim light it would be impossible for the other to see into
                  it.</p>
               <p>As for his friends, the two soldiers, he knew that they were quite securely
                  hidden.</p>
               <p>"Do you know, my friend!" said the Sepoy with a hideous grin, "that the great
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> devotes the
                     <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName> women to
                  destruction with the coming day?"</p>
               <p>"I did not know!"</p>
               <p>"Oh, I see now, you are of <geogFeat type="hills"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#dooctees">the hills</geogFeat>! You belong not
                  to one of the regiments?"</p>
               <p>"I do not; but I have fought with <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana Sahib</persName>!"</p>
               <p>"That is good! And now, O my friend, when do you expect the relief, for, to tell
                  you the sacred truth, I have a <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName> girl in my
                     <placeName type="building">bungalow</placeName> at home!"</p>
               <p>"Indeed?"</p>
               <p>"Even so! I took her myself from the boats, and she is fair to look upon as the
                  moon!"</p>
               <p>"My friend!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, assuming a mysterious look, "step aside! I, too, have
                  something to communicate!"</p>
               <p>As he spoke, the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young chief</roleName> so faced the
                  Sepoy that his back was towards the hiding-place of the two soldiers, who, he
                  though, would readily enough take the hint of what they were to do.</p>
               <p>"What is it, O wise comrade?" said the Sepoy.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> stretched
                  out his hand, and placed it, as if carelessly, on the lock of the Sepoy's musket,
                  as he added, "It is you, my friend, who are wise, for you know more than I do, and
                  it is what I want to know."</p>
               <p>"Speak!"</p>
               <p>"What is the password at the gates till dawn?"</p>
               <p>"If you know not, O fellow soldier, be content to lay the head of ignorance on the
                  pillow of patience, for I may not tell you."</p>
               <p>With a sudden wrench, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> turned the musket from the grasp of the Sepoy; and then,
                  holding with his other hand his dagger to his throat, he said, in low, clear
                  tones, "A word above your breath--a cry--a struggle--and you are a dead man!"</p>
               <p>The Sepoy looked aghast for a moment, and then he seemed, on the sudden, to think
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> but a
                  silly conqueror, who left him free to make a rapid retreat; and as he had an idea,
                  from what <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>
                  said, that the report of a musket would not at all answer his views, whatever they
                  were, he turned with a quickness of a flash of light, to fly, and flew into the
                  arms of the <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy"
                  >Highlander</addName>.</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect">Whar are you ganging, in all that muckle hurry, my
                     mon?</distinct>" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy"
                     >Sandy</persName>.</p>
               <p>The Sepoy staggered back, and then made a rush sideways, when he fell headlong
                  over <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>.</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="irishdialect">Bad luck to you, you spalpeen!</distinct>" said
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>; <cb
                     n="3"/>"<distinct type="irishdialect">is that your manners, when a gentleman
                     gathering himself up to his feet with a mighty great cramp in his knees, owing
                     to hiding in a place not big enough at all, at all?</distinct>"</p>
               <p>The Sepoy stood on the ground bewildered.</p>
               <p>"On your life, silence!" added <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>. "Silence, except to what I shall demand of you! What is the
                  pass-word at the gates?"</p>
               <p>The Sepoy was silent, until the point of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>'s dagger penetrated
                  the skin of his throat; then he gasped out, "<placeName type="city"
                     >Delhi</placeName>!"</p>
               <p>"That is well! Where is your <placeName type="building">bungalow</placeName>?</p>
               <p>"By the <geogName type="river">river Ghant</geogName>."</p>
               <p>He indicated, with his finger, the direction as he spoke.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> nodded.
                  Then, motioning to the Highlander to keep a sharp eye on their prisoner, he went
                  to the <placeName type="building">sentry-box</placeName>, and whispered hastily to
                  the sisters, "Come forth at once! There is now only one chance of escape! Follow
                  me at once! Oh, would that the day were yet an hour in its coming!"</p>
               <p>A hazy, purplish flash of light from the East at this moment lit up the tops of
                  the tallest minarets and cupolas in the city. "On! on!" added <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, in anxious tones.
                  "Follow me!"</p>
               <p>He entwined his arm, now, in that of the Sepoy, while the <addName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Highlander</addName> and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName> escorted the
                  sisters.</p>
               <p>"To your <placeName type="building">bungalow</placeName>, at once!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> to the Sepoy; "and,
                  if you would save your life, you will bring from it two female dresses of the
                  country, and as much other apparel that may disguise, for a passing glance or so,
                  two men, as you have."</p>
               <p>"On my head be it!" said the Sepoy who, since the touch with the dagger of
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, had
                  shook with fear.</p>
               <p>Skirting the side of the <placeName type="building">Assembly House</placeName>,
                  and passing down a narrow lane, with wretched huts on each side of it, the Sepoy
                  led them to a more open space, not far from the river, and then, pointing to a
                  thatched <placeName type="building">bungalow</placeName>, he said, "Lord of my
                  fate, wait but a few moments, and I will return with all that you want."</p>
               <p>"Good, O comrade," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>; "but I prefer going with you."</p>
               <p>The Sepoy nearly howled with rage; but the strong grasp of the young warrior was
                  upon him; and the blood from the slight wound in his neck yet slowly trickled on
                  to his breast.</p>
               <p>"So be it," he said "We are in the hands of fate."</p>
               <p>"Very true," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>.</p>
               <p>The Sepoy led the way to the <placeName type="building">bungalow</placeName>, at
                  the door of which he tapped gently, and then opened it without further ceremony. A
                  Hindoo woman, of one of the lowest castes, came forward to meet him.</p>
               <p>"Quick!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>.</p>
               <p>The Sepoy spoke harshly and hastily to his wife, in explanation of the wants of
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>; and the
                  clothing was quickly procured.</p>
               <p>"Is my lord content?" he said.</p>
               <p>"Happy is he," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>, "who is content with little. Come along!"</p>
               <p>The Sepoy understood perfectly well that <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> did not intend to
                  part with him yet. It would have been the height of indiscretion to do so;
                  therefore, he doggedly proceeded along with his captors. It was at this moment
                  that a loud gong was sounded in the direction of the <placeName type="building"
                     >Assembly House</placeName>, and several shots were fired in a dropping,
                  irregular manner.</p>
               <p>The escape, and the fate of the sentinel by the corner of the wall, had been
                  discovered, and this was the dropping fire of the different sentries to alarm the
                  main guard. A dark, malicious smile came over the face of the Sepoy, and then, as
                  some fear for his own safety crossed his mind, he said, "My lord will not
                  sacrifice me for no good to himself?"</p>
               <p>"No," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>;
                  "but we want a boat! He who procures me one is a friend; he who does not is a
                  foe!"</p>
               <p>The Sepoy did not seem to think this was very logical reasoning, but it had its
                  effect, for all that. He uttered, in a low tone, an imprecation, and then he said,
                  "This way! this way!"</p>
               <p>The <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young
                     chief</roleName> paused but a moment or two to hastily cover up the few
                  articles of English costume that the sisters had on, with the clothing obtained
                  from the Sepoy's <placeName type="building">bungalow</placeName>; and then,
                  handing the other apparel to the <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy"
                     >Highlander</addName> and <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis"
                     >the Irishman</addName>, he said. "At a distance, probably these may save you
                  from a shot and a pursuit, although they would be no disguise for half a moment on
                  close inspection. Hide your uniforms as best you may, and place these cloths round
                  your heads."</p>
               <p>These directions were quickly obeyed, and the whole part reached a small <foreign
                     xml:lang="hi" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#ghaut">ghaut</foreign>, or
                  water-stairs, below which several native boats lay idly, swaying to and fro, in
                  the stream.</p>
               <p>"Oh, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>!"
                  whispered <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>,
                  "whither shall we go for safety?"</p>
               <p>"As heaven is my judge, I hardly know!" said the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young chief</roleName>; "but, if we
                  can get out of <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>, we <pb n="116"/>
                  <cb n="1"/> shall perhaps be able to find a route to safety! As for me, I must, I
                  fancy, to <geogFeat type="hills" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#dooctees">the
                     hills</geogFeat>!"</p>
               <p>"You? Oh, no! With us, and with all who are friends to us, you will be safe and
                  honoured!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> shook his
                  head.</p>
               <p>"In calmer moments, perhaps, yes," he said; "but, unhappily, the blood of your
                  countrymen is up! I have fought in the ranks of the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>, and my dress and arms
                  would at once, without further inquiry, procure me a shameful or a horrible death,
                  by order of the first English officer who had me in his power!"</p>
               <p>"Can that be possible?"</p>
               <p>"It is too true! Friends are now confounded with foes, and those who have but
                  drawn the sword for <placeName type="country">India</placeName> are strung up,
                  like dogs, along with those who have massacred the mother and the babe! I dare not
                  trust your countrymen at present!"</p>
               <p>"Then farewell to <placeName type="country">India</placeName> for many a long
                  year!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>,
                  mournfully.</p>
               <p>They had reached the steps leading to the water, when, from the terrace of a house
                  close at hand, a loud voice challenged them.</p>
               <p>"Who goes there? Hillo! Guard here!"</p>
               <p>It was as <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>
                  had suspected all the <foreign xml:id="hi" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#ghaut"
                     >ghauts</foreign>, down to the most insignificant, had been made posts or
                  guard-houses, so that they were equivalent to so many gates to the city. It was
                  such a contingency as this that had made <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> so anxious to get
                  the proper pass-word of the night.</p>
               <p>"The <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana's</persName> orders!"
                  said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, in a
                  loud voice. "I bear his signet as my authority!"</p>
               <p>"And the pass-word?"</p>
               <p>Now it was that <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> shook a little, for he could not be sure that what the Sepoy
                  had told was really and truly the pass; but there was no resource but to risk it;
                  so he said, with all the ease and boldness he could assume, "<placeName
                     type="city">Delhi</placeName>!"</p>
               <p>"That is well! Pass on!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> drew a long
                  breath of relief, and a tender glance passed between him and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>.</p>
               <p>"To the boats!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> to the Sepoy. "You shall not be injured; but our own safety
                  makes it imperative that you should go with us for some distance. We will land you
                  in safety, and you shall be paid for your apparel and your time."</p>
               <p>"It is well, O king!" said the Sepoy, with a touch of sarcasm in his tone and
                  manner.</p>
               <p>At that early hour in the morning the boats were left quite unmanned and
                  unprotected. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>
                  motioned to the <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy"
                     >Highlander</addName> and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis"
                     >Dennis</persName> to enter one and hand in the sisters. For his own part, the
                  necessity of keeping a close watch on the Sepoy made it imperative that he should,
                  for the time, leave all other matters to his companions.</p>
               <p>"Come!" he said, when the others were seated in the boat.</p>
               <p>Boom, at this moment, went a great gun somewhere in the city.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> and
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName> uttered
                  each a slight cry of alarm. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> flung the Sepoy into the boat, and jumped in after him. At
                  this moment there came rushing down to the ghaut several Sepoy officers and men,
                  and one called out, "Guard! guard! fire on the escaping prisoners! By the Nana's
                  order, kill! kill! kill!"</p>
               <p>The Sepoy in the boat uttered a yell of triumph; and as <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> for a moment left
                  him unwatched, in order that he might hoist the small square sail of the boat, and
                  catch the morning air that was curling the surface of the stream into tiny waves,
                  he sprung overboard, and struck out swimming for the land, which they had only
                  drifted from about twenty yards.</p>
               <p>"Fire!" he cried, as he lifted his head above the water; "fire on the accursed
                     <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName> women and on the
                  apostate! Fire!"</p>
               <p>Up flew the little sail. For a moment it clung to the tapering mast, and then it
                  flapped out to the breeze as <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName> shook it freely.</p>
               <p>"Hold that!" he cried to the <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy"
                     >Highlander</addName>, as he gave him the hempen rope that held the sail.
                  "Down, down, all of you!--down, if you would live!"</p>
               <p>"Fire!" cried a voice in Hindostanee.</p>
               <p>A volley of musketry rattled over and about the boat. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> stood up in the
                  stern, and with a small silver-mounted pistol he took from his breast, and the
                  barrel of which was some eight or ten inches long, and rifled, he took aim at the
                  Sepoys who had just scrambled out of the water on to the steps of the ghaut, and
                  had raised a delirious shout of exultation.</p>
               <p>"Die, dog!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>.</p>
               <p>There was a sharp report--a shriek, and the Sepoy, balancing himself for a moment
                  on his heels, fell backward into the stream.</p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>," cried
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, "speak
                  to me! You are unhurt?"</p>
               <p>"Quite, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                  >Jeffur</persName>!"</p>
               <p>"And your sister?"</p>
               <p>"Safe and well!"</p>
               <p>"Thank heaven!"</p>
               <p>"Well," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName>,
                  "young man, you might just <cb n="2"/> have passed the compliment of saying,
                     '<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName>, how did
                  you like that ball in your shoulder, my man?'"</p>
               <p>"Ah, you are hurt, my friend?"</p>
               <p>"Hit, but not much hurt, for that matter?"</p>
               <p>"Mother of Moses!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis"
                     >Dennis</persName>, who was looking to the shore,--"if they haven't brought a
                  big gun down to the steps! <distinct type="irishdialect">Oh, be
                  aisy!</distinct>"</p>
               <p><emph>(To be continued in our next.)</emph></p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
