<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<TEI>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Sepoys; Or, Highland Jessie: an electronic edition</title>
            <author>James Malcolm Rymer</author>
            <editor>Rebecca Nesvet</editor>
            <editor>Rae X. Yan</editor>
            <editor type="technical">Adam McCune</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Rebecca Nesvet</publisher>
            <publisher>Rae X. Yan</publisher>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <idno>sepoys</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct xml:id="frontmatter">
               <analytic>
                  <author>Rebecca Nesvet</author>
                  <author>Rae X. Yan</author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="2014" />
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <!-- Information about the encoding of the text -->
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Information about the project itself (goals, organization, activities)</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Information about how the texts in a collection were chosen or excerpted</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="unknown">
               <p>Information about treatment of errors in the source (silently corrected, etc.)</p>
            </correction>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Information about normalization practices (e.g. treatment of roman numerals,
                  spelling, etc.)</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation form="std">
               <p>Information about treatment of quotations (preservation of original quotation
                  marks, etc.)</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="hard">
               <p>Treatment of the hyphenation of the source</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Information about whether and how the text has been segmented (mostly for
                  linguistic purposes)</p>
            </segmentation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Information about any interpretive information added to the text</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="frontmatter">
            <div xml:id="full_intro">
               <head xml:id="text_intro">Introduction</head>
               <p>On 10 May 1857, there was a disturbance in the central Indian garrison of
                  <placeName>Meerut</placeName>. A group of <orgName>sipahis</orgName> or
                  ‘<orgName>Sepoys</orgName>’, indigenous soldiers, rebelled against their
                  British commanders. Over the two years following, this ‘Sepoy Mutiny’ quickly
                  spread to nearby <placeName>Delhi</placeName> and then fanned out across the vast
                  subcontinent. Meanwhile, in <placeName>Britain</placeName>, it inspired many
                  literary, dramatic, and artistic representations. One of the earliest--and perhaps
                  the earliest such work of prose fiction--was the ‘penny blood’ <emph rend="italic"
                     ><title>The Sepoys, or Highland Jessie: A Tale of the Present Indian
                        Revolt</title></emph> (1858). Written while the rebellion was in progress by
                  the prolific ‘<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">M. J.
                     Errym</persName>’ (<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">James
                        Malcolm Rymer</persName>, creator of <persName>Sweeney Todd</persName>),
                  <title><emph rend="italic">The Sepoys</emph></title> was serialized in
                  <title><emph>Reynolds’s Miscellany</emph></title>. In its first instalment,
                  <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">Rymer</persName> explains that
                  ‘[t]he political and public incidents of the Indian Revolt will be the stream in
                  the current of which will be carried forward the individuals whose adventures we
                  shall pourtray’. Those ‘individuals’ include the fictional ‘<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie Brown</persName>’, the
                  Scottish Highlander heroine of a widely circulated urban legend about the Indian
                  Revolt.</p>
               <p>Today, scholarship on literary representations of the Indian Revolt and the legend
                  of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie Brown</persName>
                  wholly neglects <title><emph rend="italic">The Sepoys</emph></title>. ‘For a
                  decade or so’ after the Revolt, states the scholar <persName>Christopher
                     Herbert</persName>, it was ‘at the same time too overwhelmingly a matter of
                  experiential fact and too lacerating emotionally to allow for fictional
                  representation except in refracted forms’. <persName>Gautam Chakravarty</persName>
                  disagrees. He identifies Revolt poetry, prose, and drama dating from the late
                  1850s, but, like <persName>Herbert</persName>, does not mention <title><emph
                     rend="italic">The Sepoys</emph></title>. This silence is not surprising, as
                  penny fiction of all kinds tends to receive less critical attention than the
                  canonical high literature of the Victorian era, and <title><emph rend="italic">The
                     Sepoys</emph></title> was no bestseller. Despite its obscurity, <title><emph
                        rend="italic">The Sepoys</emph></title>’ early depiction of the Indian
                  Revolt, its treatment of Indian and British subaltern subjects, and its eclectic
                  take on ‘<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Highland
                     Jessie</persName>’ all merit its recovery for the Victorian canon.</p>
               <p><title><emph rend="italic">The Sepoys</emph></title> begins in the besieged city
                  of <placeName>Cawnpore</placeName> (<placeName>Kanpur</placeName>). Enter our
                  hero, a fictional young Sepoy and ‘mountain chieftain’ named <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur Ahib</persName>. He is trying
                  to rescue a British woman he loves, one <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName>, who is among
                  the British women and children imprisoned by the tyrannical (and historical)
                  <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana Sahib</persName>, an
                  ally of the Sepoys. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana
                     Sahib</persName> has incarcerated these Britons in the <placeName>Cawnpore
                        Assembly Room</placeName>. This place name would have struck <persName
                           corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">Rymer</persName>’s readers with terror:
                  at the end of the historical siege, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana Sahib</persName> had all the
                  <placeName>Assembly Room</placeName>’s inmates murdered. Would <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> save <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, or must she must
                  perish in the liquidation of the makeshift dungeon? </p>
               <p> At this suspenseful point, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#rymer"
                  >Rymer</persName> turns back the clock several weeks to question the dominant
                  British narrative. He reveals that before the revolt’s outbreak, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> had interceded on
                  his tyrannized peasant subjects’ behalf with Bessie’s English friends. Key among
                  these are the ruthless East India Company army captain <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal Hawkins</persName> and his
                  avaricious bureaucrat brother <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>. Their characterization hardly flatters the regime they
                  represent. Their surnames suggest that they are state-sanctioned pirates, like the
                  English privateer <persName>Sir John Hawkins</persName>, cousin of
                  <persName>Francis Drake</persName>. The Hawkinses' decidedly unchristian
                  forenames identify them with two ruthless empire-builders, one of whom,
                  <persName>Julius Caesar</persName>, invaded ancient
                  <placeName>Britain</placeName>. This allusion shifts the text's perspective by
                  drawing parallels between the disenfranchised Indians and the British readers' own
                  ancestors. </p>
               <p>The Hawkinses' actions make the revolution's outbreak intelligible. In their first
                  scene, in pre-revolutionary <placeName>Delhi</placeName>, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName> begs the two men
                  for assistance for an Indian peasant family whom their recreational hunting has
                  rendered homeless and whose crops they have destroyed. Unconcerned by the deaths
                  of indigenous peasant children, the Hawkinses anticipate the <persName>Marquis of
                     St-Evremonde</persName>, aristocratic villain of <persName>Dickens</persName>’
                  <title><emph rend="italic">A Tale of Two Cities</emph></title> (1859). The
                  Hawkinses abuse many Indian characters with the ‘N’ word and also call them
                  ‘rascals’. In <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">Rymer</persName>’s
                  words, before the Revolt, these ‘European residents’ in
                  <placeName>India</placeName> ‘idly lolled upon their silken cushions, little
                  dreaming of the volcano that was to explode over and around them!’ When the revolt
                  erupts, they risk reaping what they have sown. Tyrants in peacetime, the
                  <persName>Hawkins</persName> brothers are transformed by war. Adversity enables
                  <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> to become an active military hero--and the protective lover
                  of an Indian princess, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#zeelook"
                     >Zeelook</persName>. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                        >Jeffur</persName> does not overthrow the British Empire; instead, he learns to
                  reform it from within. He protects <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> and other British
                  characters from their Sepoy enemies, who, with the exception of himself, are
                  represented as atavistic savages or Oriental tyrants. He is capable of
                  revolutionary violence but suppresses it in himself and others. </p>
               <p> In this sense, he is an Indian proponent of‘ nonviolent or ‘moral force’
                  Chartism’, a movement that <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR"
                     >Rymer</persName> and his fiction workshop colleagues promoted in the 1840s.
                  ‘Chartism’ (1837-48) was the struggle for expanded suffrage, food security, and
                  other rudimentary civil rights for working-class Britons. Its name derived from
                  the ‘People’s Charter’, a <emph rend="italics">Magna Carta</emph>-inspired list of
                  demands drawn up in 1838, primarily by <persName>William Lovett</persName>, the
                  founder of the <orgName>London Working-Men’s Association</orgName>
                  (<orgName>LWMA</orgName>). <persName>Lovett</persName> promoted nonviolent
                  Chartism, and found himself at odds with the MP for
                  <placeName>Nottingham</placeName>
                  <persName>Feargus O’Connor</persName>, who argued, to the alarm of much of the
                  establishment, that working-class rights would be won only if the
                  <orgName>Chartists</orgName> displayed a credible threat of violent revolt.
                  <orgName>Parliament</orgName> refused to ratify the Charter, and the outcome of
                  the Chartist movement remains the matter of debate. Either the
                  <orgName>Chartists</orgName>, split ideologically between
                  <persName>Lovett</persName> and <persName>O’Connor</persName>’s philosophies
                  and lacking elite buy-in, failed, or their campaign indirectly contributed to the
                  suffrage and Parliamentary reform that, in the shadow of the continental
                  revolutions of 1848, created modern British government. </p>
               <p> In any case, one of the Chartists’ key vehicles was the penny press. <persName
                  corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">Rymer</persName>’s publishers
                  <persName>G.W.M. Reynolds</persName> and <persName>Edward Lloyd</persName> were
                  both <orgName>Chartists</orgName>. The critic <persName>Troy Boone</persName> has
                  shown that the genre of the penny blood tended in its content and even narrative
                  structure to promote moral force Chartism. Boone demonstrates this argument with a
                  persuasive reading of the 1842 blood <title><emph rend="italic">Varney the
                     Vampire, or, The Feast of Blood</emph></title>, which <persName>Helen R.
                        Smith</persName> and others have attributed conclusively to <persName
                           corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">Rymer</persName>. </p>
               <p> In 1858, the Chartist moment had long since passed. The Charter was abandoned,
                  <persName>O’Connor</persName> was dead, and <persName>Lovett</persName>
                  languished in obscurity. However, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur Sahib</persName> is a Chartist
                  in all but name, because he first employs moral force to rescue his people from
                  the Hawkins’ casual depredation, then, despairing of moral force’s efficacy, joins
                  the <orgName>Sepoys</orgName> in their rebellion, and finally abandons that on
                  account of its cruelty. He tries all the competing Chartist strategies, and ends
                  the serial as a conscientious, uneasy, yet essential collaborator with an elite
                  that otherwise will not let him save his people and theirs. </p>
               <p>As important as this ambivalence is <persName
                  corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">Rymer</persName>’s superimposition of
                  Chartist history over the Indian Rebellion. It suggests that despite his often
                  disturbingly racist depiction of Indians, he understood that the people of
                  <placeName>Britain</placeName> and <placeName>India</placeName> were fighting
                  the same battle against a common elite enemy, represented not only by the
                  Hawkinses but by their entitled upper-class hanger-on <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">The Honourable Miss
                     Flint</persName>, the butt of much cruel humor. As hard-headed and hearted as
                  the stone for which she is named, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">The Honourable Miss
                     Flint</persName> delusionally persists in believing that one of the Hawkinses
                  will marry her, is upset not to be treated, by the villains, as a desirable
                  heroine, and endangers the entire party of British refugees in order to rescue her
                  ‘reticule’, or handbag. <persName>Boone</persName> points out that penny bloods
                  often taught working-class families to question the elite narrative of Victorian
                  imperialism. <title><emph rend="italic">The Sepoys</emph></title> seems to, a
                  decade after the height of the Chartist struggle. </p>
               <p>
                  <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#rymer">Rymer</persName> also
                  dynamically revamps the legend of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie Brown</persName>. This
                  mythical tradition began in <placeName>Britain</placeName> a few months after the
                  outbreak of the revolt. In December 1857 and well into 1858, papers across
                  <placeName>England</placeName>, <placeName>Scotland</placeName>,
                  <placeName>Wales</placeName>, <placeName>Ireland</placeName>, and the
                  <placeName>United States</placeName> printed a report on the 1857 Sepoy Siege
                  of <placeName>Lucknow</placeName> allegedly derived from a French physician,
                  ‘<placeName>M. Banneroi</placeName>’s’ ‘Letter to the Editor’ of a Parisian
                  paper. The fictional doctor claimed that during the siege, one <perName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie Brown</perName>, the
                  <placeName>Highland</placeName> Scottish wife or fiancee of a British soldier,
                  had a delirious vision of traditional <placeName>Highland</placeName> bagpiping or
                  folksong. ‘Dinna ye hear it?’ she is said to have asked her bewildered carers.
                  Shortly thereafter, the letter claims, her lover’s <placeName>Highland</placeName>
                  regiment arrives and ends the siege. </p>
               <p> Only, it never happened. Quickly, journalists discovered that no ‘<persName
                  corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie Brown</persName>’ was at
                  <placeName>Lucknow</placeName>. The story was a ‘fable’, a ‘falsehood’, or, as
                  one Scottish paper put it, ‘a shave’. By that point, however, the story had taken
                  on a life of its own, in popular music, published and performance poetry,
                  painting, and stage drama. The Irish-American playwright <persName>Dion
                     Boucicault</persName> staged his <title><emph rend="italic"><persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie Brown</persName>, or the
                        Relief at <placeName>Lucknow</placeName></emph></title> in <placeName>New
                           York</placeName>’s <placeName>Wallack’s Theatre</placeName> as early as
                  February 22, 1858, with ads appearing by February 16th. Three days earlier, in
                  <placeName>London</placeName>, <title><emph rend="italic">Reynolds’s
                     Miscellany</emph></title> had published the first instalment of <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">Rymer</persName>’s <title><emph
                           rend="italic">The Sepoys</emph></title>. Evidently, neither
                  <persName>Boucicault</persName> nor <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">Rymer</persName> appropriated material
                  from the other, as they had not time. Instead, they both ripped the same story
                  from the pages of their respective local newspapers. </p>
               <p> By February 1858, the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie
                  Brown</persName> story was ‘completely exploded’, but in <title><emph
                     rend="italic">The Sepoys</emph></title>, <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">Rymer</persName> makes it relatively
                  fresh and surprising. Firstly, he refrains from introducing <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie</persName> until chapter
                  <!--what chapter?-->. In the meantime, he builds the audience’s admiration for the
                  true hero <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>,
                  the suspense concerning <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>’s captivity among the doomed women of
                  <placeName>Cawnpore</placeName>, and the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>-<persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> romance plot.
                  Secondly, while most accounts of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">Jessie Brown</persName>’s vision
                  present her as a passive heroine, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR"
                     >Rymer</persName> makes her an action figure. Granted, she pines for her
                  soldier love and rejects <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana
                     Sahib</persName>'s advances, but she also wields a cavalry sword and an Enfield
                  rifle. Thus armed, she protects not only <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> and other British
                  women, but several rather feckless British soldiers, too. This masculine heroism
                  makes <title><emph rend="italic">The Sepoys</emph></title> a foil for the
                  initially decadent Hawkins brothers. She challenges them to shape up and fulfill
                  their potential as defenders of the Empire and all its people: Scottish and
                  English, British and Indian.</p>
               <p>
                  <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">Rymer</persName>’s other minor
                  characters offer versions of Scottish and Irish identities that promote British
                  cohesion without English supremacism. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>, the most capable
                  and courageous of the British characters, demonstrate the necessity of Scottish
                  and Irish labor to the defense of <placeName>Britain</placeName>’s overseas
                  empire. At the tale’s conclusion, two transcultural marriages take place, and will
                  evolve under the eye of a new regime: the British Raj. Notably, the two Indians
                  involved, northern Muslims, are depicted as light-skinned in relation to the
                  Hindus. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">Rymer</persName>’s
                  progressivism extended to Chartist rhetoric, but not to imagining a British Empire
                  not ruled whites, nor to interracial marriage. The marriage plot is a device that
                  dramatizes the willing wedding of British and Indian elites. As such, it seems to
                  legitimate the Raj--the system of direct rule that replaced the <orgName>East
                     India Company</orgName>'s management of colonial <orgName>India</orgName>. </p>
               <p> Why should <orgName>Price One Penny Editions</orgName> revive this problematic,
                  unpopular, and not particularly well-written baggy monster? Firstly, our edition
                  will reveal the ‘penny blood’ genre’s engagement not only with the dynamics of
                  urban life--in this case, in 1857 <placeName>Delhi</placeName>--but with the
                  global as well. Secondly, it is a seminal and relatively late component of the
                  <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">James Malcolm Rymer</persName>
                  canon, which ought to be recovered, as <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">Rymer</persName> was not only extremely
                  prolific and influential, but, in his own time, admiringly paralleled with
                  <persName>Shelley</persName>. Comparing <title><emph rend="italic">The
                     Sepoys</emph></title> with other ‘bloods’ attributed to <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">Rymer</persName>, such as <title><emph
                           rend="italic">Varney the Vampire</emph></title>, <title><emph rend="italic"
                              >Ada, the Betrayed</emph></title>, or the ‘Sweeney Todd’ story <title><emph
                                 rend="italic">The String of Pearls</emph></title> may help to identify
                  <persName>Rymer</persName>'s aesthetic, political, and philosophical leanings.
                  <title><emph rend="italic">The Sepoys</emph></title> also belongs to the
                  Scottish diasporic literary tradition, not on account of its Scottish wanderer
                  characters, but because <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR"
                     >Rymer</persName> himself was the <placeName>London</placeName>-born son of a
                  (<placeName>Lowland</placeName>) Scot: <persName>Malcolm Rymer</persName>,
                  originally of <persName>Midlothian</persName>.</p>
               <p> Finally, <title><emph rend="italic">The Sepoys</emph></title> deserves attention
                  from scholars of postcolonial movements across the globe. As an early example of
                  Indian Revolt literature that engages the discourse of universal human rights, it
                  anticipates <persName>Reynolds</persName>’s fellow Chartist <persName>Ernest
                     Jones</persName>’s newspaper journalism and his poem <title><emph rend="italic"
                        >The Revolt of <placeName>Hindostan</placeName>, or, The New
                        World</emph></title>. In an 1857 editorial, <persName>Jones</persName>
                  proclaims that the rebel Sepoys oppose ‘one of the most iniquitous usurpations
                  that ever disgraced the annals of humanity’. By resisting this occupation, they
                  righteously defend ‘all that is sacred to man’. <persName>Jones</persName> then
                  exhorts his working-class British target readers to ‘recognize the independence of
                  the Indian race’, refuse to bear arms against the revolutionaries, and pursue
                  their own liberation. He reiterates this revolutionary rhetoric in the
                  aforementioned poem, which repeatedly equates revolutionary
                  <placeName>India</placeName> with ‘<placeName>America</placeName>’ (the
                  <placeName>United States</placeName>). Reinforcing the Revolt’s role in the
                  history of anticolonial revolution, its title recalls
                  <persName>Shelley</persName>’s <title><emph rend="italic">Cythna and Laon, or the
                     Revolt of Islam</emph></title> (1816). In that epic romance,
                  <persName>Shelley</persName> prophesies a nineteenth century revolution against
                  the Ottoman Empire. Like <persName>Jones</persName>’s <title><emph rend="italic"
                     >Revolt</emph></title>, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR"
                        >Rymer</persName>’s <title><emph rend="italic">The Sepoys</emph></title> played
                  a role in the Victorian imagination of the Indian independence struggle. It is
                  fortuitous that the digital revolution enables <orgName>Price One Penny</orgName>
                  to disseminate <title><emph rend="italic">The Sepoys</emph></title>, for the first
                  time in its history, to a global public.</p>
         </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
