<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model hcorresp="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!--<?xml-model hcorresp="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<!--
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/xsl" href="../xsl/rymer.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/css" href="../style.css" alternate="yes"?>
-->


<?xml-model href="../schema/sepoys.schema.xml" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Sepoys; Or, Highland Jessie: an electronic edition</title>
            <author>James Malcolm Rymer</author>
            <author>
               <persName type="pseudo">M. J. Errym</persName>
            </author>
            <editor>Rebecca Nesvet</editor>
            <editor>Rae X. Yan</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Rebecca Nesvet</publisher>
            <publisher>Rae X. Yan</publisher>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <idno>sepoys</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct xml:id="installment7" prev="sepoys.3.20.xml#installment6"
               next="sepoys.4.03.xml#installment8">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter XIII: A Fight and a Rescue--the Route to Delhi</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-03-27"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter XIV: The Sacrifice in the Rock Temple.--An Alarm</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-03-27"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <!-- Information about the encoding of the text -->
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Information about the project itself (goals, organization, activities)</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Information about how the texts in a collection were chosen or excerpted</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="unknown">
               <p>Information about treatment of errors in the source (silently corrected, etc.)</p>
            </correction>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Information about normalization practices (e.g. treatment of roman numerals,
                  spelling, etc.)</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation form="std">
               <p>Information about treatment of quotations (preservation of original quotation
                  marks, etc.)</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="hard">
               <p>Treatment of the hyphenation of the source</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Information about whether and how the text has been segmented (mostly for
                  linguistic purposes)</p>
            </segmentation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Information about any interpretive information added to the text</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="installment">
            <head>
               <date when="1858-03-27">Saturday, March 27, 1858</date>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="../facsimiles/sepoys.3.27.png"/>
            </figure>
            <pb n="161"/>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch13">CHAPTER XIII.</head>
               <p>A FIGHT AND A RESCUE.--THE ROUTE TO <placeName type="city">DELHI</placeName>.</p>

               <pb n="177"/>
               <cb n="1"/>
               <p>OH, happy, blessed sounds!--charming as the voices of the best beloeved
                  ones!--gentle, and spirit moving, as the songs of a happy dream!--with what a
                  fervid shout of joy was that shrill fife melody, and that roll of British drums,
                  welcomed by the poor beleagurered party, in the cavernous recess of that
                     <placeName type="building">old Indian quarry</placeName>!</p>
               <p>The sounds spoke of help, of rescue, of brave hearts and of willing hands close
                  almost as an embrace of affection. They come!--they come! The sounds deepen. The
                  pealing notes of the pipe invade the air each moment with more expressed
                  distinctness, and the echoes of the old quarry are awakened by the beating of the
                  martial drum!</p>
               <p>"Saved!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                     Hope</persName>. "Oh, we are saved!"</p>
               <p>Then those who had hidden in the narrow passage, at the back of the cavernous
                  recess, rushed forward, all heedless of any danger that might still be lurking
                  close at hand; and while the grateful tears streamed from their eyes, they crowded
                  to the narrow portal, where, still grim and arid, reposed the huge block of stone
                  at the entrance.</p>
               <p>"Back! Oh, back! all of you!" shouted <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>. "A
                  stray shot may yet do more mischief than all the efforts, as yet, of our
                  foes!"</p>
               <p>"Hark!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant
                     Adrian</persName>. "Hark! Do you hear that?"</p>
               <p>A rattling fire of musketry, from above, now broke the stillness of the moment,
                  for the drums and the fifes had ceased. The Sepoys in the hollow had heard the
                  approach of the English succours, and with cries of disappointed sage, had
                  precipitately fled up the steep <cb n="2"/>sides of the quarry, to join their main
                  body on the higher ground. And now there was one volley, so close and compact,
                  that it would only come from a British force in line; and then there was a cheer
                  following some order, a wild hurrah--a rush--and a sound of conflict!</p>
               <p>"They charge them!" cried the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>. "It is the only
                  way; a volley, and then the bayonet!"</p>
               <p>Confused cries and yells--a scattering fire--the sound of a bugle, recalling men
                  from a pursuit--and all was over. The Sepoy band was ruted, leaving behind them
                  elephants and baggage.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>
                  now rushed out of the cavern, on to the little plateau, and shouted out, "British
                  troops, hilloa!--hilloa!"</p>
               <p>"Who calls?" said a voice, and the cheery English tones were delightful to
                  hear.</p>
               <p>"Fugitives from <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>!" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>.</p>
               <p>"Come up!--all's right! Have you stood a siege there? We thought we heard
                  firing?"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>
                  and his party now rapidly emerged fromm the quarry, and were greeted by a knot of
                  officers, who stood on the brink of the hollow, to see what fugitivies they had
                  had the satisfaction of rescuing.</p>
               <p>The ladies were saluted respectfully, and each soon had a cavalier to guide her
                  steps over the broken ground. An officer in undress, picked his way towards them
                  on horseback, and when he saw the party, he called out, "Is that <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>, of the
                     <orgName>Native Infantry</orgName>?</p>
               <p>"The same!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>. "I have the pleasure to see <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood">Colonel Hood</persName>?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, my friend! We are from <placeName type="city">Agra</placeName> to <placeName
                     type="city">Delhi</placeName>, with about four hundred men. Have you any news
                  from that quarter?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, the worst!"</p>
               <p>"Not worse than ours, I fancy. <placeName type="city">Agra</placeName> is
                  beleaguered with mutinous Sepoys, and the flame seems spreading from place to
                  place. In fact, we have escaped!"</p>
               <p>"And we likewise! <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName> is a scene of uproar
                  and carnage. Blood flows in the streets. <!--[Tale of 2 Cities parallel?]--> We
                  have every reason to believe that a general massacre of Europeans has taken place.
                  We escaped by a series of hair-breadth chances that I dread to look back upon ;
                  and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant
                     Adrian</persName> here, of the cavalry, is badly wounded.</p>
               <cb n="3"/>
               <p>A group of officers now gathered round the little party, and drank in the tidings
                  of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> with strained and eager ears. The non-commissioned officers
                  and men of the small force heard detached words and sentences, and glanced at each
                  other with looks of deep interest. Then <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood">Colonel Hood</persName> waved
                  his hand, and called out, "Pile arms! Let the men rest an hour. Throw out some
                  sentinels in advance round the position, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#majorholmes">Major Holmes</persName>! All
                  this is very serious! Strike a tent for the ladies, Quartermaster, and see what
                  can be done in the name of refreshments! I thank God we came this way to rescue
                  you! The rascals fled, one over the other, at our charge! Of a truth, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>, we seem
                  to have lit upon evil times!"</p>
               <p>"I fear we have, <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Colonel</roleName>!"</p>
               <p>"And I know not what to do! Are the rebels in force, think you, at <placeName
                     type="city">Delhi</placeName>?"</p>
               <p>"The whole city is a swarming hive of rebellion!"</p>
               <p>"Humph! On my faith, I hardly know what to do! <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#generalwheeler">General Wheeler</persName> is
                  in some force about <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>!"</p>
               <p>"Oh, sir!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName>, do you know if <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#fletcher">Major Fletcher</persName> of the
                     <orgName type="military" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#32nd">32nd</orgName> is
                  with that force? The last station was <placeName type="city"
                  >Cawnpore</placeName>?"</p>
               <p>"Doubtless, madam, he is! But I see our fellows have got up a tent! Pray, ladies,
                  rest yourselves, and be assured of your safety with us!"</p>
               <p>The ladies, one and all, made their acknowledgements to <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood">Colonel Hood</persName> for his
                  timely rescue of them, all of which he gallantly deprecated, saying, as was indeed
                  true, that his arrival was but a fortunate chance,--"For which, however," he
                  added, "permit me to say that I shall ever feel most grateful!"</p>
               <p>The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Colonel</roleName> then
                  dismounted, and as the tents of the little force, one by one, rose up on the brink
                  of the quarry, the group of officers, with <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr. Hawkins</persName> and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>, looked warily
                  around them; and that vague feeling of watchfulness, which the fact of being in a
                  hostile country engenders, began to creep slowly over them.</p>
               <p>"Come into my tent," said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Colonel</roleName>, and tell me,
                  all of you, what you know of this fearful business which has come like a
                  thunder-clap upon us. Perhaps we shall be joined by other forces soon, and then I </p>
               <pb n="178"/>
               <cb n="1"/>
               <p>think, surely, we might make an attempt to wrest <placeName type="city"
                     >Delhi</placeName> from the hands of a few regiments of Sepoys!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>
                  shook his head as they all entered the tent tohether, where they found the
                     <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Colonel</roleName>'s
                  servant busy preparing some coffee, which, particularly to those of the party
                  whose adventures, since leaving <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>, we have
                  related, was a most delightful and seasonable refreshment. </p>
               <p>"Will you pardon me, <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Colonel</roleName>, said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon"
                     >Mr. Hawkins</persName>, "for hoping that our lady-friends are faring as well
                  as we are?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, you may be assured of that! But I am dying of impatience for what news you
                  can give me! For us, all we can say is, that we are glad to get away, with our
                  handful of men, from <placeName type="city">Agra</placeName>, which is one-half in
                  flames."</p>
               <p>"I think," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant
                     Adrian</persName>, advancing a step,--"I think that I can tell all that has yet
                  happened, unless their rising is a more simultaneous movement than it looks."</p>
               <p>"For heaven's sake speak, then!"</p>
               <p>"I was at <placeName type="city">Meerut</placeName>--"</p>
               <p>"But that is safe?"</p>
               <p>"You shall hear! All was, apparently, as usual--everything was going on with its
                  accustomed regularity in that station--the affair of the greased cartridges, which
                  I suppose you have heard, was believed to have blown over--"</p>
               <p>"Ah!" said a young officer, "I heard something of that! How was it?"</p>
               <p>Several others looked curious and interested, and the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant</roleName> added, "You
                  know, gentlemen, that the <orgName type="religious">Hindoos</orgName> look upon
                  the bull and cow as sacred animals, and the <orgName type="religious"
                     >Mahomedans</orgName> have a holy horror of the pig. Now, by whom the matter
                  was first mooted, it is hard to say; but by some means the Hindoo soldiery were
                  persuaded that the new cartridges introduced for the minie rifles were greased, in
                  order to make them slip along the grooved barrels easily, with the fat of the
                  sacred cow or bull; while to the Mahomednas the tale was told that the greasing
                  was accomplished with the obnoxious fat of swine. Tumults and disorders among the
                  men resulted; some were ordered imprisonment, and an order was issued, permitting
                  Sepoys to make their own cartridges, and to use what lubricating substance they
                  thought proper, so that it was considered there was an end of the affair." </p>
               <!-- explaining what caused Rebellion here -->
               <p>"So I heard," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood"
                     >Colonel Hood</persName>, "and we had a laugh over it at our mess, I recollect
                  quite well!"</p>
               <p>"Such, however, was not the fact. Either the Sepoys were embittered to a degree
                  past their patience, or a pretext was made of this cartridge budiness; for in the
                  midst of the fancied security at <placeName type="city">Meerut</placeName>, the
                  men of the <orgName type="military" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#11th">11th
                     Cavalry</orgName> rose, and fired on their officers; and in the course of a few
                  hours the whole station was in open mutiny. Europeans were fired at and cut down
                  wherever they were seen; and I, with some other officers, only escaped by the
                  fleetness of our horses. I was hurt at <placeName type="city">Meerut</placeName>,
                  but not seriously, and made my way to <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>,
                  but to encounter a second act of the mutiny in that city, with ten times the
                  horrors of <placeName type="city">Meerut</placeName>; and but for the timely aid
                  of my friends here, I must have perished. We are now fugitives from that
                  capital<!--sic-->, and whither to bend our steps we know not."</p>
               <p>There was a murmur of interest among the officers; and then <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood">Colonel Hood</persName> said
                  gravely, "I scarcely know what to do with my small force myself; but as you are
                  bothfit for duty--you, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>, and you, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian">Lieutenant Adrian</persName>--I fear I
                  must deprive your civilian friends of your escort, and order you on duty with my
                  force."</p>
               <p>"I hope not, sire!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                     >Lieutenant</roleName>. "I fancy I may say with some truth, that but for us,
                  already would the whole party have been massacred!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood">Colonel Hood</persName>
                  paced the tent with agitated steps; and then, as he was about to speak, a shot was
                  fired from without, and then another and another, as the line of sentinels took up
                  the alarm, and each fired his musket and fell back on the main body, according to
                  orders.</p>
               <p>An officer, dusty and heated, entered the tent, and saluted the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood">Colonel</roleName>.</p>
               <p>"Well,
                  <persName>Hardy</persName><!-- should we include this person in the personography?-->,
                  what is it now?"</p>
               <p>"A strong column of Sepoys are making their way through the wood, past us, on the
                  left of our position!"</p>
               <p>"Open on them, with the guns, as they deploy from the wood! We have but two guns,
                  I think?"</p>
               <p>"Only two eighteen-pounders, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Colonel</persName>!"</p>
               <p>"Get them into position at once! I will be with you directly! Gentlemen, to your
                  duty!" </p>
               <p>"I am with you, sir, if you please!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>.</p>
               <p>"And I!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                     >Lieutenant</roleName>.</p>
               <p>"Thank you, gentlemen! We are short of officers, I am sorry to say! Halloa, my
                  horse!"</p>
               <p>Bang! went one of the guns at this moment.</p>
               <p>"Ah! they are at it already!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#colonelhood">Colonel Hood</persName>, as he
                  sprung on his horse's back.</p>
               <cb n="2"/>
               <p>The whole party were in the open air in another moment. The troops had fallen in,
                  by order of the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#majorholmes"
                     >Major</roleName>, and stood to their arms; while at intervals of about half a
                  minute, one of the two guns kept delivering its fire. The blue smoke blew inthe
                  direction of where the troops stood to their arms; and as it cleared away for a
                  moment, an officer appeared, waving his sword, and a sharp rattle of musketry came
                  pealing on the air from the direction of the wood.</p>
               <p>The <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood">Colonel</persName>
                  galloped to the front of his troops, and cried "Forward!"</p>
               <p>The whole line was in motion, preceded by a company in skirmishing order, over the
                  irregular bit of roadway, and in the direction of the wood, until they dived in
                  among the smoke of the guns. The Sepoys, at that moment, had made a terrific rush
                  to the two pieces of cannon, to take them, if possible; and just as <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood">Colonel Hood</persName>, with
                  his red-coats, appeared, the men serving the guns had been compelled to retreat a
                  pace or two, for they had not time to load again.</p>
               <p>The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood">Colonel</roleName>
                  gave an order, and the English bugles sounded the recall of the skirmishers, and
                  these were in a moment absorbed in the ranks.</p>
               <p>"Halt! Make ready! Present! Fire!"</p>
               <p>A volley was poured into the thick of the advancing Sepoys, who had nearly reached
                  the guns: it was returned with a rattling discharge, and the men began to fall. A
                  ball struck <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>'s hat, and sent it flying. The word to "Charge!" was given,
                  and the whole line rushed forward with a cheer. The Sepoys stood till they saw the
                  very flash of the bayonets in the sun, and then they turned and fled.</p>
               <p>The recall of the troops was instantly sounded, or they would, without doubt, have
                  pursued the Sepoys into the wood, where there was no telling how large a force
                  might lie concealed. The men came scattering back, and were soon hid again behind
                  their guns, which kept sending shot after shot into the wood.</p>
               <p>As the smoke from the little engagement cleared off, there might be seen lying
                  grim and motionless in death, some twenty or thirty Sepoys; while the soldiers
                  were busy in the vanguard, supporting some of their wounded comrades, and several
                  lay dead close to the two guns. </p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood">Colonel Hood</persName>
                  advanced slowly past the flank of the troops, and they all noticed that his sword
                  dangled by the sword knot to his wrist, and they saw that one hand was pressed
                  against his breast.</p>
               <p>"The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood">Colonel</roleName>
                  is hurt!: exclaimed <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>, as he rushed forward and caught the horse by the
                  bridle.</p>
               <p>Several of the officers gathered anxiously round their wounded commander.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood">Colonel Hood</persName>
                  smiled faintly. "Tell," he said,--"tell the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#majorholmes">Major</roleName> to--to--"</p>
               <p>His head sunk upon his breast; and but for the half-dozen arms that supported him,
                  he would have fallen from the horse, which, as if with a consciousness of
                  something fearfully amiss, stood still and trembled. The boom of the cannon still
                  sounded at intervals, and then they laid the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood">Colonel</roleName> on the deep,
                  tall Indian grass, and some one called for the surgeon, who, flinging off his
                  cockedhat, knelt by the side of the prostrated man. </p>
               <p>"Is he badly hit?" anxiously inquired <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>.</p>
               <p>"He is dead!" said the surgeon. "The ball is in his head! How he came so far, I
                  can't imagine! <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#majorholmes">Major
                     Holmes</persName>, you are in command now; and I may informm you that I have
                  just been told the Sepoys are in force, in the wood, to the number of three
                  thousand men, or more!"</p>
               <p>"By whom?"</p>
               <p>"A wounded Sepoy we have as a prisoner," replied the surgeon.</p>
               <p>The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#majorholmes">Major</roleName>
                  sprung to his horse, and darted to the head of the men, and there a strange sight
                  presented itself to all; for, while the two guns kept playing upon then, full
                  three thousand Sepoys deployed swiftly from the wood and took the road to
                     <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>, putting up with the loss they
                  sustained by passing the range of the guns but not daring to attack them
                  again.</p>
               <p>"Will you let the rascals go, sir?" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>.</p>
               <p>"Yes! Our loss already exceeds forty men and the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood">Colonel</roleName>. Another such
                  victory, and they would be able to eat us up! They have no guns, or they would no
                  pass us in that way." </p>
               <p>And so the whole Sepoy force, leaving another hundred dead upon the field, passed
                  away; and when they got out of the range of the guns, they tried a cheer, as if
                  they had gained a victory, and beat drums and cymbals.</p>
               <p>A sad silence fell upon the little party, who had, at all events held off such a
                  vastly superior force; and the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#majorholmes">Major</roleName>, in a low tone,
                  consulted with his brother officers. Turning, then, to <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> and
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant
                     Adrian</persName>, he said, "Gentlemen, what do you propose to do?"</p>
               <cb n="3"/>
               <p>This was a question far more earily to be asked than answered; and the two young
                  men looked at each other, rather puzzled to know what to reply; which <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#majorholmes">Major Holmes</persName>
                  perceiving, induced him to add,--"I shall not interfere with your movements. For
                  all I know, <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName> may be safe as yet. My
                  obvious route will be for the neighbourhood of <placeName type="city"
                     >Delhi</placeName>, where I shall wait for such a concentration of troops as no
                  doubtwill soon take place there for we never can leave that city in the hands of
                  the Sepoys. You can still escort your friends, and I only wish I could spare you a
                  good guard; but a sergeant's party, and that of the smallest, is all I can give
                  you, provided you will return with them to me when you have seen the ladies
                  somewhere in comparative safety."</p>
               <p>"That we will!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>. "My sister, who is the wife of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#fletcher">Major Fletcher</persName>, is
                  anxious to get to <persName type="city">Cawnpore</persName>, where he is
                  stationed; and I fancy we had better all keep together, as we came from <persName
                     type="city">Delhi</persName>, in company." </p>
               <p>"Then here we part, and heaven speed you!" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#majorholmes">Major</roleName>.</p>
               <p>"The same wish follows you, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#majorholmes">Major</persName>, from us! I
                  hope we may meet again in happier times!"</p>
               <p>"Amen!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#majorholmes"
                     >Major</roleName>. "What is it, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#captainharris">Captain
                  Harris</persName>?"</p>
               <p>"We are about to bury the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood"
                     >Colonel</persName>, sir."</p>
               <p>The <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#majorholmes">Major</persName>
                  dismounted. The drums beat a solemn march, and the body of the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#colonelhood">Colonel</persName>, from which
                  the life had not departed half an hour, was laid in a narrow trench the dioneers
                  had dug for it at the foot of a peepul tree. The officers, bareheaded, crowded
                  around the spot. One read the service for the dead. A volley was fired over the
                  grave; and as the echoes died away amid the hollows of the old quarry, all turned
                  sadly from the spot where lay one of the earliest victims of a warfare that was to
                  strike to the earth the bravest and the best of <placeName type="country"
                     >England</placeName>'s sons. </p>
               <p>A sergeant and nine men, with thirty rounds of cartridge each, were placed at the
                  disposal, and under the command, of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>; and
                  then the drums and fifes of the little force struck up a lively march, and they
                  went onwards on the route to <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>; while our
                  friends, sad and tearful, turned their faces to <placeName type="city"
                     >Cawnpore</placeName>,--or rather, in that direction only; for the distance was
                  a long and weary one they had to go.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant Adrian</persName>
                  offered an arm to <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                     Hope</persName>, which she accepted, and the other ladies were helped on as
                  well as they could be by the gentlemen of the party. The three hours' rest they
                  had had--for that time had slipped away--had materially recruited their strength;
                  and although the hot sun came down upon them in force, they resolved to make some
                  progress, if the stage was but a short one. </p>
               <p>Suddenly they started, for a volley of some dozen musket-shots came upon the
                  air.</p>
               <p>"What is that? said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>.</p>
               <p>"Shooting the Sepoy prisoner we took by the guns, please, your honour," said the
                     <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>/</p>
               <p>"Ah, indeed!"</p>
               <p>"Yes, your honour; I heard the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#majorholmes">Major</persName> give the order,
                  when the ladies should be some distance off."</p>
               <p>The <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</persName>
                  looked at <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Adrian</persName>,
                  and the latter shook his head. </p>
               <p>"Two can play at that game, mu friend," he said. "If this affair is to be a war of
                  some direction, and becomes one of what is called energetic measures on one side
                  and reprisals on the other, heaven help <placeName type="country"
                     >India</placeName> and all connected with it!" </p>
               <p>The ladies trembled, and looked sadly at each other, but not a word was spoken for
                  some time; till, overcome by the heat, several of the party showed signs of
                  extreme weariness. The <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>, then, after a salute to
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>, said, "If you please, your honour, here is one of those
                  strange places the natives call rock temples, close at hand, if your honour would
                  command a halt till the cool of the evening."</p>
               <p>"It would be wise. Halt there when you come to it. Cheer up, friends all! we will
                  have a rest soon."</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName> was
                  weeping, and the <roleName>Corporal</roleName> of the guard stepped up to
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>, and bringing his musket to the salute, said, "If you
                  please, may I carry the child on my back. It will be quite comfortable above my
                  knapsack. The poor lady is ready to drop with fatigue."</p>
               <p>"My good fellow, I thank you in her name," said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#captain">Captain</roleName>, as he mentioned
                  the kind offer to <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName>, and persuaded her to accept at onc eof it; so the little
                  one was perched on the top of the <roleName>Corporal</roleName>'s knapsack, and
                  secured by a couple of silk handkerchiefs till they reached the rock temple.</p>
               <p>"Here we are, your honour," said the <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>, as the shadow
                  of a huge, mysterious-looking edifice swept over their route.</p>
               <p>"Halt!" said the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</persName>. "Make your own dispositions,
                  <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>. I suppose the place is untenanted?"</p>
               <p>"We will see to that, sir."</p>
               <p>The <roleName>Sergeant</roleName> and a couple of men entered the </p>
               <pb n="179"/>
               <cb n="1"/>
               <p>temple, and after a few minutes came back to say that it was quite empty, and
                  deliciously cool.</p>
               <p>"And what sort of a building do you call this," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">the Hon. Miss Flint</persName>.
                  "It looks like a cathedral, and I can't think how the savages here could have
                  built up such a place."</p>
               <p>"It is not built," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>, as the little party stood in the shadow of the
                  huge temple. "It is not built, but cut out of the living rock, which you see about
                  it in jagged masses. Its foundations may be deeper in the earth than any building
                  raised by human hands. Delicately sculptured as it is, and with all the
                  appearances of magnificent desihn and structure, the whole is in one piece. The
                  rock is cut away from it, and the temple left. It is one of the wonders of old
                     <placeName type="country">India</placeName>; and the modern race, with their
                  flimsy buildings, so soon destroyed by the peepul tree, which takes root amidst
                  the very stones of which the buildings are composed, and dislocates them to their
                  foundations, are quite incapable of the skill and labour which must have been
                  bestowed upon the old rock
                  temples.<!--should be end quote marks here but there aren't.--></p>
               <p>The party looked with intense interest on this strangely produced pile, which was
                  held together by no human means, and which owed nothing to human art but its mere
                  design, and the elaboration of its ornaments.</p>
               <p>"This is like a statue," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie Hope</persName>, "which, it is fancifully said, the sculptor finds in
                  the interior of a block of marble, his only labour being to chip away the
                  surrounding encasement of stone."</p>

               <p>---</p>
            </div>
            <head>
               <date when="1858-03-27">Saturday, March 27, 1858</date>
            </head>
            <pb n="161"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch14">CHAPTER XIV.</head>
               <p>THE SACRIFICE IN THE ROCK TEMPLE.--AN ALARM.</p>


               <p>THE cool shadow of the rock temple was most welcome to the weary travellers, after
                  the glare of the sun and the stifling heat of the day. They were covered, too,
                  with fine particles of dirt, which produced a choking sensation, so that a draught
                  of water would have been a luxury of price.</p>
               <p>The interior of the <placeName type="building">temple</placeName> consisted, to
                  all appearance, of a vast hall, with a range of columns with rather exaggerated
                  capitals on each side. The roof was of enormous space, but being as it was, cut
                  from the solid rock, its power of sustaining itself was unquestionable. A broad
                  flagging of glat, reddish-looking stones went up the centre of the hall, and in
                  the distance there appeared some deep recesses, that might possibly lead to other
                  halls or apartments of the temple.</p>
               <p>Not a human sound, however, made itself heard in the place, except what they
                  themselves, by their conversation, produced, and that, in the vast space, had a
                  slight and low sound, as though they were conversing in whispers.</p>
               <p>The air was cool and heavy by its contact with the stone surfaces all around, and
                  the ladies gladly availed themselves of a rest which they procured by reclining on
                  such shawls and cloaks as they had with them.</p>
               <p>"If we could but get some water, now," said the <placeName>Lieutenant</placeName>,
                  we might make a refreshing repast with the provisions <persName>Major
                     Holmes</persName> has kindly given us." </p>
               <p>"You may depend," said the <persName>Captain</persName>, "that there is a
                     <placeName type="city">village</placeName> near at hand, and, of course, a
                     <placeName type="building">well</placeName>."</p>
               <p>The little child now began wailing with thirst, and the soldiers were eagerly
                  questioned if they had any water in their canteens, but all were empty. The thirst
                  of the march had offered too many temptations to them to consume all they had.</p>
               <p>The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> then
                  started to his feet, as he said, "I will go on an exploring expedition to the
                  village, in search of water; for I am certain that there must be some close at
                  hand, as there always is where you find these rock temples."</p>
               <p>"Oh, no, no!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName>. "If we lose you what will become of us?"</p>
               <p>"Nay, there cannot be much denager. The Sepoy force that passed through the wood
                  must be far enough off by this time; and you may depend it has collected, in its
                  march, all the fighting stragglers of the district. I will take with me a couple
                  of the men, and do the thing boldly."</p>
               <p>There was an anxious look from face to face of the whole party at this
                  proposition, and then <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#volumina"
                     >Volumina</persName> remarked, "I saw a banian tree a little to the left of
                  this place, and there is very often a well close to it."</p>
               <p>"We can but try," said the <persName>Captain</persName>; "for water we must have,
                  come what may. I want a couple of volunteers with me, my men, in search of
                  water."</p>
               <p>Several of the men immediately rose up, and offered their services, including the
                     <roleName>Corporal</roleName>.</p>
               <p>"I would gladly go with you, sir," said the <roleName>Sergeant</roleName>; "but I
                  think I or you, sir, ought to stay to look after the ladies, even in this quiet
                  place. But if you will let me go instead of you, sir, I daresay we shall find a
                  well."</p>
               <p>"No," said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>; "you stay. I wish to <cb n="2"/>look about me a little, to see what
                  will be our best route. Be quite tranquil, all of you, for I shall soon be back.
                  No, no, my good friend <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                     >Adrian</persName>, don't you dream of coming! I leave you in command, you
                  know, in my absence!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant Adrian</persName>,
                  who had been hurrying after the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, now drew back;
                  and the young officer, with the <roleName>Corporal</roleName>, and a sturdy man
                  from the small guard, issued out from the rock temple.</p>
               <p>The glare of the sun now, after the delicious coolness of the place they had been
                  in, was almost insupportable, but they made their way towards the banian tree,
                  which, although not one of the largest of its class, overshadowed a large track of
                  ground by its pendant branches, which, like huge vegetable stalactites, hung down
                  from the parent stem, and struck root into the soil below, forming each another
                  tree connected with the original one.</p>
               <p>As they neared the tree, an Hindoo woman, darting from among its branches with a
                  cry of alarm, made off at a rate that set pursuit at defiance, notwithstanding all
                  the calling of the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                     >Captain</roleName>, in Hindostanee<!--note-->, to the effect that there was
                  nothing to fear from him or his party.</p>
               <p>"This is unfortunate," he said; "for if there are foes in the vicinity, she will
                  give an alarm."</p>
               <p>"Well, sir," said the <roleName>Corporal</roleName>, "at all events, here is a
                     <placeName type="building">well</placeName>, and here a good-sized native
                  earthen pitcher, which no doubt the woman has left behind in her fright."</p>
               <p>Shaded by some slim trees, that looked dwarfs by the side of the gigantic banian,
                  was a native well, and close to its banks, and earthen vessel lying on its side
                  with water slowly trickling from its narrow neck. </p>
               <p>"This is a prize, indeed!" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, as he seized
                  the rough native cords, made of the twisted fibre of a tree, by which the vessel
                  was let down into the well, and hastily filled it.</p>
               <p>A delicious draught to each of the party was their first act, and then, with a
                  flush of something like shame at the selfishness of staying to drink at the
                     <placeName type="building">well</placeName>, while his friends in the rock
                  temple were being parched with thirst, the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> cast the vessel
                  again into the <placeName type="building">well</placeName>, and brought it out
                  full.</p>
               <p>"Let us get back," he said, "at once. Who will carry this?"</p>
               <p>"I, sir," said the soldier.</p>
               <p>Even as the man spoke, he uttered a sharp cry of pain, as though it had been a
                  continuation of the last word he had uttered, and he fell writhing to the
                  ground.</p>
               <p>"What is it?--what is it?" cried <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>, as he
                  hastily flung down the earthen pitcher on the soft grass, and drew his sword.</p>
               <p>Sobs and gasping groans came from the solider, as the
                     <roleName>Corporal</roleName> helped him to a sitting posture, and then they
                  saw that a long arrow had entered his chest, and literally protruded some six
                  inches from his back.</p>
               <p>"Bring him along!" cried the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>. "I will help you. We shall be made targets of here. This
                  is from the villagers. The Sepoys are differently armed. On, on!"</p>
               <p>With a whistling sound another arrow now made its way past the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>'s head, in much
                  too close proximity to be at all pleasant. The <roleName>Corporal</roleName>
                  dropped the head of his comrade, and snatched up his musket, as he cried, "I have
                  him, sir!"</p>
               <p>Crack went the shot! A yell of pain and rage succeeded it; and tumbling from
                  branch to branch of the banian tree, came an old, villainous-looking <foreign
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#ryot">ryot</foreign>, with some half-dozen
                  arrows in his girdle-cloth and a bow in his hand. He fell directly on his head,
                  and then rolled over, yelling and cursing in choice Hindostanee, no doubt.</p>
               <p>"Hold your row~" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Corporal</roleName>, as he gave him a crack on the side of the head with the
                  brass-mounted butt of his musket, which apparently settled the affair, for the
                  Hindoo, with a gasp, shot out his limbs convulsively, and then lay quite
                  still.</p>
               <p>"Away! away!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>. "The shot may give an alarm. He is dead, I suppose?"</p>
               <p>"I rather think so, sir. But the water?"</p>
               <p>"I will carry that if you think you can help your wounded comrade." </p>
               <p>"All right, sir; I can carry him that short way, I think. Come, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hopkins">Hopkins</persName>, old fellow, how
                  are you now?" </p>
               <p>A gurgling sound came from <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hopkins"
                     >Hopkins</persName>'s throat, and the <roleName>Corporal</roleName> then, with
                  the best intention in the world, laid hold of the arrow and with one wrench pulled
                  it from the wound. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hopkins"
                     >Hopkins</persName> uttered a piercing scream, and fell back dead.</p>
               <p>"Poor fellow!" said the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</persName>. "This is sad; but I don't like leaving even his body
                  here."</p>
               <p>"His cartridges, sir!" said the <roleName>Corporal</roleName>. "They can't hurt
                  the body, if you please, sir."</p>
               <p>Hardly had the <roleName>Corporal</roleName> emptied the cartridge-box of the dead
                  soldier and taken his musket, when the dull heavy sound of an Indian drum came
                  upon their ears. They felt certain that an alarm was spreading; so just dragging
                  the body of poor <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hopkins"
                     >Hopkins</persName> under one of the <cb n="3"/>trees, the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, with the
                  earthen vessel of water, which had cost a life in the getting, and the
                     <roleName>Corporal</roleName> with the two muskets, sat off at a trot for the
                  rock temple again.</p>
               <p>There was a slight rise in the portion of ground to be traversed in their route,
                  and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> there paused a moment to reconnoitre.</p>
               <p>"Ah!" he exclaimed; "we are only in time."</p>
               <p>"For what, sir?"</p>
               <p>"For shelter. There is a party approaching; but I think they are only villagers.
                  Do you think we can hold the temple against them,
                  <roleName>Corporal</roleName>?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, yes, sir--against a thousand of that sort. But it will be a blockade, sir;
                  that's the worst of it."</p>
               <p>"We cannot help it at the present moment. On! on!"</p>
               <p>They made the best of their way, and reached the <placeName>rock
                     temple</placeName>, heated, to be sure, but still in good time to make such
                  defensive preparations as might be required. The whole of the soldiers were posted
                  at its entrance, in order to make as imposing a display of force as possible; and
                  hardly had this been done when, with shouts and cries, a rabble rout of villagers,
                  and escaped thieves from <placeName type="city">Agra</placeName> and <placeName
                     type="city">Delhi</placeName>, made a rush towards the place.</p>
               <p>"Give it to them, my men," said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>. "Fire!" </p>
               <p>The volley was not a very extensive one, but the sight of the European uniforms,
                  blocking, as it appeared, completely the entrance of the temple, gave the
                  attacking party such a surprise, that they rolled one over the other in their
                  frantic attempts to escape, and left four lying dead on the field.</p>
               <p>"That will do, I think!" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>. "They won't
                  court our acquaintance any more."</p>
               <p>The firing reverberated through the old temple, and the alarm of the ladies was
                  great for the moment; but <persName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName> soon explained the whole affair, and presented the
                  welcome refreshment of the pitcher of water, which, by the aid of one of the
                  soldier's little tin cups, was handed round and partaken of with more delight than
                  if it had been the choicest nectar.</p>
               <p>"De-licious!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>, as he drew a long breath after his draught. "Would you like
                  some more, <persName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#missflint">Miss
                     Flint</persName>?"</p>
               <p>"If you please. Oh, dear! oh, dear! that ever I should have come to this pass, to
                  be thankful for a drop of water! I, who have had such offers! Murder, murder!"</p>
               <p>"Good heavens! what's the matter?"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#missflint">The Hon. Miss
                     Flint</persName> was draining the cup, when her eyes, running along the side of
                  it, fell to the further end of the hall, and she saw emerge from one of the dark
                  recesses there a tall figure, with a robe of greyish cloth, and a long beard. Only
                  for a moment did the figure glare at the strangers, and then rapidly
                  disappeared.</p>
               <p>"Oh, come away!--come away!" at once cried <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName>. "I cannot
                  possibly stay here! There is a <distinct corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#brahmin"
                     >Brahmin</distinct>, or a Sepoy, or--what do you call them?--a <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#thug">Thug</distinct>, or something of that
                  sort, in the place."</p>
               <p>"Hush! hush! you frighten the child!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>, who saw
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>'s
                  little one clinging to her in alarm, and with difficulty pacified.</p>
               <p>"Not I!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#missflint">Miss
                     Flint</persName>. "But the child saw the wretch, no doubt, as well as I
                  did--right away there in that dark corner."</p>
               <p>"Come with me, <roleName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian"
                     >Sergeant</roleName>," said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>. "You, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian">Adrian</persName>, keep a good guard
                  at the entrance to this place."</p>
               <p>The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian">Sergeant</roleName> and
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>
                  advanced up the whole length of the hall to the dark-looking recess at the further
                  end of it, and then the latter said, "This passage may lead to some other chamber
                  of the temple, and as our stay here will be until the dusk of the evening, it is
                  better that we explore it. Follow me close, but don't use your sword till you see
                  daylight, which I fancy we soon shall!"</p>
               <p>It seemed rather a hazardous thing to plunge into that dark passage, but the young
                  officer, with his drawn sword, did not for a moment hesitate, and making sure by
                  the <!--r-->evolutions of the weapon that he cleared the passage before him, and
                  must wound any one who was in his way, he passed on.</p>
               <p>The ground was of loose pieces of rock, as if left by the very chisels of the
                  workmen, who some thousands of years before had dug out that route from the living
                  stone; but no obstacle presented itself for some time, until <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> suddenly
                  paused upon hearing a strange, low, hissing sound.</p>
               <p>Now, the young officer had lived long enough in <placeName type="country"
                     >India</placeName> to suspect what that meant, and he drew back with all the
                  undefined horror which an European feels for any of the snake or serpent tribe,
                  the peculiar hiss of wihch seemed to come unmistakably from that dark recess in
                  the old temple.</p>
               <p>"Do you hear that?" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>.</p>
               <p>"Indeed I do, sir!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian"
                     >Sergeant</roleName>. "Mercy upon us! something is touching my legs, sir!"</p>
               <p>"Rush on! rush on!" cried the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>. "I see, some faint light! This way! follow me!"</p>
               <p>The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian">Sergeant</roleName> made a
                  dash forward after the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>, <pb n="180"/><cb n="1"/>and they reached a spot where, from a sort of crevice,
                  high in the roof, there came down light sufficient for them to see each other
                  quite plainly.</p>
               <p>No snake or serpent was visible, but the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian">Sergeant</roleName> wiped the heavy
                  perspiration from his brow, as he said, "It had hold of me, your honour!"</p>
               <p>"Are you sure?"</p>
               <p>"Quite! And your honour heard the creature hiss!"</p>
               <p>"I did! I did! Ah! stand still!"</p>
               <p>"Oh, Lord!"</p>
               <p>The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian">Sergeant</roleName> got as
                  far from the wall as he could, and then they both saw, gliding along the side of
                  the passage, a lustrous-looking snake of immense size. Every moment it darted out
                  its forked tongue with a strange hissing sound, and now and then it inclined its
                  head toward the intruders, threateningly; and yet it glided on as though it would
                  say, "You leave me alone, and I won't interfere with you!"</p>
               <p>There is ever something awful and repulsive about the long, lithe movement of a
                  snake; and truly, if ever there were one of nature's productions against which it
                  may be said the ands of all men are naturally raised, it is a snake.</p>
               <p>"Cut it down!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>. "Don't let the beast go!"</p>
               <p>He made a slash at the snake as he spoke with his sword, and the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian">Sergeant</roleName> made another. The
                  creature, with its strange cunning, seemed to see that it was a battle of life or
                  death, and detaching itself from the side of the wall with a fearful contortion of
                  all its body, it might be said to almost fly at the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian">Sergeant</roleName>.</p>
               <p>The desperation with which that individual brandished his musket, showed his
                  abhorrence of it; but it flung a coil of its wounded body around him, and the
                  hideous head ran up its breast, and he fancied he felt the hot breath of the
                  reptile on his face.</p>
               <p>It was not in human nature to forbear a cry of alarm and horror, and unmistakably
                  brave as the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian"
                     >Sergeant</roleName> was, he uttered such a cry as he added, "Cut it down, cut
                  it down! It is too close to me! I cannot use my sword!"</p>
               <p>There was a risk of wounding the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian">Sergeant</roleName>, but the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, by a lively
                  stroke, struck the snake at the back of the head, nearly separating it from the
                  body, and the hideous thing dropped in the convulsions of death to the floor.</p>
               <p>"I would rather face a battery," said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian">Sergeant</roleName>, "than I would
                  have that reptile coiled about me again!"</p>
               <p>"It is dead!" replied the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>.</p>
               <p>"Thank heaven, yes!" Hush! do you hear nothing, sir?"</p>
               <p>The both listened intently, and a low, murmuring noise, as if some persons were
                  speaking in a strange chanting tone, came faintly upon their ears. It seemed to
                  come through the very thickness of the wall, and the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> beckoned the
                     <roleName corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian">Sergeant</roleName> on for
                  about twenty paces, when there was a sudden opening to the right, leaving a kind
                  of breastwork of the rock, about five feet in height, but over which, and along an
                  arched passage of not more than six feet in length, they saw into a strange
                  cavernous place, in which a most curious scene to those unversed in the strange
                  mysteries of Hindoo mythology was taking place.</p>
               <p>With a couple of torches before, it, lighting up its hideous and
                  diabolical-looking proportions and accessories, was a Hindoo idol, with three
                  faces and four arms, squatted upon what looked like a monster rat. Bangles and
                  bracelets, and huge pendant ear-rings, hung about the idol, and its faces and feet
                  were smeared with blood.</p>
               <p>Prostrate before this essence of ugliness and profanity were some Hindoos, and a
                  couple of priests were chanting a sort of prayer as they stood upon two stools
                  close to the idol.</p>
               <p>Beyond the devotees who were grovelling on the floor, was an open archway, through
                  which could be seen the fair and beautiful country.</p>
               <p>"Lord, your honour!" whispered the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian">Sergeant</roleName>, "what is all
                  that?"</p>
               <p>"Hush, hush!"</p>
               <p>As they looked now intently on what was going on, they saw the hidepous head of a
                  snake, somewhat similar to the one they had killed in the passage, slowly emerge
                  over the neck of the idol. One of the Brahmins then took from his girdle a small
                  reed flute, on which he blew a strange wild jumble of noes, that could hardly be
                  called a tune, although there was a certain cadence in it to which the snake moved
                  its head with great exactness.</p>
               <p>The devotees then rolled over and over, and uttered short cries and yells, calling
                  upon the idol by some name the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> could not
                  catch.</p>
               <p>"They are worshipping Old Nick, sir, I do think!" whispered the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#adrian">Sergeant</roleName>.</p>
               <p>"It looks like it! Speak low!"</p>
               <p>"Yes, sir! They are worse than the <orgName>Turks</orgName> ten
                  times over, your honour, for they don't have any idols!"</p>
               <p/>
               <p>
                  <emph>(To be continued in our next)</emph>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
