<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model hcorresp="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!--<?xml-model hcorresp="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<!--
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/xsl" href="../xsl/rymer.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/css" href="../style.css" alternate="yes"?>
-->


<?xml-model href="../schema/sepoys.schema.xml" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Sepoys; Or, Highland Jessie: an electronic edition</title>
            <author>James Malcolm Rymer</author>
            <author>
               <persName type="pseudo">M. J. Errym</persName>
            </author>
            <editor>Rebecca Nesvet</editor>
            <editor>Rae X. Yan</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Rebecca Nesvet</publisher>
            <publisher>Rae X. Yan</publisher>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <idno>sepoys</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct xml:id="installment6" prev="sepoys.3.13.xml#installment5"
               next="sepoys.3.27.xml#installment7">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter XI: The Attack in the Quarry--The Separation</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-03-20"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter XII: The Conflagration, and the Rescue</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-03-20"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <!-- Information about the encoding of the text -->
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Information about the project itself (goals, organization, activities)</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Information about how the texts in a collection were chosen or excerpted</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="unknown">
               <p>Information about treatment of errors in the source (silently corrected, etc.)</p>
            </correction>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Information about normalization practices (e.g. treatment of roman numerals,
                  spelling, etc.)</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation form="std">
               <p>Information about treatment of quotations (preservation of original quotation
                  marks, etc.)</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="hard">
               <p>Treatment of the hyphenation of the source</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Information about whether and how the text has been segmented (mostly for
                  linguistic purposes)</p>
            </segmentation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Information about any interpretive information added to the text</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="installment">
            <head>
               <date when="1858-03-20">Saturday, March 20, 1858</date>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="../facsimiles/sepoys.3.20.png"/>
            </figure>
            <pb n="161"/>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch11">CHAPTER XI.</head>
               <p>THE ATTACK IN THE <placeName type="building">QUARRY</placeName>--THE
                  SEPARATION</p>

               <p>The yell of exultation of the Hindoo, and his cry of agony, as he fell from
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar's</persName> shot,
                  were so nearly identical, and followed so closely the one upon the other, that it
                  was difficult to separate them, or to say which was which.</p>

               <p>For a few moments the little party stood irresolute how to act, and it was not
                  until <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>
                  himself spoke that they started into action again.</p>

               <p>"One nigger the less, at all events," said the young man, coolly. "I say,
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal</persName>, I do
                  believe it is the rascal we spared before?"</p>

               <p>"I hope so!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>. "But the shot may give an alarm, and secrecy is our only
                  chance. Follow me, all of you! It was a good shot, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>!"</p>

               <p>"Well, I fancy it stopped his howling! Don't you think it would be as well to get
                  the body out of sight, in order to stop any rascals who may pass from fancying
                  anything has taken place down here?"</p>

               <p>"Yes, if there were time! Stoop, all of you, stoop! Lower, if you can--lower
                  still!"</p>

               <p>"What is it?" whispered every one very eagerly, as they instinctively obeyed the
                  order.</p>

               <p>"There are Sepoys on the ridge!</p>

               <p>It so happened that the party were so far down the rude path that led down the
                  side of the <placeName type="building">quarry</placeName>, that they had got
                  fairly among the rank vegetation, which, when they thus found themselves enveloped
                  by it, was to their satisfaction not to dense, bu much higher, than it had looked
                  when viewed from above.</p>
               <cb n="2"/>

               <p>The variety of colours, too, of the leaves, the flowers, the fruits, and the
                  berries, prevented the likelihood of their being seen, provided they kept
                  still.</p>

               <p>"Do not move, hand or foot!" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, in a cautious
                  whisper, "or we are lost!"</p>

               <p>They scarcely seemed now to breathe, so still were they ; and so pure was the
                  morning air, and such an absence now of all disturbing sounds, that they heard the
                  Sepoys plainly conversing on the ridge. </p>

               <p>"Where are the accursed race?" said one. </p>

               <p>"The information was good!" said another. "Where is our friend, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hooderali">Hooder Ali</persName>? </p>

               <p>"Hark!" said a third, "our lord approaches! Death to all whom he shall meet! The
                  blood of the vile <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName> shall yet sink
                  into the soil!" </p>

               <p>The clangour of some rude musical instruments now again sounded, and the crouching
                  fugitives heard that peculiar heavy tread on the earth, which betokens the
                  presence of elephants. They had no doubt, now, but that the process, or the party,
                  was that of some of of the petty princes, or satraps, who had taken advantage of
                  the revolt to assume extra airs of independence and power, and that he would seek
                  to consolidate such notions, by the indiscriminate murder of all Europeans whom he
                  might come across.</p>

               <p> "There are elephants!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>. "I see them, with their gay <foreign xml:lang="hi"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#howdahs">howdahs</foreign>. Keep still till I
                  tell you to creep lower down, which probably we can do directly!"</p>

               <p>The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> was
                  right; for the Sepoys on the ridge turned to do homage to their great man, and
                  then no prying eyes were bent into the hollow. </p>

               <p>"Forward!" whispered the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName> ; but still stoop as you go, all of you! There is no safety
                  yet from the stray glances of some one above!" </p>

               <p>They were all glad to obey the order to move on, for the stooping posture, on the
                  steep declivity, was harassing ; so they followed the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> willingly
                  enough, until one of the lower depths of the <placeName type="building"
                     >quarry</placeName> was reached: we say, one of them, because there were
                  several sorts of plateaux at different depths, where the old workings had
                  extended, in looking either for different sorts of stone, or some of different
                  degrees of hardness, which are frequently found in close contact to each
                  other.</p>

               <p>The place on which they stood now was in extent about seventy feet in one
                  direction, by some twenty-five in another, and was irregularly set up by huge
                  blocks, from which sprouted, embedded in crevices, various Indian creepers; and,
                  in fact, the place was one of romantic beauty, with the side of the actual
                     <placeName type="building">quarry</placeName> overhanging it, and casting a
                  cool shadow on to it.</p>

               <p>Suddenly there was a rustling in the neighbourhood, and a young antelope, with
                  several bounds of amazing length, sped up the side of the hollow, and disappeared
                  in the woods. Some gorgeous butterflies hovered over the spot, and a thin speckled
                  snake glided, like a thread of silver, away among the rank Indian grass.</p>

               <p>"Is there rest and safety here for all?" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshope">Mrs. Hope</persName>, faintly.</p>

               <p>""Yes--yes, dear mother, cheer up!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>.</p>

               <p>"Is it not, as yet, heaven's mercy, that we are all together?"</p>

               <p>"It is--it is, my dear children!"</p>

               <p>Clash came something down among the trailing plants, with a strange sound. Clash
                  again and again came the same singular noise, and yet nothing was seen, until
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> said,
                  rather louder than caution would have dictated, "Why, they are arrows! Some one is
                  shooting down here at a venture!"</p>

               <p>Several exclamations of alarm came from the ladies, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> added, as an arrow,
                  which made itself unmistakably apparent by being shivered by the force of its
                  descent on a piece of rock close to him, narrowly avoided <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#volumina">Volumina</persName>,--"By Jove! we
                  shall be hit, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Hannibal</persName>!" </p>

               <p>"This way, this way, cried the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>. "Here is
                  shelter. Quick! quick! follow me!"</p>

               <p>They sprang after him like a troop of frightened deer; and, to their great joy,
                  they saw that the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName> had found one of tose very chambers, or inner workings, of
                  the quarry he had spoken of. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">The Hon. Miss <pb n="162"/><cb
                        n="1"/>Flint</persName> was the last in shelter, owing to stooping to pick
                  up a small bag with toilette requisites she had brought with her from <placeName
                     type="city">Delhi</placeName>, and now let drop in her hurry. As she laid her
                  hands upon it to lift it from the grass, an arrow struck it just within a couple
                  of inches of her head as she stooped.</p>

               <p>With a scream, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">the Hon.
                     Miss Flint</persName> abandoned the bag, and rushed after the party. </p>

               <p>"Good heavens! who cried out in that way?" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>. "It is
                  enough to bring destruction on us all!" </p>

               <p>"My bag!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">the Hon.
                     Miss Flint</persName>
               </p>

               <p>"Your what, Madam?"</p>

               <p>"My bag, sir! If it's all the same to you, sir--if you please, sir! And I beg to
                  say, sir, that--" </p>

               <p>"Now, now--really," interposed <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>,--"don't, my dear <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName>--don't go on
                  so, and I will make you an offer."</p>

               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName>
                  nearly screamed again as she said, "A what? An offer! Oh, sir!--oh, Mr. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar
                  Hawkins</persName>--I--really--indeed, I--" </p>

               <p>"Yes," interrupted <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>; "an offer, with all my heart, to try and pull in the bag
                  with a long stick, if I had one." </p>

               <p>"Wretch!" </p>

               <p>"Did you speak, ma'am?"</p>

               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName> sat
                  down and squeezed two tears from each eye, then blew her honourable nose, and was
                  silent. No doubt she registered it as another instance of the fickleness and
                  anti-marrying propensities of man, as there was an "offer" in a <placeName
                     type="building">stone quarry</placeName> which went off into nothing.</p>

               <p>It was quite clear now that, whether from some suspicion that the fugitives were
                  really concealed in the quarry, or for the purpose of starting any game that might
                  make it their covert, the Sepoys in the road were sending arrows, by shooting them
                  up into the air first, point downwards, among the rank vegetation of the place,
                  for they continued to come on to the plateau, and to sometimes be lost to sight
                  among the plants and flowers, and at others to lie close to the chamber where the
                  party found a refuge. </p>

               <p>The entrance to this inner working of the <placeName type="building"
                     >quarry</placeName> was not above ten feet in height, and about--if it had been
                  clear, which it was not--four feet in width. The opening, however, was rendered
                  rather difficult of access by a huge block, of many tons in weight, of stone
                  having fallen from somewhere above and split into two, close to what may be called
                  the doorway. </p>

               <p>Within the chamber, it widened out into a sort of cavern, which was deliciously
                  cool and fragrant; and from the further end of it--that is to say, about forty
                  feet from the entrance--branched off a narrow passage, which none of the party had
                  either time or inclination to explore.</p>

               <p>And now <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshope">Mrs. Hope</persName>
                  was compelled to lie down and declare that she had made all the efforts she could;
                  nor was <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshawkins">Mrs.
                     Hawkins</persName> in a much better situation. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant Adrian</persName>, too,
                  who, considering his recent wounds, had taken by far too much exertion, felt weak
                  and exhausted. He spoke faintly. </p>

               <p>"My dear fellow--<persName corresp="sepoys.persponography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Hawkins</persName>--you must make a garrison of this place while you can, for
                  I fancy you have sick and wounded on your hands." </p>

               <p>"I will do my best, you may depend. How thickly the arrows still fall!" </p>

               <p>"They do, indeed!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.perspography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>. "But they can't hurt us." </p>

               <p>"There is one great danger, though!" </p>

               <p>"What is that?"</p>

               <p>"Why, they will be sure to come down to collect them. They won't lose them, you
                  may depend. We shall have some of the rascals down here soon, when they find they
                  start no game; for I fancy, after all, that must be what they are after." </p>

               <p>"Confound them!"</p>

               <p>"Amen!"</p>

               <p>The childish and half silly-like laughter of the <orgName type="indian"
                     >Hindoos</orgName>, when they fancy they are enjoying any sport, now came upon
                  the ears of the party ; and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>, motioning with his hand for all to keep quiet,
                  himself and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>
                  carefully reconnoitred from the mouth of the opening, sheltered by the mass of
                  rock before it.</p>

               <p>"They come, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                  >Caesar</persName>!" he said. </p>

               <p>"By Jove!--yes, I see the rascals!"</p>

               <p>On the edge of the quarry, at the same place by which our party had descended, and
                  which was, no doubt, well known as a practicable mode of descent by the Sepoys,
                  there now appeared a group of about fourteen or fifteen of them gazing into the
                  quarry.</p>

               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal</persName>!
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal</persName>!"
                  said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>.</p>

               <p>"What? oh, what?"</p>

               <p>"That bag--<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss
                     Flint</persName>'s bag! It will betray us!" </p>

               <p>"Ah!" </p>
               <cb n="2"/>

               <p>"Stop where you are! I'll get it in! Too late, by Jove!" </p>

               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> just shrunk
                  back in time, as a couple of Sepoys alighted with a bound on to the plateau. </p>

               <p>"Step back a pace or two, and say 'hush!'" whispered the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Captain</persName>. </p>

               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> did so; and
                  then those in the cavernous recess understood that there was great danger without;
                  and all sounds were still, altjough it was with the greatest difficulty that
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>
                  could, at this precise moment, still a whimpering kind of half cry which the child
                  had commenced.</p>

               <p>The Sepoys paused, and looked at each other irresolutely. A sort of suspicion
                  seemed to be upon their minds that all was not quite right about the spot; but
                  yet, as they did not immediately see the bag, they had nothing particular to go
                  upon. Two more joined them, and they, together with others in different parts of
                  the quarry, kept up a yelling kind of noise, like so many savages, as, in truth,
                  they were but little removed from being. Suddenly, then, as they hastily piecked
                  up the arrows, one saw the unfortunate bag, and he held it aloft, as he cried,
                  "The <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>! The <orgName
                     xml:lang="ur" type="european" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee"
                     >Feringhee</orgName>!</p>

               <p>With a shout of exultation, the others crowded about him, and the bag was turned
                  out of its contents in a moment. Combs, brushes, a hand-mirror, and all the little
                  aids and additions in the toilette of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName>, were
                  ruthlessly disposed of by the Sepoys in a moment. </p>

               <p>Then an officer approahced, and they <foreign xml:lang="ar"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#salaamed">salaamed</foreign> low. </p>

               <p>"What is this?" he said. </p>

               <p>"The accursed race have been here," said one of the Sepoys, "and left this empty
                  bag!" </p>

               <p>"Empty?" </p>

               <p>"Even as my <roleName type="military">Captain Sahib</roleName> sees it! </p>

               <p>"Been here, say you? Why not here still?"</p>

               <p>The officer, as he spoke, turned slowly round on his heels, with <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName>'s bag in his
                  hand, and looked narrowly all around him. The Sepoys watched hisgaze with
                  interest, for he was one of those acute, cunning minds, that, by the exercise of
                  that faculty, soon acquite a character for wisdom with the herd. He was a
                  Mahomedan; and, as a covert smile played upon his swarthy features, he muttered,
                  "By the beard of <roleName type="honorofic"
                     corresp="sepoys.personograpy.xml#muhammad">the Prophet</roleName>! They have
                  been here!" </p>

               <p>As he stood, the ponderous stone that had fallen before the mouth of the chamber
                  in the rock, entirely hid it from his view. Had he moved aside two paces, he must
                  have seen the opening. After a few moments' thought, he said, "One stay here on
                  guard! I will post others about the place! I suspect--I suspect! I will have them
                  out, by fire or by the sword! I will return soon! Be wary! The fugitives from the
                  city of cities cover the land! The faithful must have breath, and they will not
                  have it while the infidel lives!" </p>

               <p>He pointed to the one who was to remain on guard, and then started off, followed
                  by the others. </p>

               <p>"What on earth is he going to be at?" whispered <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> to his brother. </p>

               <p>"I cannot guess!" </p>

               <p>At this moment a shout from above heralded some discovery; and the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> added, "They
                  have just seen the body of the fellow you shot, you may depend, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>!"</p>

               <p>"I shouldn't wonder! Did you see how they pocketed <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Miss Flint</persName>'s toilette?" </p>

               <p>"I did, indeed! Hush! Watch this fellow!" </p>

               <p>The Sepoy on guard did not by any means seem at his ease. The mysterious airs
                  assumed by his officer made him suspect that his post was not the safest one in
                  the world; and as Sepoys are never very valorous when alone, this one looked as if
                  he would very much rather have been somewhere else. The first thing he did was to
                  imitate the movement round on his heels, which the officer had made; and then he
                  said, "Ha!" After that he squatted down on his heels and hams, and took something
                  from a dirty rag tied round his arm, and began to chew it. Then he seemed to catch
                  an idea that there might, in human possibility, be a<!--sic--> something behind
                  the large piece of rock; and he fixed a gaze very suspiciously upon it, his eyes
                  opening wider and wider as he did so. </p>

               <p>All this time both the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName> and his brother kept him well in sight, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> whispered, "That
                  fellow is getting dangerous!" </p>

               <p>"How?"</p>

               <p>"He will come here--I will give long odds on it!" </p>

               <p>"Keep still!" </p>

               <p>"Yes--but--" </p>

               <p>"See--see!--he comes! Leave me to deal with him, for heaven's sake!" </p>

               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> shrunk back,
                  and the Sepoy rose to his feet, and approached the rock with a lounging gait: he
                  was armed with the clumsy-looking <foreign corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#tulwar"
                     >tulwar</foreign>, or sword, of the natives; but in a sash, round his waist,
                  were stuck a pair of handsome European pistols. He had on an uniform coat of one
                  of the revolted regiments; but the peculiarly English pantaloons he had abandoned
                     <cb n="2"/>for the looser wrappings, about the lower limbs, adopted by the
                  natives.</p>

               <p>Now, as the cleft stone before the mouth of the opening in the rock was placed by
                  accident, the Sepoy had his choice of three modes of approaching the place. He
                  could pass through the huge fissure in the rock, or he could go to either side of
                  it: as it chanced, he went to the right of it; and, as he did so, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> gently
                  slid away to the left.</p>

               <p>"Ah!" said the Sepoy, when he saw the opening in the side of the <placeName
                     type="building">quarry</placeName>. </p>

               <p>Slowly, then he advanced another step or two, and tried to look in; but he had
                  come out of the full glare of the open daylight, and it was not so easy to see at
                  once from light to darkness for about forty eet, and the party, in the cavernous
                  place, had got to the further end of it. Of course, they saw him quite plainly. </p>

               <p>Then, as if a happy idea had struck him, the Sepoy gave a grunt, and drew one of
                  his pistols. </p>

               <p>They all heard the click of the lock as he prepared it for action, and then they
                  saw a swift shadow glide behind him. It was the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, who with one
                  well-directed blow with his fist, behind the ear, sent the Sepoy down, as if he
                  had been struck by a flash of lightning.</p>

               <p>"Bravo!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>. "That was neat, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hanniball</persName>, by Jove!"</p>

               <p>"The silentest way was the best!" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, as he quickly
                  disarmed the Sepoy. "Have you anything to tie his hands and ankles with, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>--or any of you?" </p>

               <p>"Here you are!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>. "Here is a good bit of cord, but it strikes me he won't
                  move in a hurry. That blow is too composing, just in that spot!" </p>

               <p>"I hope so!" </p>

               <p>As a measure of precaution, however, they tied the hands and feet of the Sepoy and
                  dragged him far into the cavern; and hardly had they done so, when they heard
                  confused cries, and the crashing sound, among the brushwood, of the descent of a
                  large party into the quarry.</p>

               <p>"We shall have to stand a siege," said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>; "see that all
                  the fire-arms are in order, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>! We may hold out until some succour comes. At all events, we
                  have but one motto, after what we saw in <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>,
                  and that is--" </p>

               <p>"No surrender!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>. </p>

               <p>"Just so! Here they are! You get on one side, and I on the other, and we can fire,
                  crosswise, over the mouth of the place: make all the rest of the party go into the
                  narrow passage at the end. There, no stray shot can possibly reach them. If our
                  ammunition hold out, we can keep this post perhaps till the Sepoys are sick of
                  us!" </p>

               <p>"To be sure!" </p>

               <p>"I am with you, too!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                     >Lieutenant Adrian</persName>. </p>

               <p>"All right--stay close to me!" </p>

               <p>"And I, too, my boys!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon"
                     >Mr. Hawkins.</persName>
               </p>

               <p>"Oh, father!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>, "you may do us all such a lot of good, by loading the spare
                  guns as fast as we want them. I know you can do that well. And now, I think, we
                  have made our dispositions capitally! What do you say, <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant</roleName>? Why, where is
                  he?"</p>

               <p>"Here!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                  >Adrian</persName>. "I only want to tell the ladies--that is, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>--I mean the
                  ladies--that I--that is, that we would die in their defence!"</p>

               <p>"Humph!" laughed <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>; "we had better live in it. But all's right, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Adrian</persName>; and come what may,
                  you have my good word! </p>

               <p>"And mine!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Hannibal</persName>.</p>

               <p>"Why--why, what mean you?" </p>

               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, you know!"
                  said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> "Lord
                  bless you! isn't it quite plain to everybody that you love the girl!" </p>

               <p>"Eh?--what?" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr.
                     Hawkins</persName>
               </p>

               <p>"Silence, on your lives!" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>. "They are upon
                  us!" </p>

               <p>By some means or another, the Sepoys seemed now to know exactly the situation of
                  the recess in the side of the quarry, and several rushed to the mouth of it, with
                  muskets in their hands, and their <foregin corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#tulwar"
                     >tulwars</foregin> held in their teeth. </p>

               <p>"Death to the dogs! Death!--death!" </p>

               <p>Two levelled their muskets, and were on the point of firing into the cavern, when
                  one in authority cried out, "Hold! a torch, here! We want prisoners for the
                  amusement of our <foreign xml:lang="pe" type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#padisha">Padisha</foreign>! A torch, here!</p>

               <p>A flaring flambeau was brought, and a crowd of eager faces peered into the recess,
                  while one held forward the blazing torch as far as he could. </p>

               <p>There was just a possible chance, placed as the party was, that they might be
                  overlooked, for the sides of the cavernous opening were very irregular, and the
                  four persons near to its opening stood close to the rock. But suddenly the rays of
                  the torch flashed on the body of the Sepoy who had been so scientifically struck
                  down by the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>, and then there was a shout of exultation. </p>

               <p>Now, it was not at all the intention of the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName><pb n="163"/><cb
                     n="1"/> to let the enemy into his fortress. If discovered, he intended to try
                  to hold it; and now, when he saw that they would surely come in unless prevented,
                  he cried out, in a loud and shrill voice that astonished the Sepoys, "Fire!" </p>

               <p>He, and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>, and
                  the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant</roleName>
                  fired at once, and three of the Sepoys fell, including the one with the torch and
                  the officer. The others retreated in dismay, tumbling one over the other in their
                  hurry to get away. </p>

               <p>"That will do," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>.</p>

               <p>"For the present--yes," said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>; "and the siege
                  has now fairly begun." </p>

               <p>The Sepoys now raised loud yells of rage, and bang, bang, began a regular
                  fusillade from the <placeName type="building">quarry</placeName>. The bullets kept
                  hitting the rock and the side of the opening, and cracking off splinters from the
                  stone; while now and then one found its way into the cavern by accident, or by
                  glancing off from the rock in front, and so having its direction altered. </p>

               <p>The situation of the party began to be perilous in the extreme. </p>

               <p>"I say, by Jove!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>, "what is to be the end of all this, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal</persName>?" </p>

               <p>"I don't know; but we must hold out." </p>

               <p>"Yes, but how about the provisions? Why, we have not, among us all, above famish
                  rations for a couple of days, I fancy." </p>

               <p>"Heaven help us!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr.
                     Hawkins</persName>. </p>

               <p>Crack, crack, kept coming in the bullets from the fire-arms of the Sepoys; and it
                  was quite evident that any attempt to leave the place of refuge they were now in
                  would be to encounter instant death. In fact, the only thing to do, or to think
                  of, at the moment, was just the self-preservation of the time passing. What the
                  next day, or the next after that, was to produce, too sorely tried the imagination
                  to encompass.</p>

               <p>It was quite clear that the Sepoys would not venture upon another attack of the
                  party at anything like close quarters. The certainty of the instant destruction of
                  some of them, and the uncertainty as to which of them that might be, kept the
                  whole force back; but still it was hardly to be supposed that the ingenuity of the
                  foe would not suffice to devise some scheme by which to carry on offensive
                  operations in a more tangible way than by merely keeping up a sensless fusillade
                  upon the rocks.</p>

               <p>"There," said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>, "you see they are getting tired of all this firing with no
                  result, and we shall only have a stray shot or two now. They will try some other
                  dodge, you may depend."</p>

               <p>"Well," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                  >Caesar</persName>, "I only wish there were more of us, and then we could dash out
                  and give them a drubbing. What's this now coming? Look out!" </p>

               <p>From the further end of the little plateau there now appeared approaching, with
                  his musket in the attitude of saluting, a Sepoy. Stuck in the barrel of the musket
                  was a long twig from a tree, and at the end of it fluttered a white handkerchief. </p>

               <p>"It's a flag of truce," said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant</roleName>. "Shall we hear
                  what the rascals have to say?" </p>

               <p>"It will be as well," said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>. "Although I
                  must confess I don't like the idea of seeming to treat with such villains, and
                  they can propose nothing that we can possibly accede to."</p>

               <p>The Sepoy slowly advanced, and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName> muttered to himself, "Well, I should just like to knock him
                  over with a bullet! It would be so easy!"</p>

               <p>"Holloa!" cried the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>. "Halt!" </p>

               <p>The Sepoy stopped at once, and cried out, "Noble Sahibs, don't fire!" </p>

               <p>"What do you want?" </p>

               <p>"The great <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#akbarai">Akbar Ai
                     Sahib</persName>, in the name of the <addName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Light of the Earth</addName>, <addName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">King of Delhi</addName>, offers their
                  lives to the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhees</orgName>, on condition of
                  the surrender of their arms." </p>

               <p>"What do you want with our arms? Have you none?"</p>

               <p>"Oh, yes, plenty! But the <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Light
                     of the Earth</addName> is merciful, and he thinks there has been too much blood
                  spilt. He is on his route to <placeName type="city">Benares</placeName>, and would
                  fain spare the fugitive <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhees</orgName> he may meet as
                  he travels." </p>

               <p>"Very well, then! Tell him he has nothing to do but go on his way in peace, and
                  let us go on ours ; and as we will not interfere with him, he need not interfere
                  with us!" </p>

               <p>"But the <persName>Light of the Earth</persName> wishes that the <orgName
                     xml:lang="ur" type="european" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee"
                     >Feringhees</orgName> should trust to his clemency!"</p>

               <p>"Then we beg to decline ; and if you stay here a moment longer, we will shoot
                  you!" </p>

               <p>"Oh!" said the Sepoy, and he disappeared with all the speed imaginable. </p>

               <p>A smile passed across the faces of the young men as this ineffectual negotiation
                  thus came abruptly to a close, and then <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> said, "I tell you
                  what my idea is, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Hannibal</persName>! We must wait till night, and then make a dash out of this
                  hole, for stay here another day we can't, and that's certain, or we shall be
                  starved like rats!"</p>

               <p>"I fear it!"</p>
               <cb n="2"/>

               <p>"And let me tell you all to be careful of your fire!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr. Hawkins</persName>; "for there
                  are not above a dozen cartridges for the guns left in the bag!" </p>

               <p>This news fell like a death-knell on the hearts of the little party, and for some
                  few moments so severe a shock was it, that none of them could find words in which
                  to reply. At length, the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName> said, with a deep sigh, "Well, of course, we did not expect
                  to carry a magazine with us, and we must be careful not to throw away a shot. But
                  just look out, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                     >Adrian</persName>, and see if you can see what these fellows are about!" </p>

               <p>"I can see nothing of them!"</p>

               <p>A suspicious stillness now reigned throughout the quarry, and it carried with it a
                  feeling of more danger than when the Sepoys were firing as hard as they could at
                  the little party. </p>

            </div>
               <head>
                  <date when="1858-03-20">Saturday, March 20, 1858</date>
               </head>
               <pb n="163"/>
               <div type="chapter">
                  <head xml:id="Ch12">CHAPTER XII.</head>
                  <p>THE CONFLAGRATION, AND THE RESCUE</p>

                  <p>THE stillness in the <placeName>quarry</placeName> was, however, soon broken,
                     for, from above, where the sheer precipice of the rocky side went up some
                     seventy feet to the ordinary level of the ground there came a something
                     thundering down, displacing pebbles and bits of the stone and plants, and all
                     kinds of rubbish in its descent, and then ell, with a heavy dull sound, right
                     at the entrance of the recess.</p>

                  <p>"What on earth is that?" said <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName></p>

                  <p>An exclamation from <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                        >Lieutenant Adrian</persName>, and then a sudden rush on his part from the
                     cavern, astonished his friends, and they saw him stoop and fling aside some
                     object. Then there was the crash of some half-dozen muskets, and before a word
                     could be said, the explosion of a large shell awakened echoes far and near, and
                     dashed pieces of the rock in all directions.</p>

                  <p>"It was a shell!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                        >Lieutenant</roleName>. "They must have lit the fuses above, and then rolled
                     it over!"</p>

                  <p>"But you must be hurt!" exclaimed his friends.</p>

                  <p>"No! no! See, I am untouched!" </p>

                  <p>"There is fresh blood on your arm, though!" said <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>.</p>

                  <p>Crash and rumble came another large shell ; and this one hit the top of the
                     large rock before opening to the recess and rolled outwards, so that its
                     explosion could do them no damage whatever. In fact, a yell of pain among the
                     brushwood seemed to bespeak a wound from some flying pieces of the shell to one
                     of the hidden Sepoys.</p>

                  <p>"That will do!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                        >Captain</roleName>. "They have not yet hit upon the way to dislodge us!" </p>

                  <p>"Nor can they, I think," said <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Adrian</persName>. "There is but
                     one way in which they could do it, and that is by assault, and making up their
                     mind to lose a certain number of men, and so carrying the place; and that is
                     just what the Sepoys will not like to do!" </p>

                  <p>"It isn't in them!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                        >Caesar</persName>.</p>

                  <p>"Look!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                        >Captain</roleName>; "what does this mean?"</p>

                  <p>At the further end of the plateau, as if from invisible hands, there was now
                     cast rapidly a numberof boughs and branches one upon another, as fast as they
                     could be piled up. They were tossed there from different parts of the quarry as
                     fast as they could be cut until there was a large quantity, and the height was
                     above that of a man.</p>

                  <p>"Very good!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                        >Captain</roleName>. "That is a kind of breast-work they are making, anf
                     from behind that they will commence a continued fire at us agan, to which we
                     might effectually reply, if we had plenty of ammunition!"</p>

                  <p>"The worst thing in the world, though, and the instant destruction of all,
                     would be to give them the least idea that we are at all short in that
                     particular," remarked the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                        >Lieutenant</roleName> ; "and I propose that we give them a volley the
                     moment they begin to fire upon us."</p>

                  <p>"Agreed! So loose a breastwork as that won't save them much. Now keep close--I
                     see them!"</p>

                  <p>A volley of some twenty shots was poured in from among the boughs of the trees
                     by the Sepoys, and some of them passing through the wide crevie in the piece of
                     rock, found their way into the cavern.</p>

                  <p>"Now, fire!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                        >Captain</roleName>.</p>

                  <p>This time <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr.
                        Hawkins</persName>, too, fired, so that there were four shots rattling away
                     among the green branches, behind which the Sepoys were ensconced.</p>

                  <p>Scarcely had the echo of the discharge made itself heard, when, mingling with
                     it, they heard the sound of a bugle; and with a loud yelling shout, which was
                     no doubt intended to be an imitation, and thought a good one, of the British
                     cheer in charging, the Sepoys rushed from behind their cover, and made for the
                     opening in the side of the <placeName>quarry</placeName>.</p>
                  <cb n="3"/>

                  <p> "Fire again!" shouted the <roleName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, and four
                     more shots brought as many of the foe to the ground.</p>

                  <p>There were no more guns loaded, but the <roleName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, and
                        <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>, and
                     the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant</roleName>
                     had revolvers, which were carefully prepared for action, so they gave another
                     volley from those, and then another. </p>

                  <p>At least ten of the Sepoys had fallen, when <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> tried
                     the effect of a ruse on the remainder, as they were now within about twenty
                     paces of the rock. In a loud voice he called out, "Fix bayonets! Charge!"</p>

                  <p>The Sepoys, who all belonged to one of the revolted regiments, knew what that
                     order meant, and without stopping a moment to argue on the improbability of
                     British troops being in such a place, a panic seized them, and they turned and
                     fled at once.</p>

                  <p>"Hurrah!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                        >Caesar</persName>; and then the little party altogether indulged in a
                     cheer; and as the smoke cleared away they saw the bodies of the dead and
                     wounded Sepoys on the plateau and the breastwork of branches, scattered in all
                     directions. </p>

                  <p>At the sound of the firing, the ladies, no longer able to control their fear
                     and their impatience, rushed from the miserable, dark, narrow passage they were
                     in, and made their appearance in the cavern, and now they showed themselves to
                     their brave defenders. </p>

                  <p>"Oh, what has happened?" said <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>. "Tell us what
                     has happened, I implore you!" </p>

                  <p>"My bag, my bag!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint"
                        >the Hon. Miss Flint</persName>. "Has any one got or seen my bag?" </p>

                  <p>"Oh, keep back, I beg of you!" said the <roleName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>. "We have
                     beaten the rascals off for the moment, but there is no telling how soon they
                     may make another attack upon us." </p>

                  <p>"Not yet awhile, I think," said the <roleName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant</roleName>, who in a
                     moment found himself close to <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName>. "You may
                     depend that last repulse will sicken them of us for some time to come." </p>

                  <p>"I hope so," said the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                        >Captain</persName>. "But tell me, father--what more cartridges have we?" </p>

                  <p>"Only enough to load the guns all round once more." </p>

                  <p>"Alas! Then with that and what we have in our revolvers we must chance our
                     lives. Oh! for but one company of my own gallant regiment! I would sally out
                     and carry all before me. When those rascals sounded the bugle, it fell upon my
                     heart like sunshine for I thought at the moment our own troops were near. But
                     no doubt this contest will be carried on with the same words of command, and
                     the same bugle and drum calls and orders on both sides." </p>

                  <p>"It will sound strange," said the <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant</persName>. </p>

                  <p>"If," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                        >Bessie</persName>, "you really think that there is any cessation of the
                     attack upon us, there is one thing it would be well to ascertain, if possible;
                     and that is, where the narrow passage in which we took refuge extends to. I
                     went along it for some distance, and it still seemed to advance." </p>

                  <p>"That is a good thought!" cried <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>. "You fellows
                     hold the post here, and I will go on a brief exploring expedition." </p>

                  <p>"But the darkness?" said the <roleName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>. </p>

                  <p>"There are wax-lights here in this small bundle I brought with us," said
                        <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr. Hawkins</persName>;
                     "and here are matches, too. It would be a rare piece of good fortune if we
                     could find any means of escape in that direction." </p>

                  <p>"It would, indeed!" said the <roleName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>; "for I
                     almost despair of it in this." </p>

                  <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> lit a
                     piece of wax candle, and proceeded to the narrow passage which has been so
                     often mentioned. There could be no doubt of what it really was--namely, an
                     exterior working of the quarry, for the purpose of extracting blocks from a
                     particular vein of stone that had been lit upon by the quarriers in the old
                     times, when stone was extracted from that place. How far such old workings or
                     galleries might extend was beyond all conjectures, and whether or not had any
                     other outlet was a matter only to be determined by exploration.</p>

                  <p>Scarcely, however, had <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                        >Caesar</persName> taken two steps in the narrow passage than he heard his
                     name loudly called by his brother; and hastily returning to the cavern, he
                     cried out, "What has happened?" </p>

                  <p>"They are firing the brushwood," said the <roleName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, "and we
                     shall be smoked out at last, for the wind sets this way. What is to be done
                     now?"</p>

                  <p>The females uttered cries of desapri, and as <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> stood at the
                     back of the cavern with the glimmering light in his hand, there came exultant
                     shouts from the Sepoys without, and already a pungent odour of burning wood
                     began to find its way into the recess. </p>

                  <p>"Well," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                        >Caesar</persName>, "to the best of my belief, I should say it's all up with
                     us now!" </p>

                  <p>"Hush!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                        >Bessie</persName>; "I heard something! Hush!" </p>

                  <p>From afar off, the regular beat of a drum, and the shrill, faint whistle of
                     fifes, came upon their ears. </p>

                  <p>"Hurrah! hurrah!" screamed, rather than shouted, the <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"> Captain</persName>. "British
                     troops on the march, by heaven!" </p>

                  <p>
                     <emph>(To be continued in our next.)</emph>
                  </p>

                  <p>---</p>
               </div>            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
