<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model hcorresp="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!--<?xml-model hcorresp="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<!--
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/xsl" href="../xsl/rymer.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/css" href="../style.css" alternate="yes"?>
-->


<?xml-model href="../schema/sepoys.schema.xml" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Sepoys; Or, Highland Jessie: an electronic edition</title>
            <author>James Malcolm Rymer</author>
            <author>
               <persName type="pseudo">M. J. Errym</persName>
            </author>
            <editor>Rebecca Nesvet</editor>
            <editor>Rae X. Yan</editor>
            <editor type="technical">Adam McCune</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Rebecca Nesvet</publisher>
            <publisher>Rae X. Yan</publisher>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <idno>sepoys</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct xml:id="installment5" prev="sepoys.3.06.xml#installment4"
               next="sepoys.3.20.xml#installment6">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter IX: The Flight to Agra</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-03-13"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter X: The Sepoy's Gratitude--The Night in the Quarry</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-03-13"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <!-- Information about the encoding of the text -->
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Information about the project itself (goals, organization, activities)</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Information about how the texts in a collection were chosen or excerpted</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="unknown">
               <p>Information about treatment of errors in the source (silently corrected, etc.)</p>
            </correction>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Information about normalization practices (e.g. treatment of roman numerals,
                  spelling, etc.)</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation form="std">
               <p>Information about treatment of quotations (preservation of original quotation
                  marks, etc.)</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="hard">
               <p>Treatment of the hyphenation of the source</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Information about whether and how the text has been segmented (mostly for
                  linguistic purposes)</p>
            </segmentation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Information about any interpretive information added to the text</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="installment">
            <head>
               <date when="1858-03-13">Saturday, March 13, 1858</date>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="facsimiles/sepoys.3.13.png"/>
            </figure>
            <pb n="97"/>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <head>THE <orgName corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sepoys">SEPOYS</orgName>; OR,
                  <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">HIGHLAND JESSIE</persName>.</head>
            <head>A TALE OF THE PRESENT INDIAN REVOLT.</head>
            <head>AUTHOR OF <title> "JANE BRIGHTWELL,"</title>
               <title>"THE SNOW-DRIFT,"</title> ETC</head>

            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch9">CHAPTER IX: THE FLIGHT TO <placeName type="city"
                  >AGRA</placeName></head>

               <p>THE FLIGHT TO <placeName type="city">AGRA</placeName>.</p>

               <p>---</p>

               <p>THE dangers and difficulties of the fugitivies from <placeName type="city"
                     >Delhi</placeName> were far from over, even when they had fairly passed through
                  the gate of the city, and had left behind them the turmoil of the old
                  capital<!--sic--> of Indian monarchy, and all the wild riot now had a home within
                  its ancient walls. Detached groups of revolted <orgName type="indian"
                     >Sepoys</orgName>, and disorderly bands of villagers, and idlers of all kinds
                  and descriptions, athirst for plunder and violence, were scattered over the whole
                  country. The glare of burning bungalows, and the sounds of tumult, but too plainly
                  came upon their senses. They felt like people who had just escaped a hostile port,
                  to embark upon a storm-tossed ocean.</p>
               <p>The countenances of all were pale; but there was a determination in the close-set
                  lips of the men, that showed they would, with life itself, hold faithful to their
                  charge of protecting those innocent ones, whose only hope now lay in them. From
                  the frivolity, and almost the effeminate luxury, of idle Eastern habits, the young
                  men of the party seemed at once to start to life and energt, and the English
                  character shone at once through the thin mask of oriental depreciation.</p>
               <p>But now that this family, and these friends and connexions, appeared as hunted
                  fugitives--and now that they heard the yell of the aroused <orgName
                     type="religious">Hindoo</orgName> on every hand--the thought possibly struck
                  some of them, that it is the most abject of slaves, who, when the occasion serves,
                  make the worst masters; and that it might have been well to have reigned over the
                  Indian in such a manner to attack his heart a little, and not solely by awakening
                  his fears.</p>
               <p>The horses were fresh, and the night air was cool, so they trotted on swiftly; but
                  what would become of the party when relays would be wanted, and could not be
                  procured--and, when on foot, they might find themselves struggling through a
                  hostile population--was not then to be thought of with anything like
                  equanimity.</p>
               <p>And now, some six miles of distance from the city was accomplished, when, nearing
                  a clump of trees which formed a sort of covering for some building which appeared
                  faintly through them, a loud voice challenged<cb n="2"/> the party in Hindoo, and
                  before an answer could be returned by those in the first carriage, a shot was
                  fired which injured one of the horses.</p>
               <p>An instant halt of both of the vehicles took place, and as had been resolved upon
                  in case of such a contingency, the gentlemen sprang to the ground with their
                  firearms, and took a post in front, determined to sell their lives dearly in
                  defence of those whom they were trying to save.</p>
               <p>By common consent, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> was looked to as a sort of leader, and he issued his
                  directions in as calm a voice as he could command.</p>
               <p>"There are <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> in the wood," he said, "without
                  a doubt. Does any one, here, know the place?"</p>
               <p>"Yes," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr.
                     Hawkins</persName>, "I know it! It is a <placeName type="building"
                     xml:id="sepoys.backmatter.xml#elhareeb">tomb</placeName>, and thickly wooded
                  all round. There is a road through the trees, though, and to the left we shall get
                  into the high road to <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>!"</p>
               <p>"Yes--oh, yes! To <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>!" cried <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>. "He is at
                     <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>--my husband. Oh let us get there,
                  and we shall yet be saved!"</p>
               <p>"Nay," commenced <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr.
                     Hawkins</persName>; "I doubt--"</p>
               <p>"Pardon me, all of you," interrupted <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>. "We can
                  discuss our route afterwards. Let us extricate ourselves now as best we can. Help
                  me, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>! This
                  way! Turn the horses' heads from the wood! Shrink down, all of you, in the
                  carriages!</p>
               <p>The <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</persName> made
                  his dispositions quickly. The carriages were wheeled to the side of the road, and
                  their backs presented obliquely to the trees only, while <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> and his father
                  occupied posts assigned them by <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal</persName>, and he himself
                  took the centre position between the two vehicles. They were each provided pretty
                  well with fire-arms, for at the last moment, almost, before leaving the <placeName
                     type="building">bungalow</placeName>, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr. Hawkins></persName> had brought
                  away several more guns and pistols, and plenty of ammunition in a bag, where it
                  luckily had been deposited so portably.</p>
               <p>"Keep quiet, all of you, as you value your lives," said the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</persName>; "they will be
                  upon us directly, for that fellow who fired was an outpost!"</p>
               <p>Tremblingly the females shrank down in the carriages, and then a feeble voice said
                  faintly, "Where am I?--what is it all?"</p>
               <p>It was <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant
                     Adrian</persName>, who, just recovered from a swoon, into which the loss of
                  blood from his wounds had thrown him, now spoke. He was extended on the floor
                  portion of the carriage, close to the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, who inclined
                  his ear to him, as he said, "My dear fellow, keep close and quiet, and all will be
                  well, I hope. We will pull you through!"</p>
               <p>"Through! through! But, what? Oh, heaven! yes! The revolt! the revolt! They have
                  hit me hard, I fear!"</p>
               <cb n="3"/>
               <p>"Cheer up!--all will be well! Yet, stop a bit! You know the environs of <placeName
                     type="city">Delhi</placeName> well? <roleName type="famil"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Father</roleName>, what is this
                     <placeName type="building" xml:id="sepoys.backmatter.xml#elhareeb"
                     >tomb</placeName> named?"</p>
               <p>"<placeName type="building" xml:id="sepoys.backmatter.xml#elhareeb">El
                     Hareeb</placeName>!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon"
                     >Mr. Hawkins</persName>.</p>
               <p>"You hear, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                  >Adrian</persName>?--do you know anything of it?"</p>
               <p>"Only, that it was always a post of the <orgName type="indian">Sepoy guard of the
                     67th Regiment</orgName>."</p>
               <p>As these words came from the mouth of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant Adrian</persName>, there
                  rushed from among the trees, with shouts of ferocity, a disorderly band of some
                  thirty or forty <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName>, one of whom bore a torch,
                  which he held aloft as he danced a demoniacal kind of fling, which went near to
                  extinguish the flame that was intended to light his comrades to their prey. There
                  was the gleam of <foreign xml:lang="hi" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#tulwars"
                     >tulwars</foreign> and daggers, but it was evident the idea of the <orgName
                     type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> was that they had only to intercept a fugitive
                  carriage or two, and that nothing like military resistance would be made. </p>
               <p>In this they were soon undeceived.</p>
               <p>At first, the absence of the reported vehicles from the main road seemed a
                  surprise, but they were soon espied. Then there was a yell and a rush, and the
                  vouce of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> rang out clearly the word "Fire!"</p>
               <p>To his surprise, the volley that came from his little party was much more
                  effective than he expected it to be, for three shots at each discharge were all he
                  counted upon; but he felt confident there were double that number; and who were
                  the unexpected allies he could not guess</p>
               <p>The <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> staggered back, and he who bore the
                  torch fell to the ground.</p>
               <p>"Fire!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName> again; for he knew that the party had plenty of weapons
                  ready loaded.</p>
               <p>Another rattling volley completed the discomfiture of the <orgName type="indian"
                     >Sepoys</orgName>; and with howls and shouts of rage they retreated into the
                  wood, leaving five of their number dead on the field, and carrying off as many
                  more wounded.</p>
               <p>"How is this?" shouted <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>, when the smoke a little subsided. "Who fired?"</p>
               <p>"I!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                     Hope</persName></p>
               <p>"And I!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#volumina">Volumina
                     Hawkins</persName>.</p>
               <p>"And I!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant
                     Adrian</persName>, faintly. "My revolver still has a charge in it, and I
                  thought I could fire past you as I lay here!"</p>
               <p>"Why, the fact is," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>, "I handed up the spare guns to the girls, and told them to
                  blaze away if they could."</p>
               <p>"Bravo!" cried the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>. "Load everything, for they will be on us again, I
                  fancy!"</p>
               <p>"No! no!" whispered <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                     >Adrian</persName>. "On--on at once, if you would save yourselves! I know them
                  well!</p>
               <pb n="154"/>
               <cb n="1"/>
               <p>They will carry their wounded right into the temple, and howl some prayers over
                  them, before they make another attack! If you now hurry on, you may get through
                  the wood, which is very small. On--on, I beg of you, for all our sakes!"</p>
               <p>This was too good advice to be wasted, and, accordingly, it was on the moment
                  acted upon. The horses were a little restive from the firing, but not to a
                  sufficient extent to render them unconquerable, although it was a matter of far
                  more consequence to find that the one that had been wounded was evidently weak
                  from loss of blood. The necessity, however, of immediate progress had been so
                  clearly pointed out by the wounded <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant</roleName>, that, with all
                  the doubts that the state of the horse warranted, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName> and his
                  brother soon had the carriages in the roadway again.</p>
               <p>Anything like the concealment of the two carriages seemed at first to be out of
                  the question; but when they got beneath the trees they found the ground so soft
                  and yielding, that the wheels made not the slightest sound, and the horses'
                  hoofs<!--sic--> were scarcely heard, as they fell upon the thick and elastic turf.
                  Then there arose, in the breasts of the fugitives, the hope that they might pass
                  unobserved; and they listened, with throbbing hearts, to any sound that might be
                  indicative of the approach of their enemies. The wood, in the darkness that
                  surrounded it, might be a mere copse, or of much more considerable extent, so far
                  as they could see; but certainly the passage through it appeared to last an
                  age.</p>
               <p>Suddenly, then, to the immense relief of the whole party, they say the night sky;
                  and the trees thinned gradually away.</p>
               <p>"Saved, dear <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>,
                  from that danger!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                     Hope</persName>, in an agitated whisper. </p>
               <p>"Thank heaven! No one is hurt?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, no! no! There were no fire-arms used against us!"</p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>! If they
                  should kill me, you will protect this dear child! Oh, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, you will! you
                  will!"</p>
               <p>"Hush! Can you doubt me? You suffer yourself to be too much agitated! All may yet
                  be well!"</p>
               <p>The carriages just cleared the last trees of the wood, when a rattling discharge
                  of fire-arms behind them, and the loud shouts of the <orgName type="indian"
                     >Sepoys</orgName>, sufficiently evidenced an active pursuit.</p>
               <p>"We are lost!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr.
                     Hawkins</persName>.</p>
               <p>"No!--never lost!" cried the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>. "They are on foot, and we shall tire them out yet! On! on!
                  If any one is hit, let him or her at once speak! On <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>! Nay, that will do
                  better! You can drive, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#volumina"
                     >Volumina</persName>! Take the reins; don't look back or think of anything in
                  the world but keeping the horse in the middle of the road, such as it is! Follow
                  the other carriage closely--keep a line with it! I am the rear guard!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>
                  scrambled to the back portion of the carriage, and kneeling on the seat, he only
                  exposed his head over the half-hood which belonged to it. Again, by his
                  directions, the ladies crouched down with the exception of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#volumina">Volumina</persName>, who boldly
                  acted as charioteer; and on they went, pursued by a rabble rout of Sepoys, who,
                  now having fire-arms with them, took shots at them in plenty.</p>
               <p>More than one bullet passed in close proximity to the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, who kept up a
                  rapid fire from a couple of guns which his father loaded for him as quickly as he
                  could. This sort of running fight lasted for some time, until, as the distance
                  between the <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> who were on foot, and the
                  carriages, increased, there seemed evert likelihood of a complete escape from
                  them; and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> called out rather exultantly, "Bravo! bravo, my friends!
                  They are giving up the pursuit, I hope; and no mischief is done, I think!"</p>
               <p>"None! none!" cried all voices at once, when down fell the wounded horses, which
                  was in the carriage in advance, and lay either dead or so nearly so as to be
                  incapable of motion.</p>
               <p>This most <emph>malapropos</emph> accident altered at once the aspect of affair,
                  and reduced the party either to the painful necessity of separating, or of all
                  proceeding on foot; for under no pressure of circumstances whatever could one
                  carriage be made to contain the whole of the fugitives; and where anothe horse was
                  to be got was an unsolved mystery.</p>
               <p>They were now not above nine miles from <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>,
                  and in a very wild and uncultivated bit of country, abounding in small clumps of
                  trees, and in a sort of hilly well at places that made travelling difficult and
                  dangerous. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>'s heart for a moment seemed to shink within him at the
                  prospect that was before them, and springing to the ground, he looked about him
                  with a feeling akin to dismay.</p>
               <p>"There is no help for it!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>. "If the ladies
                  alone were in one of the carriages, it would not take them a mile!"</p>
               <p>At these words, with agitated looks, the whole party alighted, and <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>, the whole of
                  whose <cb n="2"/>natural courage seemed to have evaporated in the all-absorbing
                  fears for her child, was on the point of giving way to a torrent of grief and
                  despair, when she was calmed by the remonstrances of her sister.</p>
               <p>"Something must be done!" suggested <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr. Hawkins</persName>,
                  patronisingly.</p>
               <p>In this all agreed, but it was what the something was that was to be that
                  constituted the difficulty; and the dount as to whether they were still pursued or
                  not by the <orgName type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> from the wood, was one of equal
                  anxiety.</p>
               <p>
                  <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain Hawkins</persName>
                  roused himself from what looked, for a few moments, like utter depression, and in
                  a clear voice he said, "Our first care is to get rid of our pursuers, and that, I
                  think, if they are still upon our track, we may do, and save yet some of the
                  party. <roleName type="family" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon"
                     >Father</roleName>, will you, with such of the ladies as agree among themselves
                  to go in the one carriage still left us, go forward; and we, with the others, will
                  follow on foot?" </p>
               <p>"No! no!" cried everybody; "we will all remain together!"</p>
               <p>They were pale faced, tearful eyes, and trembling limbs, that stood in that
                  throng, but no one faltered for a moment in the determination to keep together,
                  and for each to share the fortune of all. Even the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint">Hon. Miss Flint</persName>, after
                  some inarticulate remarks of how she might have been "settled" often comfortably
                  in <placeName type="country">England</placeName>, declared she would take the
                  chance of what "offered" with the other party.</p>
               <p>Poor <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshawkins">Mrs.
                     Hawkins</persName>, what with the fatigue and the anxiety of the last few
                  hours, was nearly so far invalided as to be incapable of taking any active part in
                  the affair.</p>
               <p>All now looked again to <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>, and, with just a slight thickness in his voice, he
                  said, "Be it so! This one carriage will not carry us off, but in abandoning it, we
                  may make it do us good service yet. Help me such of you as can!"</p>
               <p>By the aid of <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName> and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr.
                     Hawkins</persName>, the fallen horse, which was found to be quite dead, was
                  released from its harness and dragged out of sight to the side of the road. The
                  useless carriage, too, was rolled into the thicket, where it was not reasily
                  observable, and then <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> addressed the party in explanation of what he meant to
                  do.</p>
               <p>"There is but little doubt," he said, "but we shall be pursued by horsemen; and
                  what I propose to do, is to start the horse on with this empty vehicle, so as to
                  carry them as far past as possible; and then we can hold counsel as to what course
                  we are to adopt in getting to some station where we shall find English troops. All
                  of you stoop down, among the thick brushwood by the side of the road here, and you
                  will be safe enough while they see the carriage in advance."</p>
               <p>This certainly seemed the only rational plan of present safety to pursue, and it
                  was at once adopted. Poor <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                     >Lieutenant Adrian</persName> was carefully lifted from the carriage and placed
                  among the vegetation by the roadside; although he declared that, as no bones were
                  broken, he ought to be able to walk, with a little help.</p>
               <p>"Soon enough, my good fellow," said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, "when we all go
                  on! Save your strength now!"</p>
               <p>"How much do I owe you!" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">young officer</roleName>, with tears
                  glistening in his eyes.</p>
               <p>"Pho! pho!--don't think of it! Here, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>--you look after our
                  friend <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Adrian</persName>, like
                  a good girl, as you are!"</p>
               <p>"What is that, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Hannibal</persName>?" suddenly exclaimed <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>.</p>
               <p>"What? what?"</p>
               <p>"Listen! I hear them now again! The tramp of horses' feet, and the jingle of
                  accoutremenets! If the road did not take a turn, we should see them."</p>
               <p>"And they us!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>. "We are pursued, and by some of the rebel light horse, too!
                  Down, all of you!--down among the brushwood! That will do! Not a word--not a
                  breath!"</p>
               <p>They were all hidden, and the horse in the empty carriage looked a little scared
                  at the sudden disappearance of every one, and at the rather odd way in which
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> approached him, with a long, lithe, branch of a tree in his
                  hand.</p>
               <p>"Off, and away!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>, as he dealt the horse a switch with the branch. The
                  creature crouched for a moment in surprise, for it was high-spirited, and
                  unaccustomed to the lash; and then, with the empty carriage behind it, it darted
                  off at a rapid pace.</p>
               <p>"That will do!" said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>, as he flung himself down and crawled away to his
                  friends.</p>
               <p>The night of an Indian sky is a very different thing indeed to that of our more
                  northern region. There is none of that dim blackness which enshrouds all things,
                  and commingles them into one impenetrable mass of looming shadow. There is none of
                  that dismal tangibility, so to speak, in the air, as though it had congealed into
                  a pall and clung to all in nature, robbing the sky of its glorious tints, the
                  green earth of its verdant beauty, and every sweet flower of its dazzling dyes.
                  No; the Indian night only differs from the <cb n="3"/>day as being a thing of
                  different beauty and glory. There is the same deep blue sky, but without
                  sunlight,--amends are made by the myriad stars that seem there so much nearer the
                  earth than in our misty regions; and although the daylight, properly so called,
                  has, in truth, passed away, it leaves behind it an opalescent splendour which is
                  as beautiful, if not more so, and intensely grateful to the eyes after the glare
                  of that nearly tropical sun.</p>
               <p>In this sweet, wavering light, which looks like that of some star with a new and
                  rare atmosphere of its own, all objects are sufficiently visible; and tree, and
                  hill, and stream retain certain characteristics beneath the mild effulgence, even
                  as they do in the most garish sunshine. Hence was it that, like creatures in a
                  vision, still distinct, yet still commingled in the soft, fair, ethereal splendour
                  of the night, every one of our little party played his or her part; and they could
                  see, from the hiding-place, all that passed upon the roughly-trodden road they had
                  so very recently travelled, and so close to which they crouched in hiding.</p>
               <p>Their horse-bits, chain, and loose gear--of which the Eastern soldiery are ever so
                  fond--rattling on the still air, came driving on the <orgName type="indian"
                     >Sepoy</orgName> cavalry. They made sure of their prey as with shouts they
                  careered onwards, with a wild sort of exultation that once again they could assume
                  the irregular march of Asiatic troops, instead of the regular battalion-like
                  precision of Europeans.</p>
               <p>"Forward!" cried an offiver, as he waved his sword in the air. "Not a <orgName
                     xml:lang="ur" type="european" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee"
                     >Feringhee</orgName> from <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName> should
                  escape except through the gates of death!"</p>
               <p>"Death! death!" was shouted from the strange rout as they charged on, and like a
                  whirlwind swept past the spot where lay concealed the fugitives from the city.</p>
               <p>All but one--yes, all but one! And the horse of that one stumbled in some loose
                  gear from the trappings of the dead horse that had been drawn aside by our party,
                  and he and his rider came rolling on the road together.</p>
               <p>An execration, and then a shout to his comrades to pause and assist him, and then
                  another full-mouthed curse, in the names of half a dozen <orgName type="indian"
                     >Hindoo</orgName> divinities, upon all their heads for leaving him behind them,
                  all passed in a moment, and both horse and man scrambled again to their feet; but
                  the steed was scared, and it dashed from the feeble grip of the <orgName
                     type="indian">Sepoy</orgName>, and scoured away, while he, apparently more hurt
                  than at first seemed to be the case, staggered a pace or two, and then fell
                  again.</p>
               <p>All this passed in a moment or two, and, according to the hacknied expression, in
                  a very much shorter space of time than it has taken to record it.</p>
               <p>The sound of the horses' feet of the party that had passed gradually died away,
                  and then <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> lifted his head carefully over the low brushwood and took a
                  minute observation of the prostrate Sepoy</p>
               <p>--</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch10">CHAPTER X: THE SEPOY'S GRATITUDE--THE NIGHT IN THE <placeName
                     type="building">QUARRY</placeName></head>

               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">"CAESAR,"</persName> whispered
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName> to his brother, "what is to be done with that fellow?"</p>
               <p>"Shoot him!"</p>
               <p>"Nay, I don't half fancy it."</p>
               <p>"Then I do! Here goes!"</p>
               <p>"Oh, no, no!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                     Hope</persName>. "I pray you do not. It looks so like--like--murder!"</p>
               <p>"If I were anything like assured that the fellow had committed any of the
                  atrocities of which <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName> has been a witness,"
                  said <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">the Captain</roleName>,
                  "I would shoot him like a dog; but as it is, I don't seem to fancy it."</p>
               <p>"Oh, spare all that there is a doubt about!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshope">Mrs. Hope</persName>, speaking
                  faintly, for she was ill and exhausted.</p>
               <p>"Well," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                  >Caesar</persName>, "I'll bring him in at all risks; for we can't get out of this
                  until the rascal is got rid of somehow. He may have his eyes open, although
                  otherwise done up by his tumble.</p>
               <p>No one opposed this, and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName> marched out of the cover, and dealt the Sepoy a kick, as he
                  said, "Get up, and no tricks!"</p>
               <p>The Sepoy rolled over twice, and then elevated himself to his knees, as he said,
                  "Mercy, Sahib! Mercy!"</p>
               <p>"Mercy, you rascal! That all depends on circumstance. Give up your arms, will
                  you?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, great Sahib! Lord of <placeName type="country">India</placeName>. yes.
                  yes!"</p>
               <p>The Sepoy handed his <foreign xml:lang="hi"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#tulwars">tulwar</foreign>, and took from his
                  breast a couple of pistols, which, as he held them by their butts, looked
                  awkwardly close, muzzlewise, to <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>'s heart. It was
                  accident that, at that moment, the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> called out,
                  "Quick, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                  >Caesar</persName>!"</p>
               <p>With a roar of alarm, the Sepoy tumbled backward, and one of the pistols went
                  off.</p>
               <p>"Why, you blundering fool!" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>; "if I only thought
                  that was on purpose----"</p>
               <p>"No, no, Sahib! Great and mightly Sahib! Lord</p>
               <pb n="155"/>
               <cb n="1"/>
               <p>your humble slave! No! Accident, all! The lowest of your slaves is at your feet,
                  great warrior!</p>
               <p>"Great fiddlestick!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>, as he placed the pistols in his own belt. "Come on with
                  you!"</p>
               <p>The Sepoy crawled after him, and seemed annoyed, when brought into the brushwood,
                  to find so large a party of Europeans. He struck himself on the breast twice; and
                  picking up a pinch of dust, flung it on the top of his head, and uttered several
                  groans.</p>
               <p>"The rascal!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>. "All that is in his despair that his comrades did not find
                  us out. He seems badly hurt on the side of the head, though."</p>
               <p>The fact was, that the blood was trickling from a wound that the fall had given
                  him on the head; and now, with the instinctive humanity of woman, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshope">Mrs. Hope</persName>, without a
                  word, took a scarf from her neck, and bound it round his forehead.</p>
               <p>The Sepoy crossed his hands, and burst into such a throng of expressions of
                  gratitude, and invoked such multitudinous curses on his own head, and on those of
                  all his family, past, present, and to come, if he ever forgot the goodness of
                  Madam Sahib, that <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName> gave him a pole with the end of one of the pistols, as he
                  said, "That will do! Now, what did you and your fellows want on the road?"</p>
               <p>"I am the Sahib's slave but they wanted to stop two coaches."</p>
               <p>"Is there a well near here?"</p>
               <p>"Yes; at <placeName type="city">Joondar</placeName>."</p>
               <p>"Oh, we are near the village of that name, then? I thought so, by Jove! Now,
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal</persName>, here
                  are the ladies parched with thirst, and our poor wounded friend, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Adrian</persName>, in a kind of
                  fever, and half-choked; so water we must have before we start onwards, and we must
                  consider, too, where onwards is to lie."</p>
               <p>"I have thought over it," said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>; "and if we
                  could only reach <placeName type="city">Agra</placeName>, there are sure to be
                  troops there."</p>
               <p>"It's a long march."</p>
               <p>"It is, indeed; and if we take it, we must march by night, and find out a shelter
                  somewhere by day, either in the woods or in any of the deserted <placeName
                     type="building">bungalows</placeName> on our route. I expect of the latter
                  there are many, for families living in out-of-the-way placed will naturally fly to
                  the nearest military station."</p>
               <p>"It is the only thing to be done, brother. What say you, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Adrian</persName>?"</p>
               <p>"To <placeName type="city">Agra</placeName>, by all means, if possible! Oh! water!
                  water! I think if I had water, I should be able to rise and march well with all of
                  you."</p>
               <p>"Patience, my good fellow, and you shall have some soon, or my name is not
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar Hawkins</persName>.
                  We must have some food and water for all. Now, this rascal says there is a village
                  at hand. I propose to go with him on a foraging expedition."</p>
               <p>"You with him?"</p>
               <p>"Yes, to take care of him while he takes care of me. Among the things flung into
                  the carriage over younger among the trees are plenty of odds and ends of clothing,
                  that will make a respectable mountainteer of me; and they, you know, are fairer
                  than plain men. I need not speak, and you may trust me to look sharp after our
                  friend here."</p>
               <p>"But once in the village, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>, and he may betray you at once!"</p>
               <p>"Not he! he values his own life too much. I will keep him by the hand. We need but
                  go to a hut or two, and at the first symptom of treachery he will fully understand
                  that I will blow his brains out, and then make a running fight back here for my
                  own life. Besides, it is really doubtful if any news of what has happened at
                     <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName> has reached the villages yet."</p>
               <p>"Go, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>, and
                  heaven help you!" said his father.</p>
               <p>"I'm off! Give an eye to this fellow, while I run over to the carriage for what I
                  want."</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> soon
                  returned with sufficient apparel to take off his absolutely Europan appearance,
                  and then he said to the Sepoy, "Hark ye, my friend! here are a few rupees; we want
                  food and water from the village, and you must ask for both."</p>
               <p>"May my Lord Sahib's days be lengthened as the shadows of evening! May----</p>
               <p>"Hold your row, will you? I'm going with you--to take care of you, you know. I
                  don't intend to speak; but if you say one word, or give one look that points to
                  treachery, you are a dead man!"</p>
               <p>"On my head be it! May the grave of my mother be dug up by the jackal! may--</p>
               <p>"Be quiet! What do I care about all your seed, breed, and generation? Come along
                  now."</p>
               <p>With his hand in the breast of his apparel, grasping the butt of a pistol,
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> walked by
                  the side of the Sepoy, who, by the rapidity by which he took the young man to the
                  village, showed his perfect acquaintance with the neighbourhood. It was one of
                  those miserable little Indian hamlets, with about twenty wretched huts and one
                  better than the others, the residence of the <foreign xml:lang="ur"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#zemindar">zemindar</foreign>, or landed
                  proprietor. All was still, for the villagers had retired to rest; but <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>
                  <cb n="2"/>stopped at the first door and knocked, as he said to the Sepoy in a low
                  tone of voice, "Get what you can here, but, above all, a jar of water."</p>
               <p>"Even so, great Sahib!"</p>
               <p>The wretched peon who owned the cottage came to the door in a fright, and when the
                  wants of his visitors were explained and a rupee shown him, some dates, some
                  coarse brown cakes, and a jar of water were speedily produced.</p>
               <p>"That will do," whispered <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>. "Now, back again. What are you doing now?"</p>
               <p>The Sepoy had elevated his two fingers in a mysterious way just above the crown of
                  his head, and the peon, with a slught exclamation, stepped back into the hut and
                  closed the door.</p>
               <p>"It is the sign of my caste, Sahib! I thought him one with me, but he is not. I
                  spit upon him! Bah! Poof!"</p>
               <p>"Confound your jargon and nonsense! Come along."</p>
               <p>The Sepoy put the jar of water on his head, and trotted quite patiently back to
                  the spot where the party most anxiously awaited <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>'s return.</p>
               <p>"All's right!" said the latter. "All's safe! I don't think they know anything int
                  he village of how matters stand at <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>, and
                  the best thing we can do after this little rest we have had, and finishing the
                  water and what we have to eat, is to push on <placeName type="city"
                     >Agra</placeName> way as nearly as we can."</p>
               <p>This was agreed to on all hands, and the delicious cool water was a most
                  delightful and seasonable relief. It seemed to put new life into <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant Adrian</persName>, who
                  drew a long breath, and for the first time sat up and looked about him.</p>
               <p>At that moment, with a strange rushing sound, some one passed on the road. It was
                  a dark naked figure, with the hair tied to the top of the hewad, and in all
                  respects resembling the Hindoo post or message-bearers from one station to
                  another. The figure was gone in an instant, and on the road to <placeName
                     type="city">Delhi</placeName>.</p>
               <p>"I don't like that!" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>.</p>
               <p>"Nor do I!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>.</p>
               <p>A sudden exclamation at this moment from <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant Adrian</persName>, who,
                  for thefirst, had a fair look at the Sepoy, caused every one to start round, as he
                  cried out, "Seize that villain! seize that villain! I saw him with my own eyes
                  slaughter two children in <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName>; and he pursued
                  me, too! I know him by that scar on his cheek. Seize him!"</p>
               <p>The Sepoy, with a yell, flung himself suddenly backwards, and rolled over and over
                  like a ball. <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>
                  fired two shots after him, but whether they were effective or not, there was no
                  means of telling, as, in another moment, he was gone in the darkness and distance
                  of the thick growth of underwood around.</p>
               <p>This little incident threw the party into a sea of conjectures as to what might be
                  the result of it, and <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName> exclaimed, "Confound the rascal! First thoughts are best
                  with them! If I had shot him, as I intended, all would have been right!"</p>
               <p>"Ah!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName>, "What is this?"</p>
               <p>"What? where?" said every one.</p>
               <p>An arrow had passed within two inches of her head, and stuck quivering in the
                  slender trunk of a young tree, against which she had been leaning, with the
                  child.</p>
               <p>"To the roadway!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>, "over the way! To the cover of the carriage on the
                  other side! Quick! This way all, all of you! That is the way! Face them with me,
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>! Don't
                  throw away a shot! Fire, whenever you see one of them, and be sure to hit
                  him!"</p>
               <p>In a moment the little bivouac, if it might be so termed, was broken up; and while
                  the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> and
                     <persName>Caesar</persName> kept, with <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant Adrian</persName>, their
                  faces to the direction whence the arrow came, the ladies ran across the roadway,
                  and sheltered themselves behind the disabled carriage.</p>
               <p>Strange to say, though, no more missiles of any description came against them at
                  that moment. No doubt the arrow was the only one the Sepoy had about him, hidden
                  probably in his sleeve or back. The well-known dexterity of the <orgName
                     type="religious">Hindoos</orgName> in extemporising a bow, if they have a knife
                  and a string withthem, and are anywhere near trees sufficiently accounted for that
                  part of the transaction.</p>
               <p>"Well!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                  >Caesar</persName>, "that's the Sepoy's gratitude! If ever I come across that
                  fellow again, I'll make short work of him!"</p>
               <p>"The rascal!" muttered the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain</roleName>, wrathfully. "Well, well, he is off now, and so must we be!
                  Some half-mile further on from here, the high road to <placeName type="city"
                     >Agra</placeName> branches off to the left. I do not say that we can walk so
                  far, or that we may not have many perils and adventures before getting there, but
                  yet it is to <placeName type="city">Agra</placeName> that I should advise we
                  direct our thoughts, for there are British troops certainly!"</p>
               <p>"Unlessm: said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#vernon">Mr.
                     Hawkins</persName>, "<placeName>Agra</placeName> has shared the fate of
                     <placeName type="city">Delhi</placeName> and <placeName type="city"
                     >Meerut</placeName>!"</p>
               <cb n="3"/>
               <p>"I dread to think of that!" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain.</roleName> "It is very
                  terrible, but we may be wanderers yet for many a day in <placeName type="country"
                     >India</placeName>, and how are these gentle ones to stand fatigue and
                  privation?"</p>
               <p>"Don't be down-hearted!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>. "If <placeName type="country">India</placeName> is up and
                  rebellion is over the land, detached bodies of our own troops will be on the move
                  from place to place in all directions over the country, and we may soon fall in
                  with some of them, when our worst troubles will be over!"</p>
               <p>"Heaven send we may!"</p>
               <p>The fire-arms were now carefully looked to and distributed among the party; and
                  headed by <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>, while the rear was brought up by <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>; they commenced
                  their melancholy march through a country soon to be infested with foes of the most
                  implacable character. The night was fast wearing away, and the faint dawn of a new
                  day was beginning to show itself, when poor <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshope">Mrs. Hope</persName> sunk exhausted
                  and could proceed no further.</p>
               <p>"Blessings on you all!" she said, faintly. "My prayers will attend you!"</p>
               <p>"What!" cried <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain
                     Hawkins</persName>, "do you think so meanly of us, madam, as to believe we are
                  going to leave you, or any of our number, behind? No! we all live or perish
                  together!"</p>
               <p>A faintly uttered but deeply felt English hurrah was the response to this speech
                  from every throat, and the party halted.</p>
               <p>The situation of this little band of fugitives was now as picturesque as it was
                  perilous. They had halted on a sort of ridge of rising ground, whcih to their
                  right sloped downwards with great rapidity, and was lost to observation amid a
                  confused mass of brushwood and tangled vegeration. To the left was one of those
                  singular remains which are scattered over <placeName type="country"
                     >India</placeName>, as evidences and traces of a civilization and a people
                  higher in the scale of art-education than either the <orgName type="religious"
                     >Hindoos</orgName> or the <orgName type="religious">Mussulman races</orgName>
                  that now inhabit the country. Little but a couple of walls and one ruined portico
                  survived of what had been once, no doubt, a large and magnificent building of the
                  most elaborate design and rare sculptured elegance.</p>
               <p>The road, in front, wound down a slight declivity to a wild open-looking country. </p>
               <p>"What is to be done?" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>. "By Jove, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Hannibal</persName>, it is you who
                  must decide, for the daylight is coming."</p>
               <p>"Then I decide for a halt," said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>, "till the
                  evening comes again, when we can take another march, which it would be as perilous
                  as unpleasant to do in the daytime!"</p>
               <p>"Can we find shelter there?" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#volumina">Volumina</persName>, looking at the
                  ruins.</p>
               <p>"Oh, no!" replied <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>. "There is no cover there that is not well known to every
                  wandering native of the whole district. Now, it strikes me, as we are going to
                  make a halt for some time, the best place we can get into will be among the
                  tangled bushes down yonder. They rise, as you all see, some four or five feet from
                  the ground; and, by reposing among them, we may remain quie quiet till nightfall.
                  What say you, brother?"</p>
               <p>"It is a good plan, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>, and you and I, too, can mount guard alternately, in case of
                  a surprise!"</p>
               <p>"Here goes, then," added <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                     >Caesar</persName>, "for a but of exploration before you all come. I will look
                  out for a snug place; and when I hold up my gun, with a handkerchief, you can come
                  down to me. You will easily see the signal, for the morning is coming on
                  rapidly.:</p>
               <p>It was indeed so. In long silent flushes of light, the sweet and lovely Indian
                  morn was sweeping on, awakening thousands of insect things, and scaring into their
                  lairs the larger and more savage denizens of the woods, whose habits are
                  nocturnal. The jackall, with faint cries, slunk to its den. The spotted snake
                  coiled iself up in its cool retreat, and the night birds, with strange shrieking
                  calls, dived deep into the woods. Another flush of the new sunlight, and the tips
                  of the leaves of the tallest trees were sparkled with gold, as they swayed in the
                  soft air--then another, and the old ruins, the bushes, the far-off landscape, and
                  all hill and dale, were clothed in the glorious light of day. The gauzy mists flew
                  up like so many curtains from the valley, and dissipated into thin air; and as the
                  sad and weary party looked into each other's pale and anxious faces, their eyes
                  blinked at the flood of light that the prodigality of nature poured upon them.</p>
               <p>"Halloa!" cried a voice.</p>
               <p>"Ah, that is <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                  >Caesar</persName>!" said the <roleName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName>; "and see, he
                  waves his signal to us! Let us join him, for doubtless he has found a place of
                  comparative safety!"</p>
               <p>Those who were reclining, struggled to their feet; and the ladies, by the aid of
                  the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> and
                  the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant</roleName>--the
                  latter of whom was wonderfully better--essayed the brambly and steep descent, to
                  where <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName> waved
                  his handkerchief on the muzzle of his gun.</p>
               <p>The way was impeded by the wild Indian berry, and <p n="156"/><cb n="1"/>the
                  prickly briar, and a small fruit of the strawberry species, whcih sent its
                  tendrils in all directions; but they found the route wuite as easy as they had
                  expected, and were soon close to <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>, who called out,
                  "Come on--come on! Here's one of the old stone or marble quarries, where the old
                  race<!-- what is this referencing? --> must have got the materials for the remains
                  so often seen in <placeName type="country">India</placeName>."</p>
               <p>The whole party was soon by his side, when a beautiful and interesting sight
                  presented itself.</p>
               <p>They stood on the brink of an abyss of an irregular circular shape, and about two
                  hundred feet, or more, across; while the depth seemed to vary from sixty to eighty
                  feet, to some hundreds. The wild and luxuriant vegetation from the bank had
                  trailed down into the quarry, and there, in many cases, taken root in the fissures
                  of stones, and sent up fresh shoots; so that the whole presented a mass of flowers
                  and wild fruits, alike beautiful to the eye and tempting to the appetite. </p>
               <p>"What a lovely spot!" exclaimed <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName>. "Oh, look at
                  it, dear <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>!
                  Could not one live for ever here!"</p>
               <p>"It is very beautiful!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                     >Annie</persName></p>
               <p>"Yes, said the <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian"
                     >Lieutenant</roleName>. "A <placeName type="building">bungalow</placeName> on
                  this height, with that lovely hollow before it, and one loved being to lend the
                  charm of human sympathy to the spot, and what would one desire more in this world
                  of ours!"</p>
               <p>The <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Lieutenant</roleName>
                  looked at <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie
                     Hope</persName> as he spoke, and the light of love was too evidently sparkling
                  in his eyes, to admit of a doubt with regard to which would be the loved one he
                  would like to grace the solitude.</p>
               <p>"Well!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                  >Caesar</persName>; "by Jove, I should want pale ale and <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#manillas">Manillas</distinct> in abundance, in
                  addition!"</p>
               <p>There was a faint attempt at a smile on the sad faces of the party, and then the
                     <roleName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal">Captain</roleName> said,
                  "There is a rude path down this place, I see, close to us. If it were warranted
                  free from snakes, now, we could not do better than to take shelter in it; for,
                  without doubt, there are many chambers of recesses opening from the sides of this
                  quarry, as there are such in all others I have seen!"</p>
               <p>"Hush!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar"
                  >Caesar</persName>; "listen!"</p>
               <p>They were silent as the grave; and the faint jingling sound of some cavalcade,
                  apparently on the march on the high road, met their ears--now swelling higher in
                  the morning air, and then almost entirely dying away, as though receding to a
                  great distance.</p>
               <p>"What is it?" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrshawkins">Mrs.
                     Hawkins</persName>, faintly. </p>
               <p>"Some Hindoo procession," said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#mrhawkins">Mr. Hawkins</persName>. "A wedding
                  one, I should guess, by the jingle of the <distinct
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#cresset">cresset</distinct>-shaped bells. </p>
               <p>"A wedding!" exclaimed the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#missflint"
                     >Hon. Miss Flint</persName>: "how interesting!"</p>
               <p>The sounds came nearer and nearer, and nearer still; <cb n="2"/>and then they
                  heard a wild, shrill blast, from some horn of native manufacture, and the firing
                  of muskets. </p>
               <p>"Be this what it may," said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#hannibal"
                     >Captain Hawkins</persName>, "it behoves<!--sic--> us all to get into a place
                  of safety as quicjly as we can, for they can be no friends to us!"</p>
               <p>"Yes--yes! Let us hide!" cried every one.</p>
               <p>"Follow me, then! I see the rude path cut in the stony side of the quarry.
                  On!--on!"</p>
               <p>"Death!--death!--death to the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>!" yellwed a voice
                  at this moment; and, upon casting their eyes in the direction whence it came, they
                  saw a wild-looking figure in Hindoo costume--or, rather, no costume--standing,
                  waving its arms, in an exulting fashion, on the ridge they had just left by the
                  side of the road.</p>
               <p>"All right! By Jove, I had him!" cried <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#caesar">Caesar</persName>, as he fired a
                  revolver; and, with a hideous shriek, the Sepoy plunged headlong from the ridge,
                  and rolled over and over, clutching, with the agony of death, the long trailing
                  flowers!</p>

               <p>
                  <emph>(To be continued in our next)</emph>
               </p>

            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
