<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model hcorresp="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!--<?xml-model hcorresp="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<!--
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/xsl" href="../xsl/rymer.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet title="Rymer" type="text/css" href="../style.css" alternate="yes"?>
-->

      <!-- very much work in progress on header -->

<?xml-model href="../schema/sepoys.schema.xml" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Sepoys; Or, Highland Jessie: an electronic edition</title>
            <author corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#JMR">James Malcolm Rymer</author>
            <editor corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#RN">Rebecca Nesvet</editor>
            <editor corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#RXY">Rae X. Yan</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Rebecca Nesvet</publisher>
            <publisher>Rae X. Yan</publisher>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <idno>sepoys</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct xml:id="installment1" prev="sepoys.frontmatter.xml#frontmatter"
               next="sepoys.2.20.xml#installment2">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter I: The Assembly Room at Cawnpore</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-02-13"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Reynolds's Miscellany</title>
                  <title level="a">Chapter II: The Midnight Revel of Nana Sahib</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <!-- Date of publication of source -->
                     <date when="1858-02-13"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <!-- Information about the encoding of the text -->
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Information about the project itself (goals, organization, activities)</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Information about how the texts in a collection were chosen or excerpted</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="unknown">
               <p>Information about treatment of errors in the source (silently corrected, etc.)</p>
            </correction>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Information about normalization practices (e.g. treatment of roman numerals,
                  spelling, etc.)</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation form="std">
               <p>Information about treatment of quotations (preservation of original quotation
                  marks, etc.)</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="hard">
               <p>Treatment of the hyphenation of the source</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>Information about whether and how the text has been segmented (mostly for
                  linguistic purposes)</p>
            </segmentation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Information about any interpretive information added to the text</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="installment">
            <head><date when="1858-02-13">Saturday, February 13, 1858</date></head>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="facsimiles/sepoys.2.13.png"/>
            </figure>
            <pb n="81"/>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <head>THE <orgName type="indian">SEPOYS</orgName>; OR, <persName
                  corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jessie">HIGHLAND JESSIE</persName>.</head>
            <head>A TALE OF THE PRESENT INDIAN REVOLT.</head>
            <head>BY <persName type="pseudo">M. J. ERRYM</persName>.</head>
            <head>AUTHOR OF "<title>JANE BRIGHTWELL</title>," "<title>THE SNOW-DRIFT</title>,"
               ETC.</head>
            <p>[Given a faithful Account of the Perils and Adventures of Two Families in <placeName
                  type="country">India</placeName>—the Private and Public life of <persName
                  corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName></persName>, and numerous
               romantic Episodes of Rebellion, from authentic and exclusive sources.]</p>
            <p>The romantic and exciting character of the events in <placeName type="country"
                  >India</placeName>, both public and private, are here woven into a <cb n="2"/>
               narrative, which, while it borrowsa little from imagination, presents in a more
               personal shape than the records of history, events and occurrences which far
               transcend all that the pages of old romance could hope to present to its readers. The
               political and public incidents of the Indian Revolt will be the stream, in the
               current of which will be carried forward the individuals whose adventures we shall
               pourtray. The names we introduce are not the names of the actual parties, for obvious
               reasons; but the incidents themselves are derived from the most veritable sources;
               and it is presumed that so deeply interesting a leaf from the great volume of
               existence never yet spread its regard before human gaze.</p>
            <cb n="3"/>

            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch1">CHAPTER I.</head>
               <head>THE <placeName type="building">ASSEMBLY ROOM</placeName> AT <placeName
                     type="city">CAWNPORE</placeName>.</head>
               <p>Clinging to each other with the frantic grasp of despair—uncertainty and fear upon
                  every countenance—blanched cheeks and trembling limbs, bespeaking the terror of
                  those throbbing hearts—eyes quivering through tears of agonised apprehension, as
                  they cast their hurried glances from door to window, and then from face to face of
                  the poor horror-stricken throng; listening with an agony of dread for any sound
                  from without, striving with a preternatural eagerness to separate the sobs and
                  moans of children from all extraneous noises—silent and hopeless, with the slant
                     <cb n="1"/> beams <pb n="82"/> of an Indian moon tipping with silver the torn
                  apparel, and giving a spiritual character to the wan faces—stood, sat, and clung,
                  breast to breast, or knelt apart and prayed, the throng of victims in the
                     <placeName type="building">Assembly Room</placeName> at <placeName type="city"
                     >Cawnpore</placeName>, on the eve of that awful day when Hindoo treachery had
                  gathered back its victims after the capitulation of the few and faint defenders of
                     <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>.</p>
               <p>There crouched the mother—clasping to her heart the little ones wailing for food,
                  and dabbled with the blood of the father who had fallen in their defense—despair
                  on her face, terror of yet unheard-of horrors to come, in her eyes.</p>
               <p>There the maiden in the first flush and pride of her girlish beauty, so pale and
                  wan, the very fount of tears dried up with the wild terror of the past, and the
                  dread of the still more terrible future! Where are the fond hearts that love her?
                  where the tender arms that would enfold her from even the winds of heaven, should
                  they visit her cheek too roughly? where is the gallant lover who has looked to her
                  as the star in the East, by the light of which he hoped to march to flory and
                  renown? Not there! not there!—where she like a pale spectra, with those clasped
                  hands and that faint moaning sound from her lips, awaits her dreadful doom.</p>
               <p>Wives—sisters—gentle little ones, who have but yet, through their blue eyes,
                  peeped at the great world, which so soon for them is to pass away for ever;—young,
                  fair children, with the sweet cherub faces of English youth, and the soft voices
                  of our own happy clime—beings of love, and to be beloved, with all the wild
                  idolatry of human passion;—beauty, gentleness—every charm that, in the fairest and
                  the tenderest portion of humanity, graces nature,—all are there—picturesque, yet
                  awful in their despair!</p>
               <p>Do not pitying angels crowd those latticed casements and gaze with the ineffable
                  love of a higher state on these poor victims? Is there no cheering murmur from a
                  world to come, whence cruelty and oppression are unknown, since all hope is
                  quenched in this? Oh! it was a sight to make angels weep, if tears are still the
                  inheritance of the starry host! </p>
               <p>And higher, and higher still, rose in the soft blue of that Indian sky, the full,
                  round moon, and a flood of silvery light glistened upon the tears of those who had
                  them to shed; and the murmured prayer, yet faintly uttered, seemed as though it
                  took that moonlight path to heaven.</p>
               <p>"Hush! What sound is that?"</p>
               <p>A shrill, clarion-like burst of eastern music. The clash of cymbals, and the whirr
                  of the many-stringed <emph><foreign xml:lang="ur"
                        corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#eeda">eeda</foreign></emph> , with the hoarse
                  rattle of drums, comes on the soft night air.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana <roleName type="honorific"
                        corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName></persName> holds high
                  revel in his gorgeous halls at <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>.</p>
               <p>Then, the mothers clasp their little ones yet closer to their hearts. Then the
                  young maidens sink to the floor, their breath coming short and thick; and there is
                  wringing of hands, and there are frantic prayers, and cries of help, where help
                  there is none—for mercy, which comes not.</p>
               <p>Loudly clash the cymbals again! The monotonous beat of the Indian drum falls as
                  though each tap was on some poor victim's heart! A blaze of yellow light mingles
                  with the moonbeams, and the shouts of many voices awaken echo in the blood-stained
                  streets of the city.</p>
               <p>"Death! Death to the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>!" is the cry.
                  "Long life to the lord of the earth—the conqueror of nations—<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana <roleName type="honorific"
                        corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName></persName>!"</p>
               <p>Then, with the bray of trumpets—the confused clatter of arms—the crashing of the
                  cymbals—the jingle of the silver-belled <emph><foreign xml:lang="ur"
                        corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#chunar">chunar</foreign></emph>, and the tap!
                  tap! of the drums—there sweeps past the <placeName type="building">Assembly
                     House</placeName>, bearing hundreds of torches, a confused mass of the <orgName
                     type="indian">Sepoy</orgName> guard of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana <roleName type="honorific"
                        corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName></persName>, bent on a
                  visit, propitiatory and thankful, to one of the Hindoo temples in the
                  vicinity.</p>
               <p>And now, as the rabble band neared the prison-house of these sad victims we have
                  fairly touched upon there is one who, in her despair—for she thinks the destroyer
                  is at hand—shrieks aloud. Another, in vain, tries to take her own life—for death,
                  simply death, has lost its horrors in higher horrors still. A third bemoans her
                  fate, in bitter anguished words, which keep up a strange cadence with the clash of
                  barbarous sounds without.</p>
               <p>"Oh, mercy, heaven! Why is all this? What have we done, to be so lost? So happy
                  were we in our dear home—kind kindred about us—every word a sound of true
                  affection—life so dear, so beautiful to us all! The earth so beautiful—the sky so
                  blue and fair! Each day but the harbinger of new happiness!—and now, death!
                  death!—worse than death! Help! help!—mercy! help! Father!—mother!—brother! In
                  mercy help me!—save me! Will you all leave me here to die? Help—Oh, help!"</p>
               <p>The intellect had tottered and fallen, and the young <cb n="2"/>girl—for such she
                  was—screamed with the wild energy of a maniac.</p>
               <p>Then another sat mute and smiled; she was mad! Before her eyes a father and two
                  brothers had fallen, and heaven spared her further woe. She was weaving a strange
                  kind of chapel from some Indian grasses that, by chance, were in the place; but
                  one glance at those cold, stony-looking eyes were enough to freeze the heart.</p>
               <p>The music still sounded, but more remotely, although the tramp of feet continued.
                  Suddenly, then, there was a crashing sound, and some splinters of the jalousies of
                  the windows were scattered into the room, and several shots plunged into the walls
                  and ceiling.</p>
               <p>In wanton mischief, as they passed, some of the <orgName xml:lang="ur"
                     type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> had fired into the <placeName type="building"
                     >Assembly Room</placeName>, where they knew the English prisoners were
                  confined.</p>
               <p>And now all crouched low down, as by an instinct which teaches that death, however
                  inevitable it may seem, is yet to be avoided, if possible, to the last. All was
                  still, too, except the moaning of some children, and the painful throbbing of
                  every heart there. Another—yet another shot, and the splinters from the windows
                  flew about the room. Another yet—and there is a faint cry. All eyes are turned in
                  that direction, and in the moonbeams they see a stream of blood. The bullet has
                  found its home in one fair breast, and soon death is an inhabitant of that fearful
                  place.</p>
               <p>Then broke forth the cries that will no longer be suppressed, and there is a rush
                  to the doors of the apartment. They are fast, and the <orgName type="indian"
                     >Sepoy</orgName> guard without laugh at the puny efforts to force them. But
                  still the very walls shake with the frantic efforts of so many hands, and then one
                  of the guards fires a shot through the door, and it wounds two of the victims
                  fearfully. They recoil from the door, and as a young mother finds blood upon her
                  child, she shrieks aloud for the aid, and makes frantic efforts to stanch the
                  stream of life which is flowing fast. </p>
               <p>Then from a remote corner, where they had stood clasped in each other's arms, come
                  forward two sisters. The eldest is but on the verge of womanhood, although the
                  wife of a <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#fletcher">Major
                     Fletcher</persName>, who is with the army; a young child of three year of age
                  is clinging around her neck. Her sister, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName>—on whose fair
                  brow but sixteen summer had shone—clings closely to her, and with gasping sobs
                  rather strives to keep her back then aid her in making her way to the centre of
                  the desolate throng, which seems to be <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>'s object. The
                  latter, however, perseveres, and although tears are streaming from her eyes, and
                  she is half-choked by emotions, she speaks.</p>
               <p>"Dear friends, all!—dear in misfortune, and dearer still in this dreadful time—oh!
                  be patient! Do not—oh! do not let us abandon ourselves, if we have no hope
                  elsewhere! What but more certain and dreadful destruction can we expect by clamour
                  and by resistance here? Oh, be still and patient! I cannot—will not think we are
                  wholly lost! The retribution for any ill that could be done to us will surely make
                  even <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana <roleName
                        type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                     >Sahib</roleName></persName> tremble to corresplect upon. Oh! be hopeful, and
                  do not let us exhaust our poor hearts in useless efforts! We are not lost yet, for
                  we live!"</p>
               <p>These words spread a calm over the troubled souls there present. They were spoken
                  with such a holy sweetness, and they came from one whom they all knew suffered
                  much and had much at stake. The screams and cries ceased, and many a mother strove
                  to hush her little ones to rest.</p>
               <p>Then <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName>,
                  as she sobbed upon her sister's breast, murmured to her, "Oh, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>! <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>! you know that—that
                  our foes are not all cruel, not all so barbarous and vengeful. There is one in
                  whom, could he but know of our abandonment, we might yet have hope."</p>
               <p>"Hush, sister, hush! Do not sob so!"</p>
               <p>"But, dear <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>,
                  you know who I mean! It is strange that his name and the thought of him has ever
                  been on this dreadful eve uppermost in my mind."</p>
               <p>"You mean <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur
                     Ahib</persName>, the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young chivalrous chieftain</roleName>
                  from the mountains?"</p>
               <p>"Ah, yes!"</p>
               <p>"Alas, my poor <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>, he is of different mould to these <orgName xml:lang="ur"
                     type="indian">Sepoys</orgName>, who are working all this ruin!"</p>
               <p>"But yet is with them! Oh, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                     >Annie</persName>! I thought I saw his plume in the throng, and as I looked I
                  saw a confusion on the shore when many were firing at the boats, and it was he who
                  pressed aside the weapons, and I saw him striving to stop the carnage. He has some
                  wild notions of the deliverance of <placeName type="country">India</placeName>
                  from all foreign rule, and that will place him in the ranks against us; but his
                  noble heart will make him the sworn foe to all cruelty and bloodshed. Listen,
                  sister—I have yet hope in him!"</p>
               <p>"Alas! alas! my poor <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>! What hope?"</p>
               <p>"He loves me!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>
                  clasped closer to her side her young sister, and wept.</p>
               <p>"Yes, he loves me!" sobbed <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie Hope</persName>. "You <cb n="3"/> know our poor father thought much of
                  him, and had him often to the bungalow, and did you not see how he would sit and
                  gaze at me, with such love in his dark eyes, that I was fain to leave the room to
                  recover their ardent gaze? Oh, yes, he loves me! and he is no coward, cruel
                     <orgName type="indian">Sepoy</orgName>! He belongs to a different race, as we
                  have often heard our dear father say! Listen! you have seen him on his horse, have
                  you not, with his chain-mail glittering in the sun? Oh, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>! <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>! if we could only let
                  him know—if he could but guess that we—I was here, he would save us yet! Yes, dear
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>, he would
                  save us yet!"</p>
               <p>"Hush! oh, hush, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>! How you sob! Be calm! be calm, for the love of heaven! I
                  would fain hope with you, if I had dared; but, alas! how is one arm to save us,
                  even if it wished, with thousands raised against us?"</p>
               <p>"Oh, but he is so brave, so food, so true!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName> bent down her
                  head, and kissed her sister through her tears.</p>
               <p>"My poor, poor <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>! may heaven keep you!"</p>
               <p>"Hush! Ah, what is that?—this way! Listen! Oh, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>, God is good and
                  merciful! If I could only speak—speak, for tears! This way, to the window, here! I
                  heard something!"</p>
               <p>"What? Oh, what!"</p>
               <p>"Hush!—hush!—hush!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie Hope</persName> was too
                  agitated to say more; but she led her sister to a corner of the large apartment,
                  where a window, latticed with thin jalousies, let in the slant rays of the moon.
                  None were at that part of the room but themselves; and when they reached it,
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName> heard the
                  faint tickle of one of those small Indian lutes that are in use all over
                     <placeName type="country">Hindostan</placeName>.</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName> clung to her
                  sister with a clutch that was painful, and she sobbed now as though her heart
                  would break.</p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, dear
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie">Bessie</persName>, what is
                  it? Oh, what is it?"</p>
               <p>"He—he!—God bless and aid him!—<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur"
                     >Jeffur</persName>—'tis he! He will save us yet! He is so good, so—so noble,
                  and he loves me!"</p>
               <p>The soft tinkle of the lute came quickly on the night air, and then it paused, and
                  a few words in different English were spoken from without in a low soft voice.</p>
               <p>"Is the English angel of the wild heart of the song of the mountains here, or in
                  the paradise of the blessed and the good!"</p>
               <p>"'Tis he!" gasped <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>, with a half shriek of delight. "Oh, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>, we shall see them
                  all again! Our mother—your dear
                     <persName>Edward</persName><!-- who is Edward!? in 2.27, Annie says her husband's name is George, not sure if Edward is supposed to be Major Fletcher -->—<persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#adrian">Adrian</persName>—all friends! We are
                  saved!"</p>
               <p>The lute again was gently touched.</p>
               <p>The prospect of deliverance now indeed began to dawn on the hopes of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs. Fletcher</persName>, and the
                  mother's first impulse was to cover her child with tears and kisses.
                  "Sister—sister!" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#bessie"
                     >Bessie</persName>, "how shall I let him know that I am here?—that we are here?
                  Oh, yes—yes! I know now! Hush!—be still! Oh, I know he loves me! You have a small
                  knife with you, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie"
                     >Annie</persName>! Give it me! That is well! Oh, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Annie</persName>, these are tears of
                  joy now! I remember once he said my hair was like the clear sunlight of his native
                  hills. He will know it well—he will be sure to know it! We must not cry out, for
                  he would be in danger. One tender, good heart among a thousand fiends! He will
                  know this!—he will know this!"</p>
               <p>The young girl severed from her head one of the long tresses of her beautiful
                  hair, and with trembling fingers she thrust it through the narrow crevices of the
                  jalousies at the window. Then there was a slight cry without of surprise and joy,
                  and they heard fervent kisses bestowed upon the lock of hair. The lute was struck
                  just for a few seconds in a joyous strain, and then all was still.</p>
               <p>The sisters knelt by the window in intense listening; not another sound came to
                  their ears from without.</p>
               <p>"All is lost!" sighed <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#annie">Mrs.
                     Fletcher</persName>. "He cannot help us!"</p>
               <p>"He will help us," said Annie, "for he loves me!"</p>
            </div>

            <div type="chapter">
               <head xml:id="Ch2">CHAPTER II.</head>
               <head>THE MIDNIGHT REVEL OF <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">NANA
                        <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                        >SAHIB</roleName></persName>.</head>
               <p>In the <placeName type="building">great hall</placeName> of the palace at
                     <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>, beneath a canopy of state, and
                  surrounded by all the gorgeous pomp of eastern magnificence, hastily collected and
                  so strangely intercomingled that the place looked like a plundered bazaar, sat
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana <roleName
                        type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                     >Sahib</roleName></persName>.</p>
               <p>Rich cloths covered the floor. The plunder of the <placeName type="building"
                     >Residency</placeName>, in the shape of plate, uniforms, arms, and European
                  luxuries lay strewn about in confusion. The extemporaneous canopy at one end of
                  the apartment was supported by tall spears, and formed of shawls and tapestries of
                  rare beauty, and cost. Beneath was a wilderness of embroidered cushions, forming a
                  huge divan, on which, with the favorites of the hour, sat the arch-spirit of
                  cruelty. His dress was blazing with <pb n="83"/>
                  <cb n="1"/> jewels, and the splashes of blood were on every article of his
                  apparel; his bloodshot eyes looked implacable as a tiger's in their rage; his
                  naked scimetar lay before him, and an European pair of richly mounted pistols was
                  in his girdle. Close to his right hand lay a revolver of the highest finish, which
                  had been found in the <placeName type="building">Residency</placeName>.</p>
               <p>Reposing on the cushions about him, and which straggled over a third portion of
                  the hall, were his officers, arrayed partly in European spoils. All were fully
                  armed, and at the feet of most of them lay a pile of weapons, which ever and anon
                  they fingered and examined with interest and attention. </p>
               <p>A vast throng of soldiers of all conditions filled up the lower portion of the
                  hall, and the rattle of arms and the din of vices, above which could now and then
                  be heard the cry of "Long live the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"><roleName type="honorific"
                        corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName></persName>!" were
                  incessant.</p>
               <p>Close behind the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>
                  were several attendants, bearing rich wines on golden salvers, to which he
                  frequently appealed, generally flinging the goblet or crystal from which he drank
                  far down the hall, or over his head among those behind him. A blaze of light was
                  produced from a hundred torches of scented wood; and now and then, on a sign from
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lolltall">Loll Tall</persName>, the
                  present minister of the petty satrap, a clangor of wild music would fill the air,
                  and the clash of the cymbal with the roll of the European drum made up a most
                  martial discord.</p>
               <p>The scene was, in truth, a strange and a gorgeous one of wild barbaric pomp. The
                  flashing of the flambeaux on the arms and jewels—the hum of the multitude—the
                  crashing sound of the music—the glitter of arms and accoutrements, and the flutter
                  and sparkling beauty of the rich Oriental hangings—all made a semblance to the
                  past magnificence of old <placeName type="country">India</placeName> in the height
                  of her native power and glory.</p>
               <p>And evidences, too, were there of the recent battle, in which the troops of the
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> had been
                  worsted by <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#havelock"
                     >Havelock</persName>, and forced, flying and disordered, back to <placeName
                     type="city">Cawnpore</placeName> but a few short hours before. There were drops
                  of blood upon many a gorgeous vest, and bound-up heads and arms, and blanched
                  faces even among those immediately surrounding the Chief. But wine had done much
                  of its work, and was doing more. A wild revel—the last in <placeName type="city"
                     >Cawnpore</placeName> before its evacuation—was on hand, and with all the rage
                  of recent defeat and present semi-intoxication, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana <roleName type="honorific"
                        corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName></persName> presided
                  at the fell orgies of the night.</p>
               <p>"Wine! wine!" he cried. "Death to the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>! Blood shall flow
                  till the sacred <geogName type="river">Ganges</geogName> is tinted with the
                  crimson life-stream! Wine, I say! more wine!"</p>
               <p>The startled attendance who was nearest to him presented, tremblingly, the salver
                  with a golden goblet on it; but his foot caught slightly in one of the fusions of
                  the divan, and in his stumble he spilt some of the wine on the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>.</p>
               <p>With a howl of rage, the latter seized the scimitar at his feet, and made a
                  furious slash at the peon.</p>
               <p>"<emph><foreign xml:lang="ur" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#chor"
                     >Chor</foreign></emph> (thief)!" he said; and the sword drunk deep of the
                  life-blood of the gasping wretch, who rolled back among his fellows.</p>
               <p>"Wine, I say! wine! Ah! 'tis well! This is new blood!"</p>
               <p>He drained the goblet to the bottom that was now presented to him, and then
                  drawing a long breath, he glanced around him ere he flung it furiously at the
                  figure of a crouching Hindoo, who was apparently muttering his prayers.</p>
               <p>"Dog!" he cried, "bring me the goblet back again, and let me fill it with your
                  blood!"</p>
               <p>A gaunt figure, the upper portion of which was entirely nude, strode forward with
                  the goblet, and making a low salaam, said, "I am your highness's dog, but I bite
                  others!"</p>
               <p>"Ah! the executioner of <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>! Is it not
                  so?"</p>
               <p>"Even so, <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Light of my
                     Eyes</addName>, and <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Terror of
                     the World</addName>!"</p>
               <p>"More sport!" shrieked the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana</persName>, "more sport! We have no dancing fair ones to night! Ha! ha!
                  The war has scared the bright eyes and the supple limbs, but there is other sport!
                  Sit thou there, friend! We shall want thy cunning hand! Wine here! said I not
                  wine? Ah, that is rich and rare! Why, there is blood upon my caftan! It looks
                  well, too! Defeated—defeated, are we? Well, well! such defeats are costly to the
                     <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>! Ah, the foe! But
                  yet, ere I go, a deed!—a deed! Ha! ha! there will be tears yet—tears of blood!
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lolltall">Loll Tall</persName>?</p>
               <p>"Ay, my good lord!"</p>
               <p>"The <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName> women!—eh?"</p>
               <p>He jerked his head in the direction of the <placeName type="building">Assembly
                     House</placeName>.</p>
               <p>"Safely confined," whispered the minister.</p>
               <p>The <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> drew a long
                  breath. "'Tis well! These that can get there will sup to-morrow in Paradise!"</p>
               <p>The cymbals and the drums again struck up their <cb n="2"/> wild music, and the
                  wine circulated still more freely! The <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="indian"
                     >Sepoys</orgName> at the lower pat of the hall uttered loud shouts, and now and
                  then, one more intoxicated than his fellows would sally out and fire his musket in
                  the streets. Still, the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana</persName> drunk deeply; and after a potation, he suddenly fixed his eyes
                  upon the youthful and handsome countenance of a splendidly-attired warrior in the
                  fanciful costume of the hill tribes, with his buckler slung at his back, who had
                  approached close to the divan.</p>
               <p>"Ah! I should have known thee!—I saw thy plume in the fight!"</p>
               <p>"<persName><roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                        >Sahib</roleName></persName>! I am <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur Ahib</persName>, son of the
                  chief of the <orgName type="indian" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#dooctees"
                     >Dooctees</orgName> of <geogFeat type="hills"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#dooctees">the hills</geogFeat>! I have fought
                  for you!"</p>
               <p>"By our beard, yes! Wine, wine here, for our good soldier! Death to the <orgName
                     xml:lang="ur" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee"
                  >Feringhee</orgName>!"</p>
               <p>"To <placeName type="country">India</placeName>!" cried <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, as he partook
                  sparingly of the cup presented to him. "<persName><roleName type="honorific"
                        corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName></persName>, all
                  should revel alike. Shall I relieve the guard at the <placeName type="building"
                     >Assembly Room</placeName>, where lie the <orgName xml:lang="ur"
                     type="european" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>
                  women and children, prisoners?"</p>
               <p>The <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young
                     chief</roleName> trembled slightly as he spoke, and the reeling eyes of the
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> glared upon
                  him. The suspicious character of the savage was aroused at he knew not what.
                  Moreover he was asked to do something which should have been his own thought, and
                  thecorrespore it was not to be done.</p>
               <p>"No, no! Great is the valor of our friend from <geogFeat type="hills"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#dooctees">the hills</geogFeat>, and we love to
                  have him near us! There is room on our divan for a warrior. Sit with us!"</p>
               <p>The parted lips and the show of teeth from the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> belied his hospitable
                  words, and to those who knew him well betokened anything but good to the chivalric
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, who, in
                  the name of <placeName type="country">India</placeName> alone, had taken up arms,
                  and who was so ill-suited for companionship with those around him, who fought for
                  plunder and revenge.</p>
               <p>"The <persName corresp="sepoys.personograhy.xml#nana"><roleName type="honorific"
                        corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName></persName>'s words
                  are good!" said <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">the young chief</roleName>, as he
                  calmly and gracefully reclined on the cushions near the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>. But there was trouble
                  in the ye of the young man, and there was sadness at his heart! How to save her he
                  loved, was the anxious question of his soul. Had he succeeded in obtaining the
                  command of the relief guard over the prisoners, all would have been easy; but now
                  his powers of action were more restricted than before, and his heart felt faint
                  and fluttering as he clasped his hand with a nervous clutch upon the bullion
                  tassel of the velvet cushion on which he half reclined. </p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana <roleName type="honorific"
                        corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName></persName> looked at
                  him with a searching glance, and then, as his head reeled to and fro in incipient
                  intoxication, he whispered, as he thought, but, in reality, spoke sufficiently
                  aloud for all near at hand to hear, to <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lolltall">Loll Tall</persName>, "Double the
                  guard on the prisoners! Fire on all who approach without the watchword! The dawn
                  will come!—the dawn will come!"</p>
               <p>"And the watchword, Light of the World?" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lolltall">Loll Tall</persName>.</p>
               <p>The <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young
                     mountain chief</roleName> strained his sense of hearing to the utmost; but
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana <roleName
                        type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                     >Sahib</roleName></persName> grabbed <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lolltall">Loll Tall</persName> by the neck,
                  and said a word in his ear, which the nicest attention of the young man could not
                  catch. </p>
               <p>"It is well!" said the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lolltall">Loll
                     Tall</persName>. "Words of wisdom fall like pearls from my lord's lips."</p>
               <p>The <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> burst into a
                  hideous laugh, and then he called for more wine, and glanced at <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>, as he yelled, "Who
                  held back vengeance from the sons of <placeName type="country">India</placeName>?
                  Ah! what say you?"</p>
               <p>The executioner had whispered something close to the ear of the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>, and the countenance of
                  the latter literally flushed through the dark skin with pleasure.</p>
               <p>"Say you so? Prisoners! Nay!"</p>
               <p>"Even so, my good lord."</p>
               <p>He clapped his hands loudly, and, in a yelling voice, shouted, "More lights! more
                  music! more revelling! more wine! more blood! Ha! ha! Prisoners? We live, and some
                  of the hated race live! By the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#grandlaama">Grand Laama</persName>, the air is
                  impure in <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName> while the breath of the
                     <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName> taints it! Bring
                  in the prisoners! A hunt!--a hunt! Better than the wild haunts of the jungle will
                  be the halls of <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>! Better the game than
                  the tiger or the jackal! Bring in the prisoners! we hold a feast to-night, and we
                  invite the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>! Ha! ha! We have
                  had the pale devil before in our halls! The prisoners! Bring in the prisoners!
                  Why, we are conquerors, yet!"</p>
               <p>Amid the bray of wind instruments--the clash of cymbals, and the beat of
                  drums--while countless flambeaux, lit from all quarters, made the <placeName
                     type="building">hall</placeName> a dazzling scene of light--an <roleName
                     type="military">English officer</roleName>, his uniform torn, and dabbled in
                  blood, was thrust from the lower part of the <placeName type="building"
                     >hall</placeName> towards <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana <roleName type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                        >Sahib</roleName></persName>.</p>
               <p>"Wretch!" shrieked the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana</persName>. "Know ye your fate? Know you your judge? On your knees,
                     <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="european"
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#feringhee">Feringhee</orgName>! On your knees,
                  and beg the life--you shall not get!" he added, in a hoarse whisper.</p>
               <p>The officer looked calmly and proudly in the face of the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>. He pointed with his
                  outstretched hand at the guilty wretch, and there was an awe-struck stillness in
                  the hall as he spoke.</p>
               <cb n="3"/>
               <p>"Perjured villain!--double-dyed murderer!--wretch without human heart or human
                  feeling!--I, unarmed and helpless, in the name of my country and my kindred, yet
                  defy you! Beware, <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana <roleName
                        type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                     >Sahib</roleName></persName>! for the hour of retribution will come!
                  Treacherous as the tiger--more loathsome than the serpent--"</p>
               <p>The <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> sprung to
                  his feet with a roar of rage, and then fell back again on the cushions. He grasped
                  the revolver, and, without the slightest regard to those in the background of the
                     <placeName type="building">hall</placeName>, he fired at the officer two shots,
                  in rapid succession. Cries and shouts from those hit--for both the bullets missed
                  their intended victim--mingled with the concussion of the reports, and the clang
                  of the cymbals. The fire of desperation flashed from the eyes of the officer, and
                  he sprung upon a gigantic <orgName type="indian">Sepoy</orgName> guard, and
                  wrested from him his tulwar. To cut down two men who opposed him, and to rush
                  towards the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>, was
                  the work of a moment. Fifty swords sprung from their scabbards, and such a clash
                  of weapons around one man never yet startled the night air. The <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> rolled backward over
                  the pile of cushions, and then discharged both his pistols from his gorgeous sash
                  right into the middle of the throng at a venture, for he had dropped the revolver. </p>
               <p>The the clash of swords ceased. There was a parting of the mob of <orgName
                     type="indian">Sepoy</orgName> officers and soldiers; and four bodies lay on the
                  blood-stained <placeName type="building">hall</placeName>--while some half-dozen
                  others, dropping blood as they went, tottered to the embrasures of the windows,
                  and the cushions that strewed the place.</p>
               <p>The officer lay still in death, with fifty mortal wounds upon him, and a sad, calm
                  smile upon his face.</p>
               <p>The <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> crouched
                  upon the cushions, like some wild animal of his native jungles, preparing for a
                  spring. His hand clutched deeply the velvet, and his bleared and bloodshot eyes
                  glared over the blazing gold edges of the richly embroidered divan.</p>
               <p>"Away with the carrion!" he roared. "Away with it! More spoil to-night! The last
                  in <placeName type="city">Cawnpore</placeName>! Curses on them all! Are you women,
                  that you are nearly beaten by a single man? Cowards! More prisoners--more
                  prisoners! Bring in more!--slay! I--I--Stay, yet a moment. By <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#vishnu">Vishnu</persName>, we are all mortal!
                  Arms! arms! That is well-well! Our life is that of <placeName type="country"
                     >India</placeName>! We have yet work to do!"</p>
               <p>Some ten or twelve pistols were reverently handed to the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>, who formed before him
                  a sort of breast-work of the embroidered cushions, on which he laid them, and then
                  trying--with his vision imperfect from his deep potations--to pierce the distance,
                  he waited the approach of the other prisoners. </p>
               <p>A <roleName type="military">private</roleName>, in a regiment of the line, was,
                  with kicks and cuffs, forced into the hall.</p>
               <p>"Silence, all! Cease the music!" shouted <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana <roleName type="honorific"
                        corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName></persName>; and then,
                  seeing the rank of his prisoner, he seemed to fancy that, before ordering him to
                  death, it might be possible to extract valuable information from him.</p>
               <p>"Dog!" he cried, "approach!"</p>
               <p>The prisoner did not move; and when the <orgName xml:lang="ur" type="indian"
                     >Sepoys</orgName> urged him forward, he cried out in unmistakable brogue,
                     "<distinct type="irishdialect">Arrah, thin, it's one of ye's the ould sinner is
                     after wanting, for it's dog he says, says he! And mighty bad-looking curs you
                     are!</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"Approach, villain!" yelled the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana</persName>.</p>
               <p>"There, now," said <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">the
                     Irishman</addName>, "did ye hear the likes o' that, now? There's so many of ye,
                  that it must be the biggest blackguard of the whole lot he's after wanting."</p>
               <p>Kicked, and cuffed, and, indeed, wounded by spears and tulwars, the poor soldier
                  was forced forward to the front of the divan; and then, <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana <roleName type="honorific"
                        corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib">Sahib</roleName></persName>, with a
                  loaded pistol in each hand, showed all his teeth, like an enraged wolf, as he
                  said, in what he intended should be encouraging accents, "You want your life?
                  Answer me what I ask. You want to live?"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="irishdialect">Faith, thin, we all live till we die, any
                     way.</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"A wise speech! What shall we do for you?"</p>
               <p>"Do for me? It's pretty well done for, I take it, myself is at this present time
                  of asking; but a male of victuals, a small taste of whisky, a good-bye to you, and
                  the likes of you, would be mighty agreeable!"</p>
               <p>"Give him <distinct type="indianslang" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#bang"
                     >bang</distinct>"--(an intoxicating liquor made from hemp). "Give him <distinct
                     type="indianslang" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#bang">bang</distinct>--and
                  his tongue will loosen."</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="indianslang" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#bang"
                  >bang</distinct>, is it? It's a mighty lot of bangs and whacks, too, you and your
                  heathens have been after giving me already! Twenty <placeName
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#donnybrook">Donnybrook fairs</placeName> is a
                  fool to it, all rolled into one! Oh, it's something to drink, is it? And it's this
                  you call bang? Well, here's mighty bad luck to the whole of you, and may the devil
                  fly away wid you to the place that isn't glory, as soon as his honour has time to
                  do it! <distinct type="indianslang" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#bang"
                     >bang</distinct>, is it? Ah! it's mighty poor drink, it is--a trile better than
                  nothing at all!"</p>
               <p>"Speak now!" said the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana</persName>. "How many soldiers has your general? <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#havelock">Havelock</persName> they call
                  him!"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="scotsdialect"><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis"
                        >Dennis</persName>, my mon</distinct>," said a voice from the lower end of
                  the hall, in the national vernacular of <placeName type="country"
                     >Scotland</placeName>,<pb n="84"/>
                  <cb n="1"/>"<dialect type="scotsdialect">you'll no be for telling the brute
                     onything about the force, you ken!</dialect>"</p>
               <p>"<dialect type="irishdialect">Is it myself, <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Sandy M'Laren</persName>, that's a
                     goose on a common?</dialect>" said <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>.</p>
               <p>"Who spoke there?" growled the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana</persName>.</p>
               <p>"<addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Lord of the World</addName>, the
                  other prisoner," said an officer.</p>
               <p>"Shoot him! Clear a space down yonder, and shoot him in the <placeName
                     type="building">hall</placeName>! Then fling out the body to the vultures!"</p>
               <p>The <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> himself
                  began to handle his pistols so suspiciously, that an open space down the hall was
                  cleared in a moment, in which stood a <roleName type="military"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Highland soldier</roleName>, in a
                  torn and blood-stained uniform. The attitude of the man was proud and defiant.</p>
               <p>"<dialect type="scotsdialect">Fire," he cried, "if you dare, ye black-looking,
                     ill-faured loons; but you dare not do it!</dialect>"</p>
               <p>"Fire!" shouted the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana</persName>.</p>
               <p>There was a miscellaneous discharge of fire-arms, and when the smoke cleared away,
                  the <roleName type="military" corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Highland
                     soldier</roleName> lay motionless on the floor of the
                     <placeName>hall</placeName>. A sign from an officer, and a couple of <orgName
                     xml:lang="ur" type="indian">Sepoys</orgName> bore out the body and cast it into
                  a hollow at the back of the <placeName type="building">compound</placeName>. They
                  had not left him above two minutes, when the supposed dead <addName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy">Highlander</addName> sat up, and
                  giving a rub to the top of his head, he said, "<dialect type="scotsdialect">'Deed,
                     then, that was a close touch! It's weel to go doon before you are hit, when you
                     can! The chiel that fights and get's awa', is good to fight among them
                     a'!</dialect>"</p>
               <p>With this remark, the <addName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#sandy"
                     >Highlander</addName> bent double, to avoid being seen by the <orgName
                     type="indian">Sepoy</orgName> sentinels, and ran along the covered way in the
                  direction of the <placeName type="warfront">British lines</placeName>.</p>
               <p>Little suspecting the escape of one of his victims, the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>, in a soft, persuasive
                  voice, although thickened by his deep potations, proceeded to question poor
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>.</p>
               <p>"Tell me," he said, "and spare your own life: how many men and guns has your
                  chief?"</p>
               <p>"It's how many?"</p>
               <p>"Yes--how many?"</p>
               <p>"The number you want to know?"</p>
               <p>"Wretch! Yes--the number?"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="irishdialects">It's rank and file what the boys all comes to when
                     tould off?</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"Dog!"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="irishdialects">Oh, by the saints! it's his dog he has lost, after
                     all! What's his name, ould gentleman, and I'll whistle for him? Is it Snap, or
                     Pincher?</distinct>"</p>
               <p>The <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> half rose
                  from the divan, and deliberately placing a pistol within two feet of <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>'s head, he said,
                  through his clenched teeth, "Answer me, or I fire!"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="irishdialects">Hould hard!" cried <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>; "an', if I tell
                     yer, will you swear, by the bad saints of
                        <!-- what does Ingy refer to? --><orgName>Ingy</orgName>, that you'll be
                     peaceful, and not be blazing away the mother's son of me?</distinct>"</p>
               <p>"By <persName corresp="seapoys.backmatter.xml#vishnu">Vishnu</persName>! <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#dowga">Dowga</persName>! <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#siva">Siva</persName>!--by <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#kalee">Kalee</persName> and by <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#budda">Budda</persName>, I swear!"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="irishdialects">It's a mighty big oath to hear," said <persName
                        corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis">Dennis</persName>, "Well, this
                     I'll tell ye. There's four hundred and seventy thousand and twenty-seven, all
                     from the <placeName type="country">Emerald Isle</placeName>; and a big gun to
                     every twenty-one men as knows how to fire it off any way.</distinct>"</p>
               <p>At this moment the sullen boom of cannon in the distance came upon the night air.
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana <roleName
                        type="honorific" corresp="sepoys.backmatter.xml#sahib"
                     >Sahib</roleName></persName> let his arm slowly drop, and listened.</p>
               <p>"What was that?"</p>
               <p>"<distinct type="irishdialects">Some o' the big guns I made bould to spake
                     of,</distinct>" said <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis"
                     >Dennis</persName>.</p>
               <p>"Silence, on your life! Remove him!--remove him, I say! We have sworn not to kill
                  him with our own hand! We--ha! ha!--Remove him!"</p>
               <p>The <orgName type="indian">Sepoy</orgName> guard crowded round <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#dennis"> Dennis</persName>, and he was
                  hustled from the <placeName type="building">hall</placeName>. The executioner,
                  with a lounging step, followed.</p>
               <p>The <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName> now passed
                  his hand across his brow, as though he would fain dissipate the fumes of the wine
                  which had mounted to his brain, and he struggled to his feet. Again, the sullen
                  sound of cannon shook the air, and his face turned a shade darker, as he leant
                  heavily on the shoulder of the <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lolltall">Loll Tall</persName>.</p>
               <p>"They come! they come!" he said, "Blood tracks their path and mine! War to the
                  death! They or I! They come!--the avenging band!--and, as they think, to deliver
                  and to rescue. Ha! ha! they chase us from <placeName type="city"
                     >Cawnpore</placeName>--they press onward to victory! But <placeName
                     type="country">India</placeName> is large, and has he forests and her
                  hills--her morasses and her arid plains--her gods and her temples--her vengeful
                  hearts and sharp swords! They will enter <placeName type="city"
                     >Cawnpore</placeName>, but not as deliverers! They will chase me from the city,
                  but not as saviours of the lives of those they seek! Blood shall be found, but not
                  running vital through human veins. Stagnant all--and staining the walls and floors
                  of the prison-house! Revenge! revenge! That shall be the Hindoo watchword!
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lolltall">Loll
                  Tall</persName>!"</p>
               <p>"My gracious lord."</p>
               <p>"Ha! ha! ha!"</p>
               <p>The laugh was a hideous contortion.</p>
               <cb n="2"/>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lolltall">Loll Tall</persName>!"</p>
               <p>"Light of the Earth!"</p>
               <p>"I--ha! ha!--I have prisoners in the <placeName type="building">Assembly
                     House</placeName>. Women--helpless women--mere helpless children--ha! ha!
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lolltall">Loll Tall</persName>--my
                  friend!"</p>
               <p>He clutched the minister by the neck and whispered to him. <persName
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lolltall">Loll Tall's</persName> knees shook
                  as he gasped, "All? all?"</p>
               <p>"All!" screamed the <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana"
                     >Nana</persName>; and then, in a deep guttural voice, he added, "Remember! by
                  the first light! The <placeName type="building">well</placeName>! the <placeName
                     type="building">well</placeName>! the <placeName type="building"
                     >well</placeName>!"</p>
               <p><persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#lolltall">Loll Tall</persName>
                  salaamed low.</p>
               <p>The boom of the cannon again sounded.</p>
               <p>"<persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>!" said the
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#nana">Nana</persName>: "where is
                     <persName corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">Jeffur</persName>?"</p>
               <p>All looked around him; but the <roleName type="honorific"
                     corresp="sepoys.personography.xml#jeffur">young mountain chief</roleName> had
                  disappeared amid the smoke and tumult of the firing at the Highland soldiers.</p>
               <p><emph>(To be continued in our next.</emph></p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
